const arr = [{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the best test for the diagnosis of malaria?","answers":[{"option":"Microbiological culture","bool":false},{"option":"Thick and thin film","bool":true},{"option":"Serologic test","bool":false},{"option":"Enzyme-linked immunoassay (ELISA) test","bool":false},{"option":"Pap smear","bool":false}],"id":0},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which system reaches the functional state first in the embryo?","answers":[{"option":"Nervous","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory","bool":false},{"option":"Excretory","bool":false},{"option":"Cardiovascular","bool":true},{"option":"Skeletal","bool":false}],"id":1},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Where does red infarct usually occur in?","answers":[{"option":"Venous occlusion","bool":true},{"option":"Arterial occlusion","bool":false},{"option":"Heart","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false}],"id":2},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is covered by pseudostratified columnar epithelium?","answers":[{"option":"Pharyngeal tonsil","bool":true},{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Lingual tonsil","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Palatine tonsil","bool":false}],"id":3},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which malarial parasite causes severe malaria?","answers":[{"option":"Plasmodium malariae","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmodium vivax","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmodium knowlesi","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmodium ovale","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmodium falciparum","bool":true}],"id":4},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Erythropoietin is primarily formed in which organ?","answers":[{"option":"Kidneys","bool":true},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Brain","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false}],"id":5},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Through which process do reticulocytes enter peripheral blood circulation from bone marrow?","answers":[{"option":"Phagocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Margination","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Diapedesis","bool":true},{"option":"Pinocytosis","bool":false}],"id":6},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 13-year-old female presents to the outpatient department (OPD) with on and off menorrhagia, bleeding gums, and petechial rashes. Her laboratory reports show the following results; Hb= 12.5 g/dl, platelet count= 350,000/mm3, activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT)= 49s (normal: 29-40s). Which of the following could be the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombotic microangiopathy","bool":false}],"id":7},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2021","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 5-year-old boy comes to the outpatient department complaining of a painful and swollen knee. On examination, bleeding is seen within the knee joint but with no signs of physical trauma. His mother gives a family history of a maternal uncle who recently died of a bleeding disorder. Investigations show isolated increased APTT. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia C","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":false}],"id":8},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2021","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"The red pulp of the spleen contains which one of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Cords of bilroth","bool":true},{"option":"Central arteriole","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"PALS (periarteriolar lymphoid sheaths)","bool":false}],"id":9},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following drugs is an inhibitor of ADP-induced platelet aggregation?","answers":[{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":true},{"option":"Tirofiban","bool":false},{"option":"Abciximab","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":10},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which drug is used for the reversal of heparin?","answers":[{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Protamine sulfate","bool":true},{"option":"Bivalirudin","bool":false},{"option":"Enoxaparin","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false}],"id":11},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the normal percentage of neutrophils in the adult human?","answers":[{"option":"20 - 30%","bool":false},{"option":"0 - 10%","bool":false},{"option":"30 - 40%","bool":false},{"option":"60 - 70%","bool":true},{"option":"80 - 90%","bool":false}],"id":12},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"The sensorimotor stage of a child's development is during which period?","answers":[{"option":"1 to 2 years","bool":false},{"option":"2 to 4 years","bool":false},{"option":"Birth to 4 years","bool":false},{"option":"Birth to 6 months","bool":false},{"option":"Birth to 2 years","bool":true}],"id":13},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is prolonged by the administration of low-dose heparin?","answers":[{"option":"Activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT)","bool":true},{"option":"Clotting time","bool":false},{"option":"Bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin time (PT)","bool":false},{"option":"Bleeding time and prothrombin time (PT)","bool":false}],"id":14},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What is the first step for an outbreak investigation?","answers":[{"option":"Verification of diagnosis","bool":true},{"option":"Hypothesize","bool":false},{"option":"Case definition","bool":false},{"option":"Communicating findings","bool":false},{"option":"Test hypothesis","bool":false}],"id":15},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"What is the composition of hemoglobin A (HbA)?","answers":[{"option":"α2, γ2","bool":false},{"option":"α2, β2","bool":true},{"option":"α2, δ2","bool":false},{"option":"β2, γ2","bool":false},{"option":"γ2, ε2","bool":false}],"id":16},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"What is the composition of hemoglobin F (HbF)?","answers":[{"option":"α2, β2","bool":false},{"option":"γ2, ε2","bool":false},{"option":"β2, γ2","bool":false},{"option":"α2, γ2","bool":true},{"option":"α2, δ2","bool":false}],"id":17},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following is the best non-invasive diagnostic test for iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Total iron-binding capacity test","bool":false},{"option":"Serum ferritin","bool":true},{"option":"Lipid profile","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood culture (CBC)","bool":false},{"option":"HbA1c test","bool":false}],"id":18},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Mild hypochromic microcytic anemia is associated with which of the following pathologies?","answers":[{"option":"Hemoglobin H disease","bool":false},{"option":"Diamond-Blackfan anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha-thalassemia minor","bool":true},{"option":"Beta-thalassemia major","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":false}],"id":19},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of these act as an opsonin?","answers":[{"option":"C3a","bool":false},{"option":"Fc portion of IgG","bool":true},{"option":"Leukotriene B4","bool":false},{"option":"C5a","bool":false},{"option":"Cytokines","bool":false}],"id":20},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following cells are involved in the formation of epithelioid cells and giant cells in granulomatous inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"B cells","bool":false},{"option":"T cells","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Epithelial cells","bool":false}],"id":21},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which parasite causes blackwater fever and cerebral malaria?","answers":[{"option":"Plasmodium vivax","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmodium falciparum","bool":true},{"option":"Plasmodium ovale","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmodium malariae","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmodium knowlesi","bool":false}],"id":22},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Where are white infarcts usually seen?","answers":[{"option":"Testes","bool":false},{"option":"Lungs","bool":false},{"option":"Ovaries","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":true},{"option":"Small intestine","bool":false}],"id":23},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Erythropoietin is mainly produced in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":true},{"option":"Adrenal gland","bool":false}],"id":24},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"The specialized epithelium is present in which of the following lymphoid organ?","answers":[{"option":"Thymus","bool":true},{"option":"Tonsils","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphoid tissue","bool":false}],"id":25},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Major cationic protein is present in the granules of which cell?","answers":[{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true}],"id":26},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following substances is a plasminogen activator inhibitor?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Urokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Aminocaproic acid","bool":true}],"id":27},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is involved in the inhibition of chemotaxis?","answers":[{"option":"Tumor necrosis factor(TNF) and Interleukin-1","bool":false},{"option":"Lipoxin","bool":true},{"option":"Chemokine","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"C3a and C5a","bool":false}],"id":28},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Leukotrienes are synthesized by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Lipoxygenase","bool":true},{"option":"Cyclooxygenase-1 (COX-1)","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"Phospholipase A2","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclooxygenase 2 (COX-2)","bool":false}],"id":29},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is the incorrect statement regarding granulocytes?","answers":[{"option":"They contain non-specific azurophilic granules","bool":false},{"option":"They contain specific granules","bool":false},{"option":"Granulocytes are also called myeloid cells","bool":false},{"option":"They contain a single nucleus with multiple lobes","bool":false},{"option":"The term polymorph refers to eosinophils","bool":true}],"id":30},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What is the daily requirement for Vitamin B12?","answers":[{"option":"80-100 μg","bool":false},{"option":"10-15 μg","bool":false},{"option":"2-3 μg","bool":true},{"option":"30-35 μg","bool":false},{"option":"0.05-1 μg","bool":false}],"id":31},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements regarding the role of retinoblastoma (Rb) gene during the cell cycle is correct?","answers":[{"option":"It promotes the transition from G2 to M phase","bool":false},{"option":"It inhibits the transition from G2 to M phase","bool":false},{"option":"It promotes the transition from G1 to S phase","bool":false},{"option":"It inhibits the transition from G1 to S phase","bool":true},{"option":"It promotes the transition from M to G₀ phase","bool":false}],"id":32},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is not a part of the vascular events of acute inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Attraction of leukocytes to the site of injury","bool":false},{"option":"Diapedesis","bool":false},{"option":"Migration of endothelial cells","bool":true},{"option":"Increased vascular permeability","bool":false},{"option":"Stasis","bool":false}],"id":33},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which diagnostic test is done for megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Homocysteine levels","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"Methylmalonic acid levels","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin time","bool":false},{"option":"Serum folic acid and B12","bool":true}],"id":34},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following agents directly activates plasminogen?","answers":[{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Tissue plasminogen activator (tPA)","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Urokinase","bool":true}],"id":35},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Protein C and S are involved in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Cleavage of clotting factors","bool":true},{"option":"Enhancing chemotaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Clotting","bool":false},{"option":"Decreasing bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinolysis","bool":false}],"id":36},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which antibody is found in the respiratory and digestive lining, as well as the saliva, tears, and breast milk?","answers":[{"option":"IgM","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":true},{"option":"IgG","bool":false}],"id":37},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Palatine tonsil is derived from which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"1st pharyngeal pouch","bool":false},{"option":"2nd pharyngeal pouch","bool":true},{"option":"3rd pharyngeal arch","bool":false},{"option":"2nd pharyngeal arch","bool":false},{"option":"3rd pharyngeal pouch","bool":false}],"id":38},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"In sickle cell anemia, glutamate at the sixth position of the beta chain of hemoglobin is substituted by which of the following amino acids?","answers":[{"option":"Glycine","bool":false},{"option":"Proline","bool":false},{"option":"Tyrosine","bool":false},{"option":"Lysine","bool":false},{"option":"Valine","bool":true}],"id":39},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Inflammation is a process regulated by several mediators. Which of the following is a negative regulator of inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Thromboxane A2","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotriene B4","bool":false},{"option":"Lipoxin","bool":true},{"option":"Chemokine","bool":false},{"option":"Prostacyclin","bool":false}],"id":40},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Where in the cell are oxygen free radicals formed?","answers":[{"option":"Phagosomes","bool":false},{"option":"Endoplasmic reticulum","bool":false},{"option":"Lysosomes","bool":false},{"option":"Phagolysosomes","bool":true},{"option":"Mitochondria","bool":false}],"id":41},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A patient comes into the outpatient department with signs and symptoms of anemia. Blood smear analysis shows microcytic anemia. Which type of microcytic anemia is associated with reduced ferritin levels?","answers":[{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Lead poisoning","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false}],"id":42},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Symptoms of malaria appear due to the destruction of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":true},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false}],"id":43},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Class I major histocompatibility complex (MHC) molecules are found on the surface of which of the following cells?","answers":[{"option":"B cells","bool":false},{"option":"All nucleated cells","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocytes","bool":false}],"id":44},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is an example of type III immune complex hypersensitivity?","answers":[{"option":"Contact dermatitis","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":true},{"option":"Anaphylaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Goodpasture syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":false}],"id":45},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following conditions would give rise to hypersegmented leukocytes seen on microscopic examination?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Jaundice","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":true}],"id":46},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What is the composition of hemoglobin A or HbA1?","answers":[{"option":"4  beta chains","bool":false},{"option":"1 alpha and 3 beta chains","bool":false},{"option":"3 alpha and 1 beta chain","bool":false},{"option":"2 delta and 2 beta chains","bool":false},{"option":"2 alpha and 2 beta chains","bool":true}],"id":47},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What is the amount of hemoglobin in a 70 kg man?","answers":[{"option":"900 g","bool":true},{"option":"700 g","bool":false},{"option":"500 g","bool":false},{"option":"200 g","bool":false},{"option":"1200 g","bool":false}],"id":48},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of these is the correct composition of hemoglobin Gower 1?","answers":[{"option":"2 alpha and 2 delta chains","bool":false},{"option":"2 zeta and 2 epsilon chains","bool":true},{"option":"2 alpha and 2 epsilon chains","bool":false},{"option":"2 alpha and 2 beta chains","bool":false},{"option":"2 alpha and 2 gamma chains","bool":false}],"id":49},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A patient with liver cirrhosis comes with abdominal distention (ascites). Ascites is due to the low level of protein in the plasma. Which of the following proteins could be low?","answers":[{"option":"Alpha globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":true},{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Gamma globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Microglobulin","bool":false}],"id":50},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Coagulation factors are proteins that flow in the blood in their inactivated form. During a vessel injury, they become activated. Thrombin and thrombomodulin complex inactivates which of the following factors?","answers":[{"option":"V and VIII","bool":true},{"option":"II and III","bool":false},{"option":"IX and X","bool":false},{"option":"IX and VII","bool":false},{"option":"Plasminogen","bool":false}],"id":51},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"What are the substrates of heme synthesis?","answers":[{"option":"Succinyl CoA and glycine","bool":true},{"option":"Acetyl CoA and valine","bool":false},{"option":"Acetyl CoA and glycine","bool":false},{"option":"Succinyl CoA and valine","bool":false},{"option":"Valine and glycine","bool":false}],"id":52},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Extracellular hemoglobin is bound to a plasma protein in order to avoid loss of hemoglobin in urine. Which plasma protein binds free hemoglobin?","answers":[{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Plasminogen","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":true},{"option":"Hepcidin","bool":false}],"id":53},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following statement is correct regarding folic acid and vitamin B12?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin B12 alone takes part in DNA synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 plays a role in purine synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid is essential for the formation of the active form of vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 is essential for the formation of the active form of folic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Folic acid plays a role in pyrimidine synthesis","bool":false}],"id":54},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following types of necrosis is seen in a granulomatous infection by Mycobacterium tuberculosis?","answers":[{"option":"Gangrenous necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinoid necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Caseous granulomatous necrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Liquefactive necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Non-caseating granuloma","bool":false}],"id":55},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What does a bacteriostatic agent do?","answers":[{"option":"Maintains human cell growth rate","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibits the growth of bacteria","bool":true},{"option":"No effect","bool":false},{"option":"Slows viral growth rate","bool":false},{"option":"Increases growth rate","bool":false}],"id":56},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Hemolytic disease of newborn due to Rh incompatibility is caused by which type of hypersensitivity?","answers":[{"option":"Complement mediated","bool":false},{"option":"Anaphylactic","bool":false},{"option":"Contact type","bool":false},{"option":"Cytotoxic","bool":true},{"option":"Immune complex mediated","bool":false}],"id":57},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is a unique stain used in histological studies?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophilia (pink stain) for neutrophil granules","bool":false},{"option":"Basophilia (blue stain) for DNA in ribosomes","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia (red stain) for hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophilia (yellow stain) for hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Azurophilia (purple stain) for lysosome of WBCs","bool":true}],"id":58},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Porphyria results in the accumulation of a unique pattern of intermediates caused by the deficiency of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Intermediate","bool":false},{"option":"Heme","bool":false},{"option":"Glycine","bool":false},{"option":"Succinyl CoA","bool":false},{"option":"Enzyme","bool":true}],"id":59},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Innate immunity is considered to be the first line of defense against many microorganisms. Its major component includes which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"B-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Skin","bool":true}],"id":60},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"A girl comes to the outpatient department with complaints of epistaxis and small bruising on her skin. While giving her history she informs the physician that her sister has the same problem. Laboratory analysis shows that her partial thromboplastin time (PT) and activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) are normal but prolonged bleeding time. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Bernard-Soulier syndrome (BSS)","bool":true},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia C","bool":false}],"id":61},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Raynaud's phenomenon and fibrosis of GI tract, skin, and tissues are symptoms of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Polymyositis","bool":false},{"option":"Marfan's syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic sclerosis","bool":true},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"DiGeorge syndrome","bool":false}],"id":62},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"The special propensity to collect in tissues undergoing allergic reactions is demonstrated by which of the following types of WBCs?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true}],"id":63},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Iron absorption occurs in which part of the gut?","answers":[{"option":"Ileum","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal duodenum","bool":true},{"option":"Colon","bool":false},{"option":"Jejunum","bool":false},{"option":"Stomach","bool":false}],"id":64},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which stage of P. falciparum is crescent shaped?","answers":[{"option":"Oocyte stage","bool":false},{"option":"Sporoite stage","bool":false},{"option":"Ring stage","bool":false},{"option":"Schizont stage","bool":false},{"option":"Gametocyte stage","bool":true}],"id":65},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Most of the iron in the storage pool is in the form of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Apotransferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemosiderin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":true},{"option":"Free iron","bool":false}],"id":66},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"What does heparin activate?","answers":[{"option":"Factor VIII","bool":false},{"option":"Factor XI","bool":false},{"option":"Antithrombin III","bool":true},{"option":"Prothrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombin","bool":false}],"id":67},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"The main contributor to the production of erythropoietin is the kidney. Which of the following is another organ that is also involved in the production of erythropoietin?","answers":[{"option":"Adrenal medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Membranous bone","bool":false},{"option":"Long bone","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":true},{"option":"Adrenal cortex","bool":false}],"id":68},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the first clotting factor that is common in both extrinsic and intrinsic pathway?","answers":[{"option":"Factor II","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V","bool":false},{"option":"Factor IX","bool":false},{"option":"Factor X","bool":true}],"id":69},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following terms refers to the constant presence of a disease or infectious agent within a given geographical area or population group?","answers":[{"option":"Epidemic","bool":false},{"option":"Pandemic","bool":false},{"option":"Exotic","bool":false},{"option":"Endemic","bool":true},{"option":"Sporadic","bool":false}],"id":70},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In hemoglobin S (HbS), which amino acid residue is substituted by valine at the sixth position of the beta-globin chain?","answers":[{"option":"Tyrosine","bool":false},{"option":"Isoleucine","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamate","bool":true},{"option":"Lysine","bool":false},{"option":"Glycine","bool":false}],"id":71},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"The clot is failing to retract. Defect in which of the following would be the likely cause?","answers":[{"option":"Platelets","bool":true},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":false}],"id":72},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Where are most of the body's iron reserves found?","answers":[{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Myoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":true},{"option":"Hemosiderin","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false}],"id":73},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Activation of which of the following factors results in the initiation of the coagulation cascade through the intrinsic pathway?","answers":[{"option":"Factor XII","bool":true},{"option":"Factor IX","bool":false},{"option":"Factor X","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VIII","bool":false}],"id":74},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"A person undergoes ileal resection. After some days he develops weakness, shortness of breath, and anemia. Which anemia can it possibly be?","answers":[{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic blood loss anemia","bool":false}],"id":75},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Myoglobin is a pigment. Which system of the body does it have a role in?","answers":[{"option":"Central nervous system","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatic system","bool":false},{"option":"Electron transport chain","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory system","bool":true},{"option":"Urinary system","bool":false}],"id":76},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Hemostasis is a means of preventing blood loss. Whenever an injury occurs, which one of the following is the first step towards clotting?","answers":[{"option":"Activation of coagulation cascade","bool":false},{"option":"Formation of platelet plug","bool":false},{"option":"Vasoconstriction","bool":true},{"option":"Formation of fibrin plug","bool":false},{"option":"Retraction of the platelet plug","bool":false}],"id":77},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which interleukin is required for the growth and proliferation of all the stem cells?","answers":[{"option":"Interleukin-1","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-2","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-4","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-5","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-3","bool":true}],"id":78},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following mucin antigens is present in both ovarian and breast cancers?","answers":[{"option":"CA19-9","bool":false},{"option":"CA-125","bool":false},{"option":"MUC-1","bool":true},{"option":"Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA)","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":79},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"During the development of the spleen, mesenchymal cells are present between which layers?","answers":[{"option":"The two layers of ventral mesogastrium","bool":false},{"option":"Ventral and dorsal mesogastrium","bool":false},{"option":"Ventral mesogastrium and septum transversarium","bool":false},{"option":"The two layers of dorsal mesogastrium","bool":true},{"option":"Dorsal mesogastrium and septum transversarium","bool":false}],"id":80},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"When the total storage iron is much greater than the apoferritin storage pool, the extra iron is stored in an insoluble form. This form is known as which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Hemosiderin","bool":true},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false}],"id":81},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In case of an injury, a deficiency of which of the following would impair the adhesion of platelets to the subendothelial collagen?","answers":[{"option":"Fibrinogen stabilizing factor","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmin","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand factor","bool":true},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Antithrombin III","bool":false}],"id":82},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is not an example of an antibody-mediated response?","answers":[{"option":"Rh incompatibility at birth","bool":false},{"option":"Drug-induced hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Graft-versus-host disease","bool":true},{"option":"Blood transfusion reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune disease","bool":false}],"id":83},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 13-year-old girl falls and hits her head on the wall, leading to trauma of the blood vessels. Tissue thromboplastin will be released by the endothelial cells. Which of the following factors will be involved in initiating coagulation?","answers":[{"option":"High-molecular-weight kininogen (HMWK)","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":true},{"option":"Factor IX","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V","bool":false},{"option":"Factor XII","bool":false}],"id":84},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is not an antibody-mediated disease?","answers":[{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenia (ITP)","bool":false},{"option":"Asthma","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":true},{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Urticaria","bool":false}],"id":85},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following components are involved in the first step of heme synthesis?","answers":[{"option":"Malonyl CoA and glycine","bool":false},{"option":"Succinyl CoA and glycine","bool":true},{"option":"Malonyl CoA and serine","bool":false},{"option":"Succinyl CoA and serine","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":86},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which antibody has a pentameric structure?","answers":[{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":true}],"id":87},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A girl is brought to the outpatient department with complaints of gum bleeding, and epistaxis. Her complete blood count (CBC) shows a normal platelet count and prolonged bleeding time. There is a family history of a younger sister with easy bruising. What is the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin K deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Drug induced thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":false}],"id":88},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 60-year-old patient comes to the clinic with pain in his leg for over a week. He further adds that due to pain, he could not move his leg. He has now developed deep vein thrombosis in his leg. Which of the following factors is most likely responsible for thrombus formation?","answers":[{"option":"Hypoglycemia","bool":false},{"option":"Pain","bool":false},{"option":"Surgery","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperglycemia","bool":false},{"option":"Immobilization","bool":true}],"id":89},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 5-year-old child, who has a history of eczema, develops rhinitis and develops asthma with seasonal change. What is the most likely change seen on the peripheral blood smear?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophilic leukocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Basophilic leukocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophilic leukocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytosis","bool":false}],"id":90},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 7-year-old boy developed vesicles and bullae on his face and arms due to prolonged sun exposure from participating in sports activities. His father had a similar condition. He is suspected of porphyria cutanea tarda. Which of the following enzymes is mainly deficient in the above-mentioned disease condition?","answers":[{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen carboxylase","bool":false},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen dehydratase","bool":false},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen deaminase","bool":false},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen decarboxylase","bool":true},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen synthase","bool":false}],"id":91},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the region in the primary structure of immunoglobulins that determines the antibody class?","answers":[{"option":"Variable region of heavy chain","bool":false},{"option":"Constant region of heavy chain","bool":true},{"option":"Constant region of light chain","bool":false},{"option":"Hypervariable region of light chain","bool":false},{"option":"Variable region of light chain","bool":false}],"id":92},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"C-reactive protein, which is elevated in case of inflammation and infection, falls into the category of which of the following plasma proteins?","answers":[{"option":"Transport proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma enzymes","bool":false},{"option":"Oncotic proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Acute phase proteins","bool":true},{"option":"Clotting proteins","bool":false}],"id":93},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 55-year-old man was diagnosed with constrictive pericarditis, two years after suffering from trauma to the heart. When he died an autopsy was performed. The heart was encased in a thickened, fibrotic pericardium. The pericardium was attached to the heart by a stingy material that was difficult to remove. What type of inflammation did the patient have in his pericardium?","answers":[{"option":"Purulent","bool":false},{"option":"Catarrhal","bool":false},{"option":"Serous","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinous","bool":true},{"option":"Ulcerative","bool":false}],"id":94},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 65-year-old woman is being treated for pain and inflammation in her joints for the past year. Which of the following statements regarding the patient's inflammation is correct?","answers":[{"option":"It always follows the acute inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"It is predominantly characterized by a neutrophilic infiltrate","bool":false},{"option":"Abscess formation is the hallmark","bool":false},{"option":"It may result in granulomas composed of epithelial cells and blood vessels","bool":false},{"option":"It involves co-existence of inflammation, tissue repair and attempts at repair","bool":true}],"id":95},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"An individual sprains their ankle while hiking in the mountains and it becomes inflamed. Which of the following statements is most correct regarding this type of inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"It is characterized heat, redness, pain and swelling","bool":true},{"option":"It resolves within twenty-four hours","bool":false},{"option":"The cellular infiltrate comprises of macrophages and lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"It is not associated with tissue damage","bool":false},{"option":"It is characterized by the formation of granulomas","bool":false}],"id":96},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"The blood remains in circulation because of a balance between procoagulant and anticoagulant forces. Proteolytic destruction of which of the following by the protein C inhibits the process of coagulation?","answers":[{"option":"Activated factor VII and factor X","bool":false},{"option":"Activated factor V and factor VIII","bool":true},{"option":"Activated factor I and factor IV","bool":false},{"option":"Activated factor X and factor XI","bool":false},{"option":"Activated factor II and factor III","bool":false}],"id":97},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following terms best describes the occurrence of a disease in a community or region with a frequency clearly in excess of normal expectancy?","answers":[{"option":"Sporadic","bool":false},{"option":"Endemic","bool":false},{"option":"Epidemic","bool":true},{"option":"Exotic","bool":false},{"option":"Pandemic","bool":false}],"id":98},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following terms best describes the disease causation model that can be used for explaining the mechanism of chronic disease occurrence like diabetes and heart disease with multiple risk factors?","answers":[{"option":"Wheel of causation","bool":false},{"option":"Epidemiological triangle","bool":false},{"option":"Web of causation","bool":true},{"option":"Determinants of disease","bool":false},{"option":"Dynamics of disease transmission","bool":false}],"id":99},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"The complement system is a system of about 20 different proteins which perform important defensive functions in the body. there are three pathways of complement activation, classical pathway, alternate pathway, and mannose-binding lecithin pathway. These pathways merge at which of the following stages?","answers":[{"option":"Activation of C5a","bool":false},{"option":"Breakdown of C1","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of C3b","bool":true},{"option":"Formation of the membrane attack complex (MAC)","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of C7","bool":false}],"id":100},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 45-year-old woman develops swelling in her lower legs and feet after standing for long periods at the end of her 8-hour shift with no associated pain or erythema. There is no swelling at the beginning of her day. Her kidney and liver are also in healthy condition. What is the probable diagnosis for her condition?","answers":[{"option":"Increased hydrostatic pressure due to heart failure","bool":true},{"option":"Gout","bool":false},{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Renal insufficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Arthritis","bool":false}],"id":101},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which is the characteristic morphology of red blood cells seen in megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Heinz bodies","bool":false},{"option":"Macro-ovalocyte","bool":true},{"option":"Hypersegmented neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Central pallor","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle-shaped red blood cells","bool":false}],"id":102},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which is the characteristic morphology of white blood cells seen in megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Heinz bodies","bool":false},{"option":"Polymorphonuclear neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophilic stippling","bool":false},{"option":"Hypersegmented neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"Megaovalocyte","bool":false}],"id":103},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A child gets a micro-cut on his finger while playing with a razor. The wound stops bleeding shortly after. Which of the following mechanisms is primarily responsible for this?","answers":[{"option":"Fibrin formation","bool":false},{"option":"Vasoconstriction","bool":false},{"option":"Extrinsic pathway","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet plug formation","bool":true},{"option":"Intrinsic pathway","bool":false}],"id":104},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"If the set point for diabetes mellitus in a population was 105 mg/dL and the researcher dropped it to 100 mg/dL. What will be the change in sensitivity and specificity?","answers":[{"option":"Sensitivity increases but specificity decreases","bool":true},{"option":"Only sensitivity increases","bool":false},{"option":"Sensitivity decreases but specificity increases","bool":false},{"option":"No change in sensitivity or specificity","bool":false},{"option":"Only sensitivity decreases","bool":false}],"id":105},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which one of the following is not a vitamin K-dependent factor?","answers":[{"option":"Factor II","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":false},{"option":"Factor IX","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V","bool":true},{"option":"Factor X","bool":false}],"id":106},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which one of the following can be best used to describe erythropoietin?","answers":[{"option":"Enzyme","bool":false},{"option":"Cofactor","bool":false},{"option":"Glycoprotein","bool":true},{"option":"Coenzyme","bool":false},{"option":"Metalloprotein","bool":false}],"id":107},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"How would the CD4 (cluster of differentiation 4) cells be classified as?","answers":[{"option":"Granulocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"T-lymphocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":false},{"option":"B-lymphocytes","bool":false}],"id":108},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following cells become macrophages once they leave the blood circulation to invade the tissue?","answers":[{"option":"Monocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false}],"id":109},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following antibodies has a role in type I hypersensitivity?","answers":[{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":true},{"option":"IgA","bool":false}],"id":110},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following processes are involved In the clotting of blood?","answers":[{"option":"Intrinsic pathway","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic pathway","bool":false},{"option":"Intrinsic pathway and extrinsic pathway","bool":true},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Extrinsic Pathway","bool":false}],"id":111},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following tests would be the most appropriate to be recommended to a person having a thalassemic family member?","answers":[{"option":"Urinalysis","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin A1c","bool":false},{"option":"Hb electrophoresis","bool":true},{"option":"None of them","bool":false}],"id":112},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"What would be the recommended amount of folic acid to be given in thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"6 mg/day","bool":false},{"option":"7 mg/day","bool":false},{"option":"0.5 mg/day","bool":false},{"option":"1 mg/day","bool":true},{"option":"0.1 mg/day","bool":false}],"id":113},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following are among the signs and symptoms of anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Conjunctival redness and pallor","bool":false},{"option":"Conjunctival pallor and tachycardia","bool":true},{"option":"Yellow sclera and bradycardia","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphadenopathy and tachycardia","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphadenopathy and bradycardia","bool":false}],"id":114},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"What does a high reticulocyte count indicate?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Bone marrow abnormality","bool":false},{"option":"B-12 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":115},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"A 17-year-old boy comes to the clinic with complaints of fatigue and shortness of breath. He has had a history of blood transfusions since childhood and his family history is also positive for blood disorders. His laboratory findings are as follows: Reticulocyte count=3%, increased HbF, low Hb, and MCV. What is the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Thalassemia minor","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell disease","bool":false},{"option":"G6PD deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia major","bool":true}],"id":116},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"What is the embryological origin of the spleen?","answers":[{"option":"Mesenchymal tissue","bool":true},{"option":"Mesoderm","bool":false},{"option":"Endoderm","bool":false},{"option":"Ectoderm","bool":false},{"option":"Neuroectoderm","bool":false}],"id":117},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Where is plasminogen released from?","answers":[{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":true},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false}],"id":118},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is incorrect regarding the platelets?","answers":[{"option":"Have a nucleus","bool":true},{"option":"2–3 µm in greatest diameter","bool":false},{"option":"Biconvex discs","bool":false},{"option":"Formed from megakaryocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Not true cells","bool":false}],"id":119},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"What are protein C and S involved in?","answers":[{"option":"Anti-clotting","bool":true},{"option":"Scarring","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Necrosis","bool":false}],"id":120},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"In which of the following disorders is red blood cell count increased?","answers":[{"option":"Leukocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia","bool":true},{"option":"Anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytosis","bool":false}],"id":121},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following have a role in the production of both the interleukin-1 (IL-1) and tumor necrosis factor (TNF)?","answers":[{"option":"Osteoblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Keratinocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false}],"id":122},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Women lose a lot of iron during their menstrual cycles. What is the most common cause of iron loss in men?","answers":[{"option":"Malnutrition","bool":false},{"option":"Physiological demands","bool":false},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false},{"option":"Brain trauma","bool":false},{"option":"GIT bleeding","bool":true}],"id":123},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following cells have lobed nucleus, purple-blue-staining granules in the cytoplasm, and release histamine?","answers":[{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":true},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false}],"id":124},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which one of the following is not a screening test?","answers":[{"option":"Complete blood culture (CBC)","bool":true},{"option":"Prothrombin time (PT) test","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) test","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin time (PT) test and activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) test","bool":false}],"id":125},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which type of necrosis is found in type III hypersensitivity?","answers":[{"option":"Liquefactive necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinoid necrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Caseous necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Fat necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Coagulative necrosis","bool":false}],"id":126},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which one of the following base-pair change is the cause of sickle cell anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Thymine for guanine at 4th codon","bool":false},{"option":"Thymine for adenine at 4th codon","bool":false},{"option":"Thymine for cytosine at 4th codon","bool":false},{"option":"Thymine for adenine at 6th codon","bool":true},{"option":"Thymine for guanine at 6th codon","bool":false}],"id":127},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which one of the following is the most appropriate test for the diagnosis of spherocytosis?","answers":[{"option":"Thyroid profile","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin time","bool":false},{"option":"Osmotic fragility test","bool":true},{"option":"Complete blood culture","bool":false},{"option":"Hb electrophoresis","bool":false}],"id":128},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"What is prevented by giving a test dose of iron dextran solution before administering the remaining intravenous/intramuscular iron dextran injection?","answers":[{"option":"Fever","bool":false},{"option":"Backache","bool":false},{"option":"Headache","bool":false},{"option":"Anaphylaxis","bool":true},{"option":"Vomiting","bool":false}],"id":129},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is an example of type 3 immune complex hypersensitivity?","answers":[{"option":"Contact dermatitis","bool":false},{"option":"Anaphylaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Allergies","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":true},{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false}],"id":130},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"What is incorrect about X-linked agammaglobulinemia?","answers":[{"option":"Premature B-cells do not produce mature B-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Presents with absent or reduced immunoglobulins","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow does not produce premature B-cells","bool":true},{"option":"It is an X-linked recessive disorder with increased frequency in males","bool":false},{"option":"Defect in BTK gene","bool":false}],"id":131},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is the best test for hemolytic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Low LDH","bool":false},{"option":"Low serum haptoglobin","bool":true},{"option":"Low reticulocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Low hematocrit","bool":false},{"option":"Low bilirubin","bool":false}],"id":132},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is not nodulated?","answers":[{"option":"Tonsils","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Thymus","bool":true},{"option":"Lymph node","bool":false}],"id":133},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is included in type II hypersensitivity?","answers":[{"option":"Antibody mediated reaction","bool":true},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Cytotoxic T cells","bool":false},{"option":"Anaphylactic reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Immune complexes deposits","bool":false}],"id":134},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2016"],"question":"Which of the following describes the mechanism of action of warfarin?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibits thrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Acts on hepatocytes to inhibit factor Xa","bool":false},{"option":"Complexes with clotting factors to inhibit thrombus formation","bool":false},{"option":"Acts on hepatocytes and inhibits vitamin K epoxide reductase","bool":true},{"option":"Acts on thrombocytes and inhibits vitamin K epoxide reductase","bool":false}],"id":135},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which one of the following is a plasma mediator?","answers":[{"option":"Histamine and nitric oxide (NO)","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotrienes","bool":false},{"option":"Chemokines","bool":false},{"option":"Complement proteins","bool":true}],"id":136},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"The breakdown of heme produces which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Amino acids","bool":false},{"option":"Globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Bile","bool":false},{"option":"Bilirubin","bool":true}],"id":137},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Heme is broken down in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Liver","bool":true},{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Stomach","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false}],"id":138},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is considered normal bleeding time?","answers":[{"option":"30-50 seconds","bool":false},{"option":"15-20 minutes","bool":false},{"option":"6-20 minutes","bool":false},{"option":"2-5 minutes","bool":true},{"option":"5-10 minutes","bool":false}],"id":139},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is true for hemophilia B?","answers":[{"option":"Can be transmitted from father to daughter","bool":false},{"option":"Is characterized by a marked decrease in coagulation time","bool":false},{"option":"Also called Christmas disease","bool":true},{"option":"Can be treated by anticoagulants","bool":false},{"option":"Is an autosomal disorder","bool":false}],"id":140},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"In which disease is the conjugated bilirubin not being transported outside the liver?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Dubin Johnson syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Gilberts syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Criglar Najjar syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Physiological Jaundice of the newborn","bool":false}],"id":141},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which factor takes part in the intrinsic pathway?","answers":[{"option":"Heparin-like factor","bool":false},{"option":"Rheumatoid factor","bool":false},{"option":"Factor II","bool":false},{"option":"Hageman factor","bool":true},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":false}],"id":142},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is a major plasma protein?","answers":[{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":true},{"option":"Immunoglobulin","bool":false}],"id":143},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following characteristic is INCORRECT about basophils?","answers":[{"option":"Contain major basic proteins","bool":true},{"option":"Releases histamine","bool":false},{"option":"Has basophilic cytoplasm","bool":false},{"option":"Contains blue/purple staining granules","bool":false},{"option":"contains lobed nucleus","bool":false}],"id":144},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is a precursor for plasma cells?","answers":[{"option":"B lymphocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"T lymphocytes","bool":false}],"id":145},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Cytotoxic T cells destroy microbes in which part of the cell?","answers":[{"option":"Smooth endoplasmic reticulum","bool":false},{"option":"Rough endoplasmic reticulum","bool":false},{"option":"Golgi Apparatus","bool":false},{"option":"Cell membrane","bool":false},{"option":"Cytoplasm","bool":true}],"id":146},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which type of antibodies are found in tears and saliva?","answers":[{"option":"IgA","bool":true},{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":false}],"id":147},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Hemolytic anemia is the result of which hypersensitivity reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Type 5","bool":false},{"option":"Type 2","bool":true},{"option":"Type 4","bool":false},{"option":"Type 3","bool":false},{"option":"Type 1","bool":false}],"id":148},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is not an anticancer drug?","answers":[{"option":"Bleomycin","bool":false},{"option":"Etoposide","bool":false},{"option":"Dactinomycin","bool":false},{"option":"Streptomycin","bool":true},{"option":"Vinblastine","bool":false}],"id":149},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Hemopoiesis is production of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Stem cells","bool":false},{"option":"White blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"All blood cells","bool":true}],"id":150},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which anti-TB drug is given parenterally?","answers":[{"option":"Streptomycin","bool":true},{"option":"Isoniazid","bool":false},{"option":"Ethambutol","bool":false},{"option":"Rifampin","bool":false},{"option":"Pyrazinamide","bool":false}],"id":151},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Blood plasma level is maintained by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Plasma proteins","bool":true},{"option":"Estrogen","bool":false},{"option":"Thyroxine","bool":false},{"option":"Testosterone","bool":false},{"option":"RBCs","bool":false}],"id":152},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is the correct statement regarding the cell cycle?","answers":[{"option":"S phase is DNA replication phase","bool":true},{"option":"G2 is the same as the mitotic phase","bool":false},{"option":"I phase is the mitotic phase","bool":false},{"option":"S phase is synthesis of organelles","bool":false},{"option":"G1 is premitotic phase","bool":false}],"id":153},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Primary health care involves which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Justice, equity, resources","bool":false},{"option":"Justice, fairness, ethics","bool":false},{"option":"Planning, effictivness, fairness","bool":false},{"option":"Resources, planning, situation analysis","bool":false},{"option":"Equity, effectiveness, efficiency","bool":true}],"id":154},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"How many amino acids does alpha-hemoglobin have?","answers":[{"option":"141","bool":true},{"option":"118","bool":false},{"option":"115","bool":false},{"option":"184","bool":false},{"option":"162","bool":false}],"id":155},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What are the first identified cells of red blood cells (RBC) series?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombocyte","bool":false},{"option":"Proerythroblasts","bool":true},{"option":"Normoblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Polychromatic erythroblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyte","bool":false}],"id":156},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Radicals are physiologically formed in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Nucleus","bool":false},{"option":"Phagolysosomes","bool":true},{"option":"Mitochondrion","bool":false},{"option":"Proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Cell membrane","bool":false}],"id":157},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Type-1 hypersensitivity involves which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophil","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"Basophil","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"Mast cell","bool":true}],"id":158},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which test is not neccessary in initial diagnosis of hemoglobin deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Blood smear","bool":false},{"option":"WBC count","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet count","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":true},{"option":"RBC indices","bool":false}],"id":159},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which immunosuppressant is also a IL-2 inhibitor?","answers":[{"option":"Mofetil","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclosporine","bool":true},{"option":"Sirolimus","bool":false},{"option":"Daclizumab","bool":false},{"option":"Azathioprine","bool":false}],"id":160},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What does not cause the cobalamin deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Inadequate diet","bool":false},{"option":"Tape worm infection","bool":false},{"option":"Esophagitis","bool":true},{"option":"Pernicious Anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Deficiency of intrinsic factor","bool":false}],"id":161},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following drug is not topical?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Streptomycin","bool":true},{"option":"Nitroglycerin","bool":false},{"option":"Lidocaine","bool":false},{"option":"Estradiol","bool":false}],"id":162},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"In which of the following conditions, round, microcytic, and hypochromic red blood cells are not usually seen in?","answers":[{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Beta thalassemia major","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Beta thalassemia minor","bool":false}],"id":163},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following anti-cancer drug is not a cell cycle specific?","answers":[{"option":"Methotrexate","bool":false},{"option":"Bleomycin","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclophosphamide","bool":true},{"option":"Vinblastine","bool":false},{"option":"Vincristine","bool":false}],"id":164},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"A 32-year-old female presented to OPD with bleeding gums, epistaxis, and non-palpable rashes. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false}],"id":165},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What does anemia in thalassemia lead to?","answers":[{"option":"Convulsions","bool":false},{"option":"Skeletal deformities","bool":true},{"option":"Protuberant abdomen","bool":false},{"option":"Stunted growth","bool":false},{"option":"Genetic mutations","bool":false}],"id":166},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is the gold standard diagnostic test for thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":true},{"option":"Polymerase chain reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Peripheral blood smear","bool":false},{"option":"Red cell distribution width (RDW)","bool":false}],"id":167},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Where does intrinsic factor release from?","answers":[{"option":"Interstitial cells of Cajal","bool":false},{"option":"Pacemaker cells of the GI tract","bool":false},{"option":"Parietal Cells of the stomach","bool":true},{"option":"D1 cells of pancreas","bool":false},{"option":"Interstitial cells of Leydig","bool":false}],"id":168},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is not a common pathway of metastasis?","answers":[{"option":"Local invasion","bool":true},{"option":"Seeding to body cavity","bool":false},{"option":"Seeding to other body surfaces","bool":false},{"option":"Hematogenous spread","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphatic spread","bool":false}],"id":169},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the agents are responsible for causing cancer?","answers":[{"option":"Adenoviruses","bool":false},{"option":"Blood transfusion","bool":false},{"option":"Mutagens","bool":false},{"option":"Nicotine","bool":false},{"option":"Carcinogens","bool":true}],"id":170},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is pyrrole made up of?","answers":[{"option":"2 Succinyl COA","bool":false},{"option":"2 Succinyl CoA + 2 glycine","bool":true},{"option":"2 Glycine","bool":false},{"option":"2 Hb beta chains","bool":false},{"option":"2 Hb alpha chains","bool":false}],"id":171},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"The parents of a child with iron-deficiency anemia are being counseled regarding dietary modifications. Which of the following food items should be added to the diet of this child?","answers":[{"option":"Rice","bool":false},{"option":"Tea","bool":false},{"option":"High-fiber diet","bool":false},{"option":"Citrus fruits","bool":true},{"option":"Legumes","bool":false}],"id":172},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Gastrectomy requires a lifelong administration of what?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin B-6","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin A","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin D","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B-12","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false}],"id":173},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is considered as negative reinforcement?","answers":[{"option":"Punishment will prevent the repetition of behavior","bool":false},{"option":"Punishment will encourage the repetition of positive behavior","bool":false},{"option":"Removal of reward prevent the repetition of behavior","bool":false},{"option":"Removal of painful situation will encourage the repetition of behavior","bool":true},{"option":"Reward will prevent the repetition of negative behavior","bool":false}],"id":174},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is another name for operant conditioning?","answers":[{"option":"Instrumental conditioning","bool":true},{"option":"Classical conditioning","bool":false},{"option":"Pavlovian Conditioning","bool":false},{"option":"Observational learning","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":175},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is not responsible for the tensile strength of a wound during healing?","answers":[{"option":"Collagen cross linking","bool":false},{"option":"Structural collagen modifications","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in the size of collagen fibers","bool":false},{"option":"Collagen fibrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Collagen synthesis","bool":false}],"id":176},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What does a deficiency of C1 esterase inhibitor lead to?","answers":[{"option":"Episodes of edema that never resolve","bool":true},{"option":"Urticaria is a presenting feature","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Delay in immune response","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in anaphylatoxins","bool":false}],"id":177},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is the correct function of Fab fragment of antibodies?","answers":[{"option":"Antigen binding","bool":true},{"option":"Binding to specific proteins","bool":false},{"option":"All of these are functions of Fab","bool":false},{"option":"Binding to cells receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Binding to complement proteins","bool":false}],"id":178},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which one of the following enzymes is dependent on vitamin K to help in the formation of coagulation factors?","answers":[{"option":"Dehydrogenase","bool":false},{"option":"Carboxylase","bool":true},{"option":"Oxidase","bool":false},{"option":"Transferase","bool":false},{"option":"Decarboxylase","bool":false}],"id":179},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"How does cimetidine inhibit warfarin?","answers":[{"option":"By decreasing warfarin metabolism","bool":false},{"option":"Increasing warfarin metabolism/breakdown","bool":true},{"option":"By increasing anticoagulants","bool":false},{"option":"By enhancing erythropoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"By decreasing antithrombin III formation","bool":false}],"id":180},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"All the cells of blood originate from which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Colony forming unit","bool":false},{"option":"Committed stem cells","bool":false},{"option":"Growth and differentiation inducer cells","bool":false},{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Pluripotent hematopoietic stem cells","bool":true}],"id":181},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is the average sum of squares of the deviation about mean, divided by N is called?","answers":[{"option":"Mean deviation","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Variance","bool":true},{"option":"Absolute deviation","bool":false},{"option":"Standard deviation","bool":false}],"id":182},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which drug is bacteriostatic but becomes bactericidal if given in high doses?","answers":[{"option":"Capreomycin","bool":false},{"option":"Isoniazid","bool":false},{"option":"Chloramphenicol","bool":true},{"option":"Pyrazinamide","bool":false},{"option":"Rifampicin","bool":false}],"id":183},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Regarding DiGeorge syndrome, select the inappropriate one:","answers":[{"option":"Defect in 3rd & 4th pharyngeal pouch","bool":false},{"option":"B cell immunodeficiency syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Tetany","bool":false},{"option":"T cell immunodeficiency syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Heart and blood vessel enlargement","bool":false}],"id":184},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is the normal bleeding time in the Duke method?","answers":[{"option":"10-15 minutes","bool":false},{"option":"15-30 seconds","bool":false},{"option":"1-6 minutes","bool":true},{"option":"5-10 minutes","bool":false},{"option":"2-8 minute","bool":false}],"id":185},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Interferon gamma activates which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"T cells","bool":false},{"option":"B cells","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false}],"id":186},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Lymphoid organ with outer darkly staining and inner lightly staining with patches of acidophilic type?","answers":[{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Thymus","bool":true},{"option":"Lymph node","bool":false}],"id":187},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"The thymus is derived from which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"4th pharyngeal pouch","bool":false},{"option":"1st pharyngeal pouch","bool":false},{"option":"3rd pharyngeal pouch","bool":true},{"option":"2nd pharyngeal arch","bool":false},{"option":"5th pharengeal arch","bool":false}],"id":188},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"A person contains both type A and B antibodies. What would his blood group be?","answers":[{"option":"A-","bool":false},{"option":"AB+","bool":false},{"option":"D","bool":false},{"option":"O-","bool":true},{"option":"B+","bool":false}],"id":189},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following vitamins do the clotting factors II, VII, IX, and X depend on for their synthesis?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin E","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin B","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin D","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin A","bool":false}],"id":190},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is the volume of the formed elements in blood?","answers":[{"option":"55%","bool":false},{"option":"28%","bool":false},{"option":"35%","bool":false},{"option":"45%","bool":true},{"option":"33%","bool":false}],"id":191},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is a major source of vitamin K?","answers":[{"option":"Green leafy vegetables","bool":true},{"option":"Mother's milk","bool":false},{"option":"Meat","bool":false},{"option":"Date","bool":false},{"option":"Fish","bool":false}],"id":192},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is not related to inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"COX-1","bool":false},{"option":"Lipoxin","bool":false},{"option":"COX-2","bool":false},{"option":"Thromboxane","bool":true},{"option":"Prostacyclin","bool":false}],"id":193},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is the major function of complement protein C1?","answers":[{"option":"Agglutination","bool":false},{"option":"Binding to Fc IgG and IgM","bool":true},{"option":"Opsonisation","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophil chemotactic agent","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":194},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following induces contraction of endothelial cells to increase vascular permeability?","answers":[{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrin","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine","bool":true},{"option":"Vascular endothelial growth factor","bool":false},{"option":"Serotonin","bool":false}],"id":195},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is wrong regarding Wiskott Aldrich syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"It is X-linked dominant","bool":true},{"option":"Associated with WASP gene","bool":false},{"option":"Causes patches across skin","bool":false},{"option":"It is an immune deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Associated with T-cell defects","bool":false}],"id":196},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which one of the following is not among the main cells that are involved in chronic inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false}],"id":197},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"High amounts of which of these make up the cell walls of the gram-positive bacteria?","answers":[{"option":"Proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Peptidoglycans","bool":true},{"option":"Glycerol phosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Lipopolysaccharide","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":198},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is passive transport?","answers":[{"option":"From low to high gradient","bool":false},{"option":"From high to low gradient using ATP","bool":false},{"option":"From low to high using ATP","bool":false},{"option":"From low to high across a membrane","bool":false},{"option":"From high to low gradient","bool":true}],"id":199},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"A woman took aspirin while being pregnant. What would its effect be?","answers":[{"option":"Gastric ulcer","bool":false},{"option":"Closure of ductus arteriosus","bool":true},{"option":"Post partum hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Congenital Anomalies","bool":false},{"option":"No effect","bool":false}],"id":200},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is major histocompatibility complex (MHC) genes present on?","answers":[{"option":"Short arm of chromosome number 8","bool":false},{"option":"Short arm of chromosome number 13","bool":false},{"option":"Short arm of chromosome number 6","bool":true},{"option":"Long arm of chromosome number 21","bool":false},{"option":"Long arm of chromosome number 4","bool":false}],"id":201},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is the most major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class for transplant determination?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"MHC class II","bool":false},{"option":"MHC class I","bool":true},{"option":"MHC class III","bool":false},{"option":"All of these","bool":false}],"id":202},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which coagulation factor is deficient in hemophilia A?","answers":[{"option":"XI","bool":false},{"option":"VIII","bool":true},{"option":"IX","bool":false},{"option":"II","bool":false},{"option":"V","bool":false}],"id":203},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following are Major histocompatibility complex (MHC) Class II alleles?","answers":[{"option":"HLA-DR, HLA-DQ, HL-C","bool":false},{"option":"HLA-A, HLA-B, HL-C","bool":false},{"option":"HLA-DR, HLA-DQ, HL-DP","bool":true},{"option":"HLA-A, HLB-DQ, HL-DP","bool":false},{"option":"C2, C4, TNF","bool":false}],"id":204},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What do Major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class III loci consists of?","answers":[{"option":"HLA-A, HLA-B, HLA-C","bool":false},{"option":"C2, C4, TNF, LT","bool":true},{"option":"HLA-DP, HLA-DQ, HLA-DR","bool":false},{"option":"HLA-DP, HLA-B, HLA-DR","bool":false},{"option":"C5a, C3a, C4","bool":false}],"id":205},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following are the signs of contact dermatitis?","answers":[{"option":"Skin ulcers","bool":false},{"option":"Uremia","bool":false},{"option":"Inflammation with blisters","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Fever","bool":false}],"id":206},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What is prenatal age?","answers":[{"option":"From 6 months after conception to birth","bool":false},{"option":"From 3 months after conception to birth","bool":false},{"option":"From conception to birth","bool":true},{"option":"After birth","bool":false},{"option":"From birth till 1 year after","bool":false}],"id":207},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is correct regarding erythrocytes?","answers":[{"option":"They consume the oxygen they carry","bool":false},{"option":"They are hemoglobin containing pigments","bool":false},{"option":"They form ATP anaerobically","bool":true},{"option":"Are nucleated cells","bool":false},{"option":"Become macrocytes in infection","bool":false}],"id":208},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Obstructive jaundice leads to the deficiency of:","answers":[{"option":"Ca+2 ions","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B9","bool":false}],"id":209},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Lymphadenopathy is most commonly seen in which of the following regions?","answers":[{"option":"Neck","bool":true},{"option":"Arms","bool":false},{"option":"Head","bool":false},{"option":"Abdomen","bool":false},{"option":"Chest","bool":false}],"id":210},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What defects are found in hereditary spherocytosis?","answers":[{"option":"Improperly formed or weak spectrin, band 3, 4.2, and ankyrin proteins","bool":true},{"option":"Hyperchromic and microcytic red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Hypochromic and microcytic red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperchromic red blood cells and weak spectrin","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":211},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What are ferritin and hemosiderin classified as?","answers":[{"option":"Iron binding proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma iron","bool":false},{"option":"Transport form of iron","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Stored form of iron","bool":true}],"id":212},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is an example of a type IV hypersensitivity reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE)","bool":false},{"option":"Arthus reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Graves disease","bool":false},{"option":"Contact dermatitis","bool":true},{"option":"Serum sickness","bool":false}],"id":213},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which is incorrect about type III hypersensitivity?","answers":[{"option":"Involve antigen-antibody reactions","bool":false},{"option":"Immune complexes formed are in circulation","bool":false},{"option":"They are also formed in extravascular tissues","bool":false},{"option":"Immune complexes are formed only in circulation","bool":true},{"option":"This type of reaction occurs in SLE","bool":false}],"id":214},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"A secondary case is infected by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Quaternary case","bool":false},{"option":"Primary case","bool":true},{"option":"Another secondary case","bool":false},{"option":"Tertiary case","bool":false},{"option":"None of the options are correct","bool":false}],"id":215},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"How would 'index case' be defined?","answers":[{"option":"An average case","bool":false},{"option":"Most symptomatic case","bool":false},{"option":"Least symptomatic case","bool":false},{"option":"First identified case","bool":true},{"option":"Most lethal case","bool":false}],"id":216},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is incorrect regarding secondary immunodeficiencies?","answers":[{"option":"Most common form is AIDS","bool":false},{"option":"Occur later in life","bool":false},{"option":"Result from infections, malnutrition, or treatment","bool":false},{"option":"Can cause an increased incidence of certain cancers","bool":false},{"option":"They are genetically determined","bool":true}],"id":217},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following are involved in type-2 hypersensitivity reactions?","answers":[{"option":"Antigen-antibody complexes","bool":false},{"option":"CD4 cells","bool":false},{"option":"IgE immunoglobulins","bool":false},{"option":"CD8 cells","bool":false},{"option":"IgG immunoglobulins","bool":true}],"id":218},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"What are the antibodies involved in immediate hypersensitivity?","answers":[{"option":"IgE","bool":true},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false}],"id":219},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which drug inhibits the ADP pathway of the platelet aggregation?","answers":[{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":true},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Abciximab","bool":false},{"option":"Tirofiban","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":220},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is an example of gamma globulins in circulation?","answers":[{"option":"Immunoglobulin","bool":true},{"option":"Agglutinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha-fetoprotein (AFP)","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false}],"id":221},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Von Willibrand factor (VWF) is responsible for which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Production of collagen","bool":false},{"option":"Production of cytokines","bool":false},{"option":"Attachment of platelets to endothelial wall","bool":true},{"option":"Repair of endothelium","bool":false},{"option":"Attachment of platelets to each other","bool":false}],"id":222},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is true regarding Bruton's disease?","answers":[{"option":"Is charectarized by defect in phagolysosome synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"B cells are not affected","bool":false},{"option":"Is autosomal dominent","bool":false},{"option":"B cells undergo maturation","bool":false},{"option":"T cells are not affected","bool":true}],"id":223},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following cells' development is impaired in severe combined immunodeficiency (SCID)?","answers":[{"option":"NK cells, B cells and T cells","bool":false},{"option":"NK cells and B cells","bool":false},{"option":"T cells only","bool":false},{"option":"T cells and B cells","bool":true},{"option":"NK cells only","bool":false}],"id":224},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Pick the incorrect statement regarding leukocytes:","answers":[{"option":"They have one multilobed nucleus","bool":false},{"option":"They are nonspecific phagocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages and neutrophils are important phagocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocytes are functionally active in circulation","bool":true},{"option":"Some contain specific granules","bool":false}],"id":225},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Pick the incorrect statement about leukocytes:","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils are polymorph","bool":false},{"option":"Granulocytes can be differentiated by stain","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils are anti-parasitic","bool":false},{"option":"Granulocytes originate from myeloid lineage","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophil specific granules have affinity for methylene blue","bool":true}],"id":226},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is correct about red blood cells (RBCs)?","answers":[{"option":"They contain all usual cellular organelles","bool":false},{"option":"They contain carbonic anhydrase","bool":true},{"option":"Their first stage of development is the reticulocyte","bool":false},{"option":"They are nucleated","bool":false},{"option":"They generate energy primarily via lipolysis","bool":false}],"id":227},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of these is not included in acute inflammation events?","answers":[{"option":"Adherence of neutrophils to endothelium","bool":false},{"option":"Transmigration at arteriolar end","bool":true},{"option":"Chemotaxis of leukocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Increased vascular permeability","bool":false},{"option":"Vasodilation","bool":false}],"id":228},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"What is the embryological origin of the thymus?","answers":[{"option":"4th pharyngeal pouch","bool":false},{"option":"3rd pharyngeal pouch","bool":true},{"option":"1st pharyngeal pouch","bool":false},{"option":"3rd pharyngeal arch","bool":false},{"option":"2nd pharyngeal pouch","bool":false}],"id":229},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"The first step in the clotting mechanism is the formation of the platelet plug. The platelet plug is initially weak. Which of the following is needed to strengthen it?","answers":[{"option":"Prostaglandin","bool":false},{"option":"ATP","bool":false},{"option":"ADP","bool":false},{"option":"Growth factor","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrin stabilizing factor","bool":true}],"id":230},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Coagulation factors are proteins that flow in blood in their inactivated form. During a vessel injury, they become activated. Which of the following factors would be affected by a vitamin K deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"III, IV, XII, X","bool":false},{"option":"V, VIII, X, XI","bool":false},{"option":"II, VII, IX, X","bool":true},{"option":"I, IV, V, IX","bool":false},{"option":"V, IX, XI, XII","bool":false}],"id":231},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Coagulation factors are proteins that flow in blood in their inactivated form and are activated during vessel injury. During liver failure, the absence of which of the following substance contributes to an increased bleeding tendency?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin E","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin A","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":false}],"id":232},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"A 15-year-old girl comes to the outpatient department with a complete blood count (CBC) report that shows RBC count to be 5.5 million/μl, Hb=11.5 g/dL, MCV=60 fL, and normal red cell distribution width (RDW). What test should be done next?","answers":[{"option":"Serum ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow examination","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":true},{"option":"Serum iron/Total iron binding capacity (TIBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Reassure the patient and order no further test","bool":false}],"id":233},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following acts as an opsonin?","answers":[{"option":"C3a","bool":false},{"option":"Fc part of IgG","bool":true},{"option":"Cytokine","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotriene","bool":false},{"option":"C5a","bool":false}],"id":234},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is a strong activator of macrophage?","answers":[{"option":"Transforming growth factor (TGF)","bool":false},{"option":"Interferon gamma (IFNγ)","bool":true},{"option":"IL-10","bool":false},{"option":"Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF)","bool":false},{"option":"IL-4","bool":false}],"id":235},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Vascular leakage caused by the contraction of endothelial cells is mediated by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Histamine","bool":true},{"option":"Tumor necrosis factor (TNF)","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotriene","bool":false},{"option":"C5a","bool":false}],"id":236},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Regarding folic acid and vitamin B12 function in DNA synthesis, which of the following is correct?","answers":[{"option":"Folic acid produces B12","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid produces pyrimidine","bool":false},{"option":"B12 synthesizes folic acid","bool":true},{"option":"B12 alone takes part in DNA synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid produces purine","bool":false}],"id":237},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"In which disease do autoinfarcts occur in the spleen causing the spleen to become shrunken?","answers":[{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell disease","bool":true},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false}],"id":238},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Where does most of the iron bound to transferrin come from?","answers":[{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Hemosiderin","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Absorbed from intestine","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false}],"id":239},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Heme synthesis in erythroid tissue is regulated by which of the following enzymes?","answers":[{"option":"Aminolevulinic acid synthase(ALA synthase)","bool":true},{"option":"Coproporphyrinogen oxidase","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrochelatase","bool":false},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen decarboxylase","bool":false},{"option":"Porphobilinogen deaminase","bool":false}],"id":240},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following lymphoid organs has lobules with an outer darker region and an inner lighter region with concentric acidophilic bodies?","answers":[{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Tonsils","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Thymus","bool":true},{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":false}],"id":241},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"In which disease is uroporphyrinogen decarboxylase deficient?","answers":[{"option":"Hereditary coproporphyria","bool":false},{"option":"Congenital erythroid porphyria","bool":false},{"option":"Acute intermittent porphyria","bool":false},{"option":"Variegate porphyria","bool":false},{"option":"Porphyria cutanea tarda","bool":true}],"id":242},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following chemical mediators causes vasodilation in acute inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"C3a and C5a","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine and NO","bool":true},{"option":"Endothelin","bool":false},{"option":"IL-1 and IL-6","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotriene B4","bool":false}],"id":243},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"In which stage of erythrocyte maturation does hemoglobin formation start?","answers":[{"option":"Orthochromatophilic erythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Basophilic erythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Mature erythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Polychromatophil erythroblast","bool":true},{"option":"Reticulocyte","bool":false}],"id":244},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Erythropoietin is a hormone that promotes hematopoiesis. In which organ is this hormone produced?","answers":[{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":true},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false}],"id":245},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following laboratory studies is the most useful in the diagnosis of iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Normal MCV(mean corpuscular volume) and normal MCH (mean corpuscular hemoglobin)","bool":false},{"option":"Normal MCV(mean corpuscular volume) and high MCH (mean corpuscular hemoglobin)","bool":false},{"option":"Normal MCV (mean corpuscular volume) and low MCH (mean corpuscular hemoglobin)","bool":false},{"option":"High MCV(mean corpuscular volume) and high MCH (mean corpuscular hemoglobin)","bool":false},{"option":"Low MCV (mean corpuscular volume) and low MCH (mean corpuscular hemoglobin)","bool":true}],"id":246},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"What is the term for an epidemic that occurs over countries and continents and in large populations?","answers":[{"option":"Pandemic","bool":true},{"option":"Epizootic","bool":false},{"option":"Eruption","bool":false},{"option":"Endemic","bool":false},{"option":"Outbreak","bool":false}],"id":247},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following word differentiates rate from proportion?","answers":[{"option":"Time","bool":true},{"option":"People","bool":false},{"option":"Part","bool":false},{"option":"Place","bool":false},{"option":"Population","bool":false}],"id":248},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"A 45-year-old woman admitted to the intensive care unit complains of nose bleeding. She is on unfractionated heparin (UFH) treatment for deep venous thrombosis prophylaxis. Laboratory analysis shows normal platelet count and elevated activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT). Which of the following can reverse the toxic effects of heparin?","answers":[{"option":"Alkylating agent","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false},{"option":"Low molecular weight heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Protamine sulfate","bool":true}],"id":249},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which unglycosylated protein affects the osmotic pressure of human plasma?","answers":[{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Transthyretin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":true},{"option":"Ceruloplasmin","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":false}],"id":250},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following statements regarding the cell cycle is true?","answers":[{"option":"In S phase, there is synthesis of organelles","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclins and cyclin-dependent kinases and inhibitors regulate cell cycle","bool":true},{"option":"In mitosis, the entire cell is divided into four daughter cells","bool":false},{"option":"G1 is the premitotic phase","bool":false},{"option":"G2 is the growth phase","bool":false}],"id":251},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is a sign of metastatic cancer in lymph nodes?","answers":[{"option":"Tender and immobile nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Firm and rubbery nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Hard and immobile nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Rubbery and mobile nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Soft and pliable nodes","bool":false}],"id":252},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Plasminogen is released from which of the following cells?","answers":[{"option":"Renal tubule cells","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Endothelial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false}],"id":253},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following has no role in chemotaxis?","answers":[{"option":"IL-8","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandin","bool":true},{"option":"Chemokine","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotriene B4","bool":false},{"option":"C5a","bool":false}],"id":254},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is incorrect regarding reticulocytes?","answers":[{"option":"They are the immature form of erythrocytes released into the blood","bool":false},{"option":"They are stained with supravital staining","bool":false},{"option":"They constitute less than 1% of all blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"They synthesize 50% red blood cell's hemoglobin","bool":true},{"option":"They contain organelles for hemoglobin synthesis","bool":false}],"id":255},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following has the same water and electrolyte balance as blood plasma?","answers":[{"option":"Intracellular fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Synovial fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Extracellular fluid","bool":true},{"option":"Cerebrospinal fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph","bool":false}],"id":256},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Classical conditioning is based on which of the following principles?","answers":[{"option":"Instrumental conditioning","bool":false},{"option":"Skinner conditioning","bool":false},{"option":"Pavlovian conditioning","bool":true},{"option":"Conditioned response","bool":false},{"option":"Higher order conditioning","bool":false}],"id":257},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Platelets are formed from fragments of which of the following cells?","answers":[{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Reticulocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Myeloid cells","bool":false}],"id":258},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Albumin to globulin ratio is an important measure. When albumin concentration in plasma is low, the ratio is lowered and one of its functions is decreased. Which of the following corresponds to that function?","answers":[{"option":"Enzymatic function","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrostatic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Colloid oncotic pressure","bool":true},{"option":"Elasticity of vessel","bool":false}],"id":259},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"A 70-year-old man presents with fatigue and shortness of breath. Upon bone marrow examination, abnormally large red cell precursors are observed. A serum B12 evaluation confirms B12 deficiency. Which of the following will be used to treat the patient?","answers":[{"option":"Filgrastim","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Erythropoietin","bool":false},{"option":"Iron dextran","bool":false},{"option":"Hydroxycobalamin","bool":true}],"id":260},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following activates plasminogen to cause fibrinolysis?","answers":[{"option":"Tissue plasminogen activator","bool":true},{"option":"Enterokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinogen degradation products","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinolysin","bool":false}],"id":261},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following cells are the key markers of chronic inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Immunoblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false}],"id":262},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Tissue damage in chronic inflammation is a result of the action of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"T cells","bool":false},{"option":"B cells","bool":false}],"id":263},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is a feature of red blood cells?","answers":[{"option":"Biconvex shape","bool":false},{"option":"No flexibility","bool":false},{"option":"Myoglobin present","bool":false},{"option":"Mitochondria present","bool":false},{"option":"No nucleus","bool":true}],"id":264},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is used to treat megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Iron dextran","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":true},{"option":"Filgrastim","bool":false},{"option":"Sodium gluconate","bool":false},{"option":"Erythropoietin","bool":false}],"id":265},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following cannot be the cause of iron deficiency anemia in a young girl with irregular menstrual cycles?","answers":[{"option":"Menorrhagia","bool":false},{"option":"Post gastrectomy iron malabsorption","bool":true},{"option":"Increased demands, growth, and pregnancy","bool":false},{"option":"Hookworm","bool":false},{"option":"Blood loss","bool":false}],"id":266},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"According to Piaget's theory, in which of the following stages does a child have animistic thinking and perceives inanimate objects to have wishes, wants, and feelings?","answers":[{"option":"Postnatal stage","bool":false},{"option":"Sensorimotor stage","bool":false},{"option":"Formal operational stage","bool":false},{"option":"Concrete operational stage","bool":false},{"option":"Preoperational stage","bool":true}],"id":267},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is the research methodology in which you move from consequence to exposure?","answers":[{"option":"Cohort study","bool":false},{"option":"Cross-sectional study","bool":false},{"option":"Case-control study","bool":true},{"option":"Interventional study","bool":false},{"option":"Case study","bool":false}],"id":268},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following cells are involved in the formation of giant cells in granulomatous inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Epithelial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"T cells","bool":false},{"option":"B cells","bool":false}],"id":269},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which cells are involved in hypersensitivity type I?","answers":[{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"T cells","bool":false},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":true},{"option":"B cells","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false}],"id":270},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"What antibodies are involved in hypersensitivity type I?","answers":[{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":true},{"option":"IgD","bool":false}],"id":271},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following leads to the presentation of caseous necrosis?","answers":[{"option":"Allergy","bool":false},{"option":"Myasthenia gravis","bool":false},{"option":"Neoplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberculosis","bool":true},{"option":"Reaction","bool":false}],"id":272},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which leukocyte upon entering into the tissue becomes macrophage?","answers":[{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false}],"id":273},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"Which of the following are the signs and symptoms of anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Conjunctiva pallor and tachycardia","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphadenopathy and bradycardia","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphadenopathy and tachycardia","bool":false},{"option":"Conjunctiva redness and skin pallor","bool":false},{"option":"Yellow sclera and bradycardia","bool":false}],"id":274},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2018"],"question":"What is the composition of HbF?","answers":[{"option":"Two alpha, two gamma","bool":true},{"option":"One alpha, two beta","bool":false},{"option":"One alpha, three beta","bool":false},{"option":"One alpha, one beta","bool":false},{"option":"Four alpha","bool":false}],"id":275},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following plasma proteins is involved in the transportation of free fatty acids?","answers":[{"option":"Albumin","bool":true},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Transcobalamin","bool":false},{"option":"Gamma-globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":false}],"id":276},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"An old man is brought to the emergency room in a state of unconsciousness. On examination, it is revealed that he is in a state of anaphylactic shock. Which cells in his body played a role in bringing him to this state?","answers":[{"option":"B-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":true},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Cytotoxic T cells","bool":false},{"option":"Helper T cells","bool":false}],"id":277},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"An old woman comes to the outpatient department and is diagnosed with iron deficiency anemia. Which of the following cells will be seen on her blood smear?","answers":[{"option":"Target cells","bool":false},{"option":"Bite cells","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cells","bool":false},{"option":"Poikilocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Helmet cells","bool":false}],"id":278},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which cells produce lymphokines?","answers":[{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"B-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Helper T cells","bool":true},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false}],"id":279},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following drugs can reverse the effects of heparin?","answers":[{"option":"Alkylating agents","bool":false},{"option":"Protamine sulfate","bool":true},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false}],"id":280},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A woman on warfarin therapy gets pregnant. Which drug should be administered now?","answers":[{"option":"Heparin","bool":true},{"option":"Antithrombin III","bool":false},{"option":"Protamine sulfate","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Continue with warfarin","bool":false}],"id":281},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is responsible for iron absorption from the intestine?","answers":[{"option":"Ceruloplasmin","bool":true},{"option":"Transcobalamin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Hepcidin","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false}],"id":282},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a characteristic of red blood cells?","answers":[{"option":"Biconvex","bool":false},{"option":"No nucleus","bool":true},{"option":"Average volume of 30 femtoliters","bool":false},{"option":"11 micrometer in diameter","bool":false},{"option":"Not flexible","bool":false}],"id":283},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following conditions is seen in megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Hypersegmented eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Hypersegmented erythrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Hyposegmented erythrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Hyposegmented neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Hypersegmented neutrophils","bool":true}],"id":284},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Prolonged administration of vitamin K can cause hemolytic anemia and jaundice in infants due to membrane damage of which of the following cells?","answers":[{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":true},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatocytes","bool":false},{"option":"White blood cells","bool":false}],"id":285},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"B and T cells that recognize self-antigens during their development in the lymphoid organs are destroyed at an early stage. What is this process called?","answers":[{"option":"Induced tolerance","bool":false},{"option":"Peripheral tolerance","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmunity","bool":false},{"option":"Self tolerance","bool":false},{"option":"Central tolerance","bool":true}],"id":286},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is an autoimmune disease?","answers":[{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Thymic aplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Severe combined immunodeficiency (SCID)","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE)","bool":true},{"option":"Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS)","bool":false}],"id":287},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is responsible for the tensile strength of a wound during healing?","answers":[{"option":"Structural collagen modification and thinning of collagen fibers","bool":false},{"option":"Collagen fibrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrosis of wound","bool":false},{"option":"Collagen synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Structural collagen modifications and collagen cross linking","bool":true}],"id":288},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A patient is given oral iron supplements. Which of the following in the diet would increase iron absorption in the gut?","answers":[{"option":"Phosphoric acid","bool":false},{"option":"Tetracyclines","bool":false},{"option":"Ascorbic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Nicotine","bool":false},{"option":"Antacids","bool":false}],"id":289},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following foods cause the best iron absorption in the gut?","answers":[{"option":"Grains","bool":false},{"option":"Tea","bool":false},{"option":"Citrus fruits","bool":true},{"option":"Dry fruits","bool":false},{"option":"Pulses","bool":false}],"id":290},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Monocytes after entering the tissues, swell and become which of the following cells?","answers":[{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":false},{"option":"Histiocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Tissue macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false}],"id":291},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Structures are said to be basophilic if they take which of the following color?","answers":[{"option":"Deep purple","bool":false},{"option":"Pink","bool":false},{"option":"Lilac","bool":false},{"option":"Blue","bool":true},{"option":"Red","bool":false}],"id":292},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Brain tumor cells are formed as a result of overexpression of a platelet-derived growth factor. A mutation in which of the following genes is responsible for this tumor formation?","answers":[{"option":"Proto-oncogene","bool":true},{"option":"Anti-apoptotic gene","bool":false},{"option":"DNA repair gene","bool":false},{"option":"Pro-apoptotic gene","bool":false},{"option":"Tumor suppressor gene","bool":false}],"id":293},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Some inflammatory mediators are cell-derived while others are plasma-derived. Which of the following groups of inflammatory mediators is plasma-derived?","answers":[{"option":"Leukotrienes","bool":false},{"option":"C3a,C4a and C5a","bool":true},{"option":"Histamine and nitric oxide (NO)","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"Chemokines","bool":false}],"id":294},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Mesenchymal cells eventually lead to the formation of blood islands. Which of the following precursor cells play a part in this?","answers":[{"option":"Hemoblast","bool":false},{"option":"Angioblast","bool":true},{"option":"Mesoblast","bool":false},{"option":"Fibroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Definitive heart","bool":false}],"id":295},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the term used to describe the time between attack by an organism and the appearance of the first symptom?","answers":[{"option":"Incubation period","bool":true},{"option":"Latent period","bool":false},{"option":"Asymptomatic period","bool":false},{"option":"Easy period","bool":false},{"option":"Infectious period","bool":false}],"id":296},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"At what angle is the second slide held while preparing a blood smear?","answers":[{"option":"60°","bool":false},{"option":"10°","bool":false},{"option":"45°","bool":true},{"option":"25°","bool":false},{"option":"20°","bool":false}],"id":297},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following blood groups is devoid of both A and B agglutinogens?","answers":[{"option":"ABO","bool":false},{"option":"B","bool":false},{"option":"O","bool":true},{"option":"AB","bool":false},{"option":"A","bool":false}],"id":298},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A first-year medical student performs a blood group test in the physiology lab. He notices blood cells clumping upon the addition of anti-A and anti-B serum to the blood, however, nothing happens when anti-D serum is added. What is the blood group of the blood sample he is testing?","answers":[{"option":"O-positive","bool":false},{"option":"A-negative","bool":false},{"option":"AB-positive","bool":false},{"option":"AB-negative","bool":true},{"option":"O-negative","bool":false}],"id":299},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Interaction of warfarin with which other drug causes excessive bleeding?","answers":[{"option":"Cimetidine","bool":true},{"option":"Protamine sulfate","bool":false},{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false}],"id":300},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Ceruloplasmin transports which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Iron","bool":false},{"option":"Zinc","bool":false},{"option":"Copper","bool":true},{"option":"Oxygen","bool":false}],"id":301},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Chronic diseases may lead to disability and complications. This can be prevented by which level of prevention?","answers":[{"option":"Primary prevention","bool":false},{"option":"Early detection","bool":false},{"option":"Tertiary prevention","bool":true},{"option":"Primordial prevention","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary prevention","bool":false}],"id":302},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Bilirubin is conjugated with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Glucuronyltransferase","bool":false},{"option":"Glucuronic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Biliverdin","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamate","bool":false},{"option":"Glutathione","bool":false}],"id":303},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"The sum of the squared distances of each term in the distribution from the mean, divided by the number of terms in the distribution, is called which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Mean","bool":false},{"option":"Variance","bool":true},{"option":"Standard deviation","bool":false},{"option":"Standard error","bool":false},{"option":"Median","bool":false}],"id":304},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following mediator plays no role in leukocyte recruitment to the blood vessels?","answers":[{"option":"Integrins","bool":false},{"option":"All of these play a role in leukocyte recruitment","bool":false},{"option":"Prostacyclins","bool":false},{"option":"Lipoxins","bool":true},{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false}],"id":305},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following chemical mediators cause vasodilation in acute inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Interleukin-1 and interleukin-6","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotriene B4 and thromboxane A2","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine and nitric oxide","bool":true},{"option":"C3a and C5a","bool":false},{"option":"Chemokines","bool":false}],"id":306},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Hemoglobin A1c (HbA1C) levels are used in the identification of which of the following diseases?","answers":[{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes mellitus","bool":true},{"option":"Malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":307},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Erythropoietin is a hormone that promotes hematopoiesis. Which of the following organ is responsible for its production?","answers":[{"option":"Gall bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":true},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false}],"id":308},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What is the process of production of the solid components of blood called?","answers":[{"option":"Hemopoiesis","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphopoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombopoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"Leukopoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"Erythropoiesis","bool":false}],"id":309},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Lobed nucleus, bluish-purple cytoplasmic granules, and release of histamine are characteristics of which of the following white blood cell?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":true}],"id":310},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is incorrect about central tolerance?","answers":[{"option":"Ensures that mature T-cells don't recognize self-antigens","bool":false},{"option":"Self-antigens can be expressed on thymus epithelial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Lack of central tolerance can result in autoimmune disorders","bool":false},{"option":"Central tolerance occurs only in thymus","bool":true},{"option":"Immature T-cell recognizes self antigens and undergo apoptosis","bool":false}],"id":311},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the best diagnostic test for thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Peripheral blood smear","bool":false},{"option":"Red cell distribution Width (RDW)","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":true},{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Polymerase chain reaction","bool":false}],"id":312},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which cells are involved in hypersensitivity type 1?","answers":[{"option":"Mast cells","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"T cells","bool":false}],"id":313},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What antibodies are involved in hypersensitivity type 1?","answers":[{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":true}],"id":314},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a common mixed tumor of the oral cavity?","answers":[{"option":"Mucosal melanoma","bool":false},{"option":"Tubular adenoma","bool":false},{"option":"Sarcoma","bool":false},{"option":"Pleomorphic adenoma","bool":true},{"option":"Squamous cell carcinoma","bool":false}],"id":315},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common oral cancer?","answers":[{"option":"Papillary adenoma","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Melanoma","bool":false},{"option":"Hematologic tumors","bool":false},{"option":"Squamous cell carcinoma","bool":true}],"id":316},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following best describes carcinoma in situ?","answers":[{"option":"Dysplasia of epithelium without the invasion of basement membrane","bool":true},{"option":"Dysplasia of epithelium with the invasion of basement membrane","bool":false},{"option":"Carcinoma in 1/3rd epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Dysplasia of epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Carcinoma in 2/3rd epithelium","bool":false}],"id":317},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"By what means do white blood cells move through tissue spaces?","answers":[{"option":"Floating","bool":false},{"option":"Extravasation","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Diapedesis","bool":false},{"option":"Amoeboid movement","bool":true}],"id":318},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A woman presents to the outpatient department (OPD) with bleeding gums, epistaxis, and non-palpable rashes. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Von willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet disorder","bool":true}],"id":319},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common oral cancer-causing agent?","answers":[{"option":"Tobacco","bool":true},{"option":"Benzene","bool":false},{"option":"Asbestos","bool":false},{"option":"Arsenic","bool":false},{"option":"Alcohol","bool":false}],"id":320},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following research method is used to describe and evaluate different aspects of a disease?","answers":[{"option":"Hypothetical","bool":false},{"option":"Experimental","bool":false},{"option":"Numerical","bool":false},{"option":"Descriptive","bool":false},{"option":"Observational","bool":true}],"id":321},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a chromoprotein?","answers":[{"option":"Actin and myosin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":true},{"option":"Immunoglobulin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Globulin","bool":false}],"id":322},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A child with a bone marrow disorder is undergoing a blood transfusion. He has also been given 400 ml citrate intravenously to prevent blood clotting. After three transfusions, which of the following conditions will be observed in the child’s blood?","answers":[{"option":"Hypocalcemia","bool":true},{"option":"Hypernatremia","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperkalemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypercalcemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hyponatremia","bool":false}],"id":323},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"In which of the following disease the rate of synthesis of the globin chains is defective?","answers":[{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":true},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobinopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":324},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Immunoglobulins are produced by which of the following cells?","answers":[{"option":"B cells","bool":true},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"T cells","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false}],"id":325},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"In which of the following disorder, antibodies are produced against the body's own immunoglobulin G (IgG)?","answers":[{"option":"DiGeorge syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Anaphylaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes mellitus","bool":false},{"option":"Rheumatoid arthritis","bool":true},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false}],"id":326},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which isotype of antibodies is found on immature B-cells?","answers":[{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":true}],"id":327},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements is true regarding immunoglobulins?","answers":[{"option":"They are formed by helper T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"They are formed by cytotoxic T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"They are formed by B-cells","bool":true},{"option":"They are all monoclonal","bool":false},{"option":"They are formed by thymus","bool":false}],"id":328},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"In porphyrias, which of the following factors is involved?","answers":[{"option":"An excess of inhibitors of heme synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced enzymes of heme synthesis","bool":true},{"option":"An excess of haptoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced intermediates of heme synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced hemoglobin","bool":false}],"id":329},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Interleukin-5 (IL-5) is required for the activation of which of the following cells?","answers":[{"option":"B-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true},{"option":"T-cells","bool":false}],"id":330},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Where is the mean found in a positively skewed data distribution?","answers":[{"option":"Extreme left of the distribution","bool":false},{"option":"Extreme top of the distribution","bool":false},{"option":"Extreme right of the distribution","bool":true},{"option":"Between mean and mode","bool":false},{"option":"Bottom of the distribution","bool":false}],"id":331},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A histologist is studying a blood smear under a microscope. He observes an anucleated, biconcave, disc-shaped cell. Which of the following cells has he observed?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophil","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophage","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocyte","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocyte","bool":true},{"option":"Leukocyte","bool":false}],"id":332},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"How long after birth does the transition from HbF to HbA take place in patients with thalassemia major?","answers":[{"option":"1 year","bool":false},{"option":"1-2 years","bool":false},{"option":"10 years","bool":false},{"option":"1 month","bool":false},{"option":"6-9 months","bool":true}],"id":333},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"In sickle cell anemia, which type of hemoglobin is most useful?","answers":[{"option":"HbA1","bool":false},{"option":"HbF","bool":true},{"option":"HbA2","bool":false},{"option":"HbS","bool":false},{"option":"HbC","bool":false}],"id":334},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the characteristic of a benign tumor?","answers":[{"option":"Metaplastic","bool":false},{"option":"Poorly differentiated","bool":false},{"option":"Well differentiated","bool":true},{"option":"Anaplastic","bool":false},{"option":"Invasive","bool":false}],"id":335},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a characteristic of malignant tumors?","answers":[{"option":"Atrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Anaplasia","bool":true},{"option":"Dysplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperplasia","bool":false}],"id":336},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What is the inheritance pattern of sickle cell anemia?","answers":[{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":true},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Mitochondrial","bool":false}],"id":337},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Classic hemophilia is caused by the deficiency of which of the following factors/parts of factors?","answers":[{"option":"Small part of factor VIII","bool":true},{"option":"Factor XI","bool":false},{"option":"Small part of factor IX","bool":false},{"option":"Large part of factor IX","bool":false},{"option":"Large part of factor VIII","bool":false}],"id":338},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What is the most common cause of iron loss?","answers":[{"option":"Anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Exercise","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic blood loss","bool":true},{"option":"Red blood cell turnover","bool":false},{"option":"Physiological demands","bool":false}],"id":339},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following would be the most useful to test iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Iron profile","bool":true},{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR)","bool":false},{"option":"Homocysteine levels","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 levels","bool":false}],"id":340},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is correct about the rate of multiplication of bacteria in the log phase?","answers":[{"option":"It depends on the environment","bool":false},{"option":"It is decreasing","bool":false},{"option":"It is constant","bool":false},{"option":"It is increasing","bool":true},{"option":"It is zero","bool":false}],"id":341},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Hemolytic disease of the newborn (HDN) can be categorized as which type of hypersensitivity?","answers":[{"option":"Type 5","bool":false},{"option":"Type 1","bool":false},{"option":"Type 4","bool":false},{"option":"Type 3","bool":false},{"option":"Type 2","bool":true}],"id":342},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the causative agent of syphilis?","answers":[{"option":"Mycobacterium pneumoniae","bool":false},{"option":"Streptococcus pneumoniae","bool":false},{"option":"Treponema pallidum","bool":true},{"option":"Staphylococcus aureus","bool":false},{"option":"Mycobacterium tuberculosis","bool":false}],"id":343},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"The female Anopheles mosquito is responsible for the transmission of which of the following diseases?","answers":[{"option":"Syphilis","bool":false},{"option":"Dengue","bool":false},{"option":"Elephantiasis","bool":false},{"option":"Malaria","bool":true},{"option":"AIDS( Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome)","bool":false}],"id":344},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Conjugated bilirubin after entering into the intestine is modified by the action of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Fecal matter","bool":false},{"option":"Salts","bool":false},{"option":"Intestinal enzymes","bool":false},{"option":"Gut bacteria","bool":true},{"option":"Rectum","bool":false}],"id":345},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Streptococcus pneumoniae is a part of the normal flora of which of the following regions?","answers":[{"option":"Nasopharynx","bool":true},{"option":"Vagina","bool":false},{"option":"Colon","bool":false},{"option":"Intestine","bool":false},{"option":"Stomach","bool":false}],"id":346},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which option correctly describes the appearance of red blood cells in aplastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Macrocytic hyperchromic","bool":false},{"option":"Microcytic normochromic","bool":false},{"option":"Microcytic hyperchromic","bool":false},{"option":"Microcytic normochromic","bool":false},{"option":"Macrocytic normochromic","bool":true}],"id":347},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What is the site of erythropoiesis after seven months of in-utero life?","answers":[{"option":"Yellow marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Red marrow","bool":true},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":false}],"id":348},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements is incorrect regarding lymph nodes?","answers":[{"option":"Paracortex of nodes contains T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Hassall's corpuscles are present in the medulla of lymph nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphatic sinuses are present in nodes","bool":false},{"option":"They have high vascular endothelial venules","bool":false},{"option":"Cortex has germinal centers","bool":false}],"id":349},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Cell-mediated immunity is related to which of the following cells?","answers":[{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"T-cells","bool":true},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"B-cells","bool":false}],"id":350},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"By decreasing the levels of which of the following substances does aspirin inhibit platelet aggregation?","answers":[{"option":"COX-1 (cyclooxygenase-1)","bool":false},{"option":"Thromboxane A2","bool":true},{"option":"Lipoxygenase","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"Serotonin","bool":false}],"id":351},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a direct plasminogen activator?","answers":[{"option":"Urokinase","bool":true},{"option":"Alteplase","bool":false},{"option":"Tenecteplase","bool":false},{"option":"Reteplase","bool":false},{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":false}],"id":352},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which protein is abundantly present in neoplastic cells?","answers":[{"option":"Telomerase","bool":true},{"option":"Cytochrome C","bool":false},{"option":"Actin","bool":false},{"option":"Myosin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false}],"id":353},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which clotting factors are activated by vitamin K?","answers":[{"option":"III, IV, V, and X","bool":false},{"option":"III, V, VII, and IX","bool":false},{"option":"II, V, VI, and IX","bool":false},{"option":"II, VII, IX, and X","bool":true},{"option":"II, VI, VII, and IX","bool":false}],"id":354},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following options represents the correct characteristics of red blood cells in the blood smears of a patient suffering from thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Nucleated cells, target cells, and microcytic, normochromic cells","bool":false},{"option":"Nucleated cells, target cells, and microcytic, hypochromic cells","bool":true},{"option":"Non-nucleated cells, target cells, and microcytic, hypochromic cells","bool":false},{"option":"Non-nucleated cells and normocytic, hypochromic cells","bool":false},{"option":"Nucleated cells, target cells, and microcytic, hyperchromic cells","bool":false}],"id":355},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is not an anti-platelet drug?","answers":[{"option":"Urokinase","bool":true},{"option":"Ticlopidine","bool":false},{"option":"Prasugrel","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false},{"option":"Dipyridamole","bool":false}],"id":356},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"The presence of pus and swelling in the tonsils indicates which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Leukopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophilia","bool":true},{"option":"Basophilia","bool":false}],"id":357},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A cell can divide a maximum of up to 30-35 times, however, neoplastic cells do not have a limited number of cell divisions. This characteristic of neoplastic cells can be attributed to which of the following factors?","answers":[{"option":"Mutation in DNA repair gene","bool":false},{"option":"Upregulated telomerase","bool":true},{"option":"P53 mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclin gene mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Over-expression of growth factor receptors","bool":false}],"id":358},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following conditions is associated with the complications of heparin intake?","answers":[{"option":"Renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"Osteomalacia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemorrhage","bool":true},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false},{"option":"Pancytopenia","bool":false}],"id":359},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Where does erythropoiesis occur from birth till the age of 5?","answers":[{"option":"Yellow marrow of long bones","bool":false},{"option":"Only in the sternum and hip bone","bool":false},{"option":"Only in the vertebrae","bool":false},{"option":"Only in long bones","bool":false},{"option":"Red marrow of long bones","bool":true}],"id":360},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A 16-year-old girl comes to the clinic with complaints of recurrent infections and itching. She has a family history of the same problem. The diagnosis relates to a deficiency in innate response. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Leukocyte adhesion deficiency (LAD)","bool":true},{"option":"Common variable immunodeficiency","bool":false},{"option":"DiGeorge syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Severe combined immunodeficiency disorder (SCID)","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked lymphoproliferative syndrome","bool":false}],"id":361},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A 15-year-old boy comes to the outpatient department with a prolonged history of hemarthrosis (bleeding and swelling into muscles and joints) and unexplained bleeding from small bruises. Laboratory examination shows prolonged activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) as well as prolonged bleeding time. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease (vWD)","bool":true},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia C","bool":false}],"id":362},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A 5-year-old boy is brought to the clinic with the complaint of a swelling in the neck. On examination, his cervical lymph nodes are hard, tough, and immobile. What is the most likely diagnosis on the basis of examination?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Neutropenia","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Neutrophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Hodgkin's lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":363},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which infection is caused by plasmodium falciparum?","answers":[{"option":"Sleeping sickness","bool":false},{"option":"Ascariasis","bool":false},{"option":"Chagas disease","bool":false},{"option":"Babesiosis","bool":false},{"option":"Malaria","bool":true}],"id":364},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is true about a trophozoite?","answers":[{"option":"It is the non-motile stage of a lifecycle","bool":false},{"option":"It is the feeding and reproducing stage of a lifecycle","bool":true},{"option":"It is the infectious stage of a lifecycle","bool":false},{"option":"It is the death stage of a lifecycle","bool":false},{"option":"It is the vector stage of a lifecycle","bool":false}],"id":365},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the function of tumor necrosis factor (TNF) in septic shock?","answers":[{"option":"Vasoconstriction","bool":false},{"option":"Fever","bool":true},{"option":"Neutrophil diapedesis","bool":false},{"option":"Detachment of cells from endothelium","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotaxis of white blood cells","bool":false}],"id":366},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is an appropriate diagnostic method for a Leishmania infection?","answers":[{"option":"Intestinal cross section","bool":false},{"option":"Blood culture","bool":true},{"option":"Peripheral blood film","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count(CBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Spinal cross section","bool":false}],"id":367},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Sudden ischemia resulting from vascular occlusion leads to which of the following types of necrosis?","answers":[{"option":"Coagulative necrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Apoptosis","bool":false},{"option":"Fat necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Caseous necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinoid necrosis","bool":false}],"id":368},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"The brain undergoes which of the following types of necrosis?","answers":[{"option":"Fibrinoid necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Fat necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Caseous necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Liquefactive necrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Coagulative necrosis","bool":false}],"id":369},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following factors contributes to infarction in an organ?","answers":[{"option":"Carbondioxide concentration","bool":false},{"option":"Occlusion of the lymphatic supply of an organ","bool":false},{"option":"Carbon monoxide concentration","bool":false},{"option":"Edema in the organ","bool":false},{"option":"Occlusion of the vascular supply of an organ","bool":true}],"id":370},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Infarction results in which of the following types of necrosis?","answers":[{"option":"Fibrinoid necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Liquefactive necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Ischemic necrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Fat necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Caseous necrosis","bool":false}],"id":371},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Intrinsic factor is synthesized by which of the following cells?","answers":[{"option":"Chief cells","bool":false},{"option":"Mucoid cells","bool":false},{"option":"Parietal cells","bool":true},{"option":"Esophageal cells","bool":false},{"option":"G cells","bool":false}],"id":372},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following vitamins is related to the metabolism of folic acid?","answers":[{"option":"B6","bool":false},{"option":"B1","bool":false},{"option":"D","bool":false},{"option":"A","bool":false},{"option":"B12","bool":true}],"id":373},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Iron deficiency affects which of the following mechanisms?","answers":[{"option":"Homocysteine synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Methylmalonic acid synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin synthesis","bool":true},{"option":"Folic acid synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 synthesis","bool":false}],"id":374},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A 24-year-old male presents in the outpatient department with headache, tremors, and mood changes. The patient also gives a history of fly bite. The posterior cervical lymph nodes are also enlarged. Which protozoan parasite might be the cause?","answers":[{"option":"Plasmodium falciparum","bool":false},{"option":"Leishmania donovani","bool":false},{"option":"Pneumocystis jirovecii","bool":false},{"option":"Trypanosoma gambiense","bool":true},{"option":"Toxoplasma gondii","bool":false}],"id":375},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A 24-year-old male presents in the outpatient department with headache, tremors, and mood changes. The patient also gives a history of fly bite. The posterior cervical lymph nodes are also enlarged. Which of the following conditions can this be?","answers":[{"option":"Black sickness","bool":false},{"option":"Sleeping sickness","bool":true},{"option":"Encephalitis","bool":false},{"option":"Intracranial calcification","bool":false},{"option":"Megacolon","bool":false}],"id":376},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following organism acts as an insect vector for Trypanosoma gambiense?","answers":[{"option":"Diptera","bool":false},{"option":"Tsetse fly","bool":true},{"option":"Sand fly","bool":false},{"option":"Anopheles mosquito","bool":false},{"option":"Deer fly","bool":false}],"id":377},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following tests is most commonly used to detect infection with Trypanosoma gambiense in the early stages of the disease?","answers":[{"option":"Screening tests for antibody detection","bool":false},{"option":"Blood smears revealing trypomastigotes in blood","bool":true},{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Culture of organism","bool":false},{"option":"Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)","bool":false}],"id":378},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following drugs is usually used for the treatment of sleeping sickness?","answers":[{"option":"Atovaquone","bool":false},{"option":"Benzimidazole","bool":false},{"option":"Ibuprofen","bool":false},{"option":"Sumarin","bool":true},{"option":"Sodium stibogluconate","bool":false}],"id":379},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"How much erythropoietin is produced by kidneys?","answers":[{"option":"80%","bool":false},{"option":"65%","bool":false},{"option":"70%","bool":false},{"option":"90%","bool":true},{"option":"95%","bool":false}],"id":380},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following can be the most reliable indicator that can be used to differentiate between benign and malignant tumors?","answers":[{"option":"Invasion of local tissues","bool":true},{"option":"Cytoplasmic eosinophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Degree of hypertrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Dysplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Nuclear basophilia","bool":false}],"id":381},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the mechanical factor that plays its role in the sterility of the genitourinary tract?","answers":[{"option":"B cells","bool":false},{"option":"Low pH","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary flow","bool":true},{"option":"T cells","bool":false}],"id":382},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Pernicious anemia can result from which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Esophagitis","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Malabsorption syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Gastrectomy","bool":true},{"option":"Oral carcinoma","bool":false}],"id":383},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the optimum temperature for growth of bacteria?","answers":[{"option":"120 °C","bool":false},{"option":"4 °C","bool":false},{"option":"37 °C","bool":true},{"option":"100 °C","bool":false},{"option":"50 °C","bool":false}],"id":384},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following can play its role as an anticoagulant to prevent further clotting around the injured part after a clot has been formed there?","answers":[{"option":"Factor XII","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombin","bool":true},{"option":"Prothrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Factor X","bool":false}],"id":385},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is not a sign of acute inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Warmth","bool":false},{"option":"Pain","bool":false},{"option":"Edema","bool":false},{"option":"Confusion","bool":true},{"option":"Redness","bool":false}],"id":386},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following cells are seen abundantly in the blood of a person infected by a helminth?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false}],"id":387},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"In extremely rare diseases, the calculated odds are equal to which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Rate ratio","bool":false},{"option":"Prevalence ratio","bool":false},{"option":"Difference ratio","bool":false},{"option":"Relative risk/risk ratio","bool":true},{"option":"Odds ratio","bool":false}],"id":388},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following leads to infarction in a tissue?","answers":[{"option":"Ischemia","bool":true},{"option":"Necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Apoptosis","bool":false},{"option":"High blood supply","bool":false},{"option":"Necroptosis","bool":false}],"id":389},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following drugs does not affect wound healing?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin A","bool":false},{"option":"Tetracycline","bool":true},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Steroids","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false}],"id":390},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"\"Since when has the disease been occurring?\", \"Where is it occurring?\", \"What is the type of person getting the disease?\". What type of diagnosis is being done by asking questions like these?","answers":[{"option":"Descriptive","bool":true},{"option":"Experimental","bool":false},{"option":"Exotic","bool":false},{"option":"Environmental","bool":false},{"option":"Analytical","bool":false}],"id":391},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A 10-year-old male comes to the emergency room with burns. His complete blood count (CBC) shows neutrophilia with 40 x 10⁹/L WBCs. What reaction causes this neutrophilia?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Drug reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Arthus reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Fever","bool":false},{"option":"Acute inflammation","bool":true}],"id":392},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is not associated with a patient suffering from a disease caused by Trypanosoma cruzi?","answers":[{"option":"Palpable swelling","bool":false},{"option":"Chagoma","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatosplenomegaly","bool":false},{"option":"Facial edema","bool":false},{"option":"Sleeping sickness","bool":true}],"id":393},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is correct regarding the normal flora in humans?","answers":[{"option":"Formed after the neonatal period","bool":true},{"option":"Not present in the stomach at all due to an acidic pH","bool":false},{"option":"Not affected by antimicrobial drugs","bool":false},{"option":"The same numbers and types of organisms inhabit the throat and the bronchioles","bool":false},{"option":"Formed in intra-uterine life","bool":false}],"id":394},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A 5-year-old boy was diagnosed with chronic granulomatous disease (CGD). CGD is a disease associated with a defect in the oxidative burst. Which of the following cells are affected in CGD?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Phagocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Natural killer cells","bool":false}],"id":395},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"A blister is an example of which type of inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Purulent inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Ulceration","bool":false},{"option":"Granulomatous inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Serous inflammation","bool":true},{"option":"Fibrinoid inflammation","bool":false}],"id":396},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What is the inheritance pattern of thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Y-linked","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":true},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":false}],"id":397},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What enzyme catalyzes the first step of heme degradation?","answers":[{"option":"Protoporphyrinogen  oxidase","bool":false},{"option":"Delta aminolevulinic acid synthase","bool":false},{"option":"Heme oxygenase","bool":true},{"option":"Biliverdin reductase","bool":false},{"option":"Heme reductase","bool":false}],"id":398},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which type of antibody plays a dominant role in helminth infection?","answers":[{"option":"Ig M","bool":false},{"option":"Ig D","bool":false},{"option":"Ig G","bool":false},{"option":"Ig A","bool":false},{"option":"Ig E","bool":true}],"id":399},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"Which type of hemoglobin plays a protective role in infants against thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"HbF","bool":true},{"option":"HbA","bool":false},{"option":"HbS","bool":false},{"option":"HbA2","bool":false},{"option":"HbC","bool":false}],"id":400},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"In a fetus aged 2-7 months, what is the main site of hemopoiesis?","answers":[{"option":"Yolk sac","bool":false},{"option":"Yellow marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":true},{"option":"Red marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false}],"id":401},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What is the typical blood picture in thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Intrinsic hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Macrocytic, megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Target cells","bool":false},{"option":"Microcytic, hypochromic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Bite cells","bool":false}],"id":402},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2019"],"question":"What does non-tender and rubbery submandibular, cervical, and axillary lymphadenopathy indicate?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sarcoidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Melanoma","bool":false}],"id":403},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A patient is on heparin, which is an anticoagulant. In case of heparin overdose, bleeding can occur. This bleeding can be controlled by administering which of the following drugs as an antidote to this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Hydroxocobalamin","bool":false},{"option":"Acetylcysteine","bool":false},{"option":"Protamine sulfate","bool":true},{"option":"Ascorbic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Methylene blue","bool":false}],"id":404},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the process in which antigen-antibody (Ag-Ab) complexes are phagocytosed much more efficiently in the presence of C3b known as?","answers":[{"option":"Cytolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotoxin","bool":false},{"option":"Opsonization","bool":true},{"option":"Anaphylatoxin","bool":false},{"option":"Lysis of bacteria","bool":false}],"id":405},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Alpha thalassemia presents in four different clinical conditions because of the presence of how many copies of genes?","answers":[{"option":"5","bool":false},{"option":"3","bool":false},{"option":"2","bool":false},{"option":"4","bool":true},{"option":"1","bool":false}],"id":406},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"\"A thymus-derived cell that participates in a variety of cell mediated immune reactions\". Which cell does this statement define?","answers":[{"option":"Monocyte","bool":false},{"option":"T-cell","bool":true},{"option":"Natural killer cell","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cell","bool":false},{"option":"Polymorphonuclear cell","bool":false}],"id":407},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A woman has a mechanical heart valve and takes warfarin. What advice should she receive regarding her anti-thrombotic medication in pregnancy?","answers":[{"option":"Warfarin should be replaced with aspirin at high doses","bool":false},{"option":"All the medications that affect the blood should be avoided","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin should be replaced with heparin","bool":true},{"option":"Warfarin should be discontinued and supplementary vitamin A should be taken everyday throughout the pregnancy","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin should be discontinued until the third trimester","bool":false}],"id":408},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A young male brought to the emergency room was in an unconscious state following an injection dose of a medicine given by a general practitioner. On examination, the patient was diagnosed with anaphylactic shock. Which of the following is the main causative factor for the mentioned condition?","answers":[{"option":"B-lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":true},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Antigen presenting cells","bool":false}],"id":409},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is inhibited by aminocaproic acid?","answers":[{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Iron","bool":false},{"option":"Antiplatelet drugs","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinolytic drugs","bool":true},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false}],"id":410},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is the most abundant plasma protein?","answers":[{"option":"Albumin","bool":true},{"option":"Globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Peptones","bool":false},{"option":"Peptide","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":false}],"id":411},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"An outbreak of septicemia by Staphylococcus aureus occurred in a children's ward. Where is the causative organism usually found as part of the normal flora?","answers":[{"option":"Lower respiratory tract","bool":false},{"option":"Nose","bool":true},{"option":"Colon","bool":false},{"option":"Gastrointestinal tract","bool":false},{"option":"Throat","bool":false}],"id":412},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Aspirin differs from other nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) in what aspect?","answers":[{"option":"Unlike other NSAIDs, aspirin can arrest the progress of arthritis","bool":false},{"option":"Analgesic action of aspirin is due to the decrease in PGE₂ synthesis while other NSAIDs have no action on this prostaglandin","bool":false},{"option":"Unlike other NSAIDs, aspirin inhibits both the cyclooxygenase and lipoxygenase pathways","bool":false},{"option":"Unlike aspirin, NSAIDs are reversible inhibitors of cyclooxygenase","bool":true},{"option":"Interstitial nephritis can only result from aspirin","bool":false}],"id":413},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"How does aspirin inhibit platelet aggregation?","answers":[{"option":"Because it inhibits TXA₂ production in platelets for 3 - 7 days","bool":false},{"option":"When it is given at 60 - 80 g/day doses","bool":false},{"option":"By irreversible inhibition of cyclooxygenase pathway in endothelial cells","bool":true},{"option":"By reversible inhibition of cyclooxygenase pathway for the lifetime of the platelets","bool":false},{"option":"By irreversible inhibition of lipooxygenase pathway","bool":false}],"id":414},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Before cell division, the final check point for DNA damage/abnormality occurs at which phase of the cell cycle?","answers":[{"option":"G1 / S","bool":false},{"option":"M","bool":false},{"option":"G2 / M","bool":true},{"option":"G1","bool":false},{"option":"G2","bool":false}],"id":415},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is Blackwater fever a complication of?","answers":[{"option":"Ovale malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Amoebic dysentery","bool":false},{"option":"Dengue","bool":false},{"option":"Vivax malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Falciparum malaria","bool":true}],"id":416},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Cancer cells have limitless proliferative capacities because of which of the following mechanisms?","answers":[{"option":"Cellular senescence","bool":false},{"option":"Mitotic catastrophe","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in apoptosis","bool":false},{"option":"Increased IGF resulting in angiogenesis","bool":false},{"option":"Upregulation of the enzyme telomerase","bool":true}],"id":417},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the cancerous mutation of myelogenous or lymphogenous cells called?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Leukopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemoid reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":true}],"id":418},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following regarding ceruloplasmin is correct?","answers":[{"option":"Involved in Zn absorption","bool":false},{"option":"Changes Fe⁺² to Fe⁺³","bool":true},{"option":"Present in neurons","bool":false},{"option":"Acts primarily in muscle cells","bool":false},{"option":"Converts hemoglobin to myoglobin","bool":false}],"id":419},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of these is a clotting factor that requires activation and is dependent on vitamin K?","answers":[{"option":"Calcium","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Labile factor","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin","bool":true},{"option":"Tissue factor","bool":false}],"id":420},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Defensins are highly positively charged cationic peptides that perform which of the following functions?","answers":[{"option":"Activate complement","bool":false},{"option":"Create pores in bacterial membrane","bool":true},{"option":"All of these","bool":false},{"option":"Cause opsonization of bacteria","bool":false},{"option":"Help in the formation of superoxide","bool":false}],"id":421},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is deferoxamine a specific antidote of?","answers":[{"option":"Antiplatelet drugs","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Iron","bool":true},{"option":"Fibrinolytic drugs","bool":false}],"id":422},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What does a deficiency of factor VIII cause?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":false}],"id":423},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Epstein-Barr virus causes which type of malignancy in African children?","answers":[{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Burkitt's lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Peripheral T-cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Mastocytosis","bool":false}],"id":424},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What combination of blood groups leads to erythroblastosis fetalis?","answers":[{"option":"When the mother is Rh- and fetus is Rh+","bool":true},{"option":"When the mother is B+ and fetus is O+","bool":false},{"option":"When the mother is AB+ and fetus is AB-","bool":false},{"option":"When the mother is O+ and fetus is O-","bool":false},{"option":"When the mother is A+ and fetus is B-","bool":false}],"id":425},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"The fibroblast used to heal wounds is derived from which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Endothelium","bool":false},{"option":"Local mesenchyme","bool":true},{"option":"Vascular fibrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Epithelium","bool":false}],"id":426},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Where does the first step of red blood cell formation normally occur in an adult?","answers":[{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":true},{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphoid tissues","bool":false}],"id":427},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What does glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase do?","answers":[{"option":"Oxidizes NADPH to NADP","bool":false},{"option":"Reduces NADPH to NADP","bool":false},{"option":"Reduces NADP to NADPH","bool":true},{"option":"Reduces ATP to ADP","bool":false},{"option":"Oxidizes NADP to NADPH","bool":false}],"id":428},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Glycine and succinyl CoA combine to form delta-aminolevulinic acid in the presence of which enzyme?","answers":[{"option":"Esterase","bool":false},{"option":"Hexokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Delta aminolevulinic acid synthase","bool":true},{"option":"Glucokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Pyruvate kinase","bool":false}],"id":429},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What are growth factors usually made of?","answers":[{"option":"Carbohydrates","bool":false},{"option":"Aminoglycosides","bool":false},{"option":"Glycoproteins","bool":false},{"option":"Fat","bool":false},{"option":"Polypeptides","bool":true}],"id":430},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"How does histamine cause increased vascular leakage?","answers":[{"option":"Endothelial cell necrosis and detachment","bool":false},{"option":"Increased trancytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Increased hydrostatic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Increased margination of leukocytes at the site of injury","bool":false},{"option":"Contraction of endothelial cells","bool":true}],"id":431},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Human T-cell leukemia virus type-1 (HTLV-1) affects which inflammatory cells?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":false},{"option":"CD2+ T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"CD4+ T-cells","bool":true}],"id":432},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"For malaria, sporozoites are injected into humans beings. The exo-erythrocytic cycle takes place in which organ of the body?","answers":[{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":true},{"option":"Lymph node","bool":false},{"option":"Heart","bool":false}],"id":433},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"In malignant tumors, what does the term \"loss of polarity\" mean?","answers":[{"option":"Formation of tumors against normal cells","bool":false},{"option":"Pleomorphism","bool":false},{"option":"More than 10 mitoses/10 high power fields","bool":false},{"option":"Altered nuclear cytoplasmic ratio of cancer cells","bool":false},{"option":"Markedly disturbed orientation of cancer cells","bool":true}],"id":434},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"In reticuloendothelial cells, what initially degrades heme?","answers":[{"option":"Dehydratase","bool":false},{"option":"Synthase","bool":false},{"option":"Heme oxygenase","bool":true},{"option":"Biliverdin reductase","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrochelatase","bool":false}],"id":435},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Innate immunity is considered to be the first line of defense against many microorganisms. Which of the following is a major component of this immunity?","answers":[{"option":"T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"B-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Skin","bool":true}],"id":436},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"How can iron be  rapidly depleted from the body?","answers":[{"option":"High altitude","bool":false},{"option":"Weight loss","bool":false},{"option":"High calcium absorption","bool":false},{"option":"Blood loss","bool":true},{"option":"Vigorous exercise","bool":false}],"id":437},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Kala-azar is found in most tropical and subtropical countries and is transferred by the sand-fly. What is its causative organism?","answers":[{"option":"T. cruzi","bool":false},{"option":"L. tropica","bool":false},{"option":"L. braziliensis","bool":false},{"option":"L. mexicana","bool":false},{"option":"L. donovani","bool":true}],"id":438},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What condition are macro-ovalocytes in a peripheral blood smear seen in?","answers":[{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false}],"id":439},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the mechanism of action of penicillin?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibition of transpeptidation in the cell wall","bool":true},{"option":"Inhibition of beta-lactamase in the cell wall","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of endogenous phospholipases, destroying bacterial cell wall","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of endogenous proteases, destroying bacterial cell wall","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of exogenous proteases, destroying bacterial cell wall","bool":false}],"id":440},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is a major mediator of an anaphylactic reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Slow-reacting substance of anaphylaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine","bool":true},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Serotonin","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotriene","bool":false}],"id":441},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of these is the most appropriate technique for identifying thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Estimation of shape hemoglobin molecules","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin chromatography","bool":false},{"option":"Measurement of iron","bool":false},{"option":"Measurement of mean corpuscular volume","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":true}],"id":442},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the movement of leukocytes to the site of an injurious stimulus called?","answers":[{"option":"Rolling","bool":false},{"option":"Adhesion","bool":false},{"option":"Margination","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotaxis","bool":true},{"option":"Diapedesis","bool":false}],"id":443},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is 1 gram of pure hemoglobin capable of combining with?","answers":[{"option":"13.4 ml of carbon dioxide","bool":false},{"option":"1.34 ml of oxygen","bool":true},{"option":"134 ml of oxygen","bool":false},{"option":"13.4 ml of oxygen","bool":false},{"option":"1.34 ml of carbon dioxide","bool":false}],"id":444},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following substances is found in the specific cytoplasmic granules of neutrophils?","answers":[{"option":"Cationic proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Myeloperoxidase","bool":false},{"option":"Elastase","bool":false},{"option":"Proteinase","bool":false},{"option":"Lysozyme","bool":true}],"id":445},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is most likely to lead to a patient presenting with bleeding?","answers":[{"option":"High platelet count","bool":false},{"option":"Prolonged bed rest or immobilization","bool":false},{"option":"Protein S deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Protein C deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Low platelet count","bool":true}],"id":446},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"How does penicillin kill bacterial cells?","answers":[{"option":"By inhibiting the transpeptidation reaction","bool":true},{"option":"By inhibiting the 50S ribosomal RNA","bool":false},{"option":"By inhibiting the folic acid synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"By inhibiting the tubulin polymerization","bool":false},{"option":"By inhibiting the 30S ribosomal RNA","bool":false}],"id":447},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What causes pernicious anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Inadequate diet","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid antagonists","bool":false},{"option":"Deficiency of intrinsic factor","bool":true},{"option":"Vegetarianism","bool":false},{"option":"Hemodialysis","bool":false}],"id":448},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Pleomorphic adenoma is the swelling of the parotid gland and is an example of what?","answers":[{"option":"Mixed malignant tumor","bool":false},{"option":"Benign epithelial cell tumor","bool":false},{"option":"Painful, fast growing inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Malignant tumor","bool":false},{"option":"Benign mixed tumor","bool":true}],"id":449},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Regarding blood grouping, what does an Rh-positive individual possess?","answers":[{"option":"Agglutinogen D","bool":true},{"option":"Agglutinin D","bool":false},{"option":"Agglutinogen A","bool":false},{"option":"Agglutinogen B","bool":false},{"option":"Agglutinin AB","bool":false}],"id":450},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Regarding carcinogens, which of the following statements is correct?","answers":[{"option":"No promotor is required for direct acting chemical carcinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Most of the known carcinogens are metabolized by cytochrome P-450","bool":true},{"option":"All carcinogens are some form of ionic radiation","bool":false},{"option":"All carcinogens are manmade","bool":false},{"option":"Man cannot manufacture carcinogens","bool":false}],"id":451},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following regarding HbH is correct?","answers":[{"option":"Iron overload is usually seen","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia is moderately severe","bool":false},{"option":"Results because of gene deletion","bool":false},{"option":"Caused by the deletion of three α-globin genes","bool":true},{"option":"Not as severe as β-thalassemia major","bool":false}],"id":452},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Regarding signalling mechanisms in cell growth, what does \"autocrine signalling\" mean?","answers":[{"option":"Cell responding to signalling molecules that are secreted by far away cells","bool":false},{"option":"Cell responding to signalling molecules brought by blood","bool":false},{"option":"Cell responding to signalling molecules that they themselves secreted","bool":true},{"option":"Cell responding to signalling molecules brought by lymphatics","bool":false},{"option":"Cell responding to signalling molecules that are secreted by adjacent cells","bool":false}],"id":453},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Why might cancer stem cells be less susceptible to chemotherapy?","answers":[{"option":"Because of tumor debulking","bool":false},{"option":"Because of distant metastasis of tumor","bool":false},{"option":"Cells are mostly in G₀ phase","bool":true},{"option":"Growth rate equals that of adjacent normal cells","bool":false},{"option":"Because of local tumor invasion","bool":false}],"id":454},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Reiter's syndrome is a systemic autoimmune disease triggered by infection with intestinal pathogen. Which triad characterizes this disease?","answers":[{"option":"Conjuctivitis, arthritis, cervicitis","bool":false},{"option":"Arthritis, oophoritis, thydroiditis","bool":false},{"option":"Thydroiditis, tonsilitis, conjuctivitis","bool":false},{"option":"Arthritis, conjuctivitis, urethritis","bool":true},{"option":"Cervicitis, arthritis, pancreatitis","bool":false}],"id":455},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What causes sickle cell disease?","answers":[{"option":"Increased synthesis of normal hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Replacement of valine by a glutamic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased synthesis of abnormal hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased synthesis of beta chain of globin","bool":false},{"option":"Point mutation in the 6th codon of the beta globin chain","bool":true}],"id":456},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"The sum of the squared deviations from the mean, when divided by the number of observations will give what value?","answers":[{"option":"Mean deviation","bool":false},{"option":"Standard error","bool":false},{"option":"Variance","bool":true},{"option":"Median","bool":false},{"option":"Standard deviation","bool":false}],"id":457},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Systemic lupus erythematosus, a systemic autoimmune disease is caused by the formation of antibodies against which structure?","answers":[{"option":"Nerves","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Myocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Nuclear proteins","bool":true},{"option":"RBCs","bool":false}],"id":458},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Formation of which of the following is the rate-controlling factor in the coagulation process?","answers":[{"option":"Fibrin-stabilizing factor","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin activator","bool":true},{"option":"Prothrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Potassium ions (K+)","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium ions (Ca++)","bool":false}],"id":459},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"In hemoglobin C (HbC), which amino acid is substituted for glutamate?","answers":[{"option":"Glycine","bool":false},{"option":"Isoleucine","bool":false},{"option":"Lysine","bool":true},{"option":"Leucine","bool":false},{"option":"Valine","bool":false}],"id":460},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"In the formation of hemoglobin, which enzyme is involved in the incorporation of Fe into protoporphyrin IX?","answers":[{"option":"ALA dehydratase","bool":false},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen III decarboxylase","bool":false},{"option":"Ferroxidase","bool":false},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen III synthase","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrochelatase","bool":true}],"id":461},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following plays a vital role in the maturation of red blood cells?","answers":[{"option":"Thiamine","bool":false},{"option":"Copper","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false},{"option":"Cyanocobalamin","bool":true},{"option":"Iron","bool":false}],"id":462},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"After how many days are platelets replaced?","answers":[{"option":"17 days","bool":false},{"option":"5-7 days","bool":false},{"option":"8-10 days","bool":true},{"option":"13-15 days","bool":false},{"option":"30-35 days","bool":false}],"id":463},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the other name for cobalamin?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin B-12","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin B-6","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B-9","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false}],"id":464},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"On the surface of which of these are type A, type B, and Rh antigens present?","answers":[{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Granulocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":false}],"id":465},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"How many pyrrole rings are present in one molecule of hemoglobin?","answers":[{"option":"4 pyrrole rings","bool":true},{"option":"7 pyrrole rings","bool":false},{"option":"No pyrrole ring","bool":false},{"option":"5 pyrrole rings","bool":false},{"option":"6 pyrrole rings","bool":false}],"id":466},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Activated platelets undergo degranulation to release ADP and enzymes. Which of the following is formed by those enzymes?","answers":[{"option":"ATP","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine","bool":false},{"option":"Endothelin","bool":false},{"option":"Thromboxane A2","bool":true},{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":false}],"id":467},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following is activated by interleukin 5 (IL-5)?","answers":[{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":false},{"option":"B lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"T lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true}],"id":468},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is the most appropriate measure of association for a case-control study?","answers":[{"option":"Death-to-case ratio","bool":false},{"option":"Odds ratio","bool":true},{"option":"Rate ratio","bool":false},{"option":"Risk ratio","bool":false},{"option":"Prevalence ratio","bool":false}],"id":469},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following is the most important factor in opsonization?","answers":[{"option":"C3a","bool":false},{"option":"C5a","bool":false},{"option":"C4","bool":false},{"option":"C5b","bool":false},{"option":"C3b","bool":true}],"id":470},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following models of disease causation involves a susceptible host, an external agent, and an environment that brings these two together?","answers":[{"option":"Wheel of disease causation","bool":false},{"option":"Germ theory of disease","bool":false},{"option":"Epidemiologic triad","bool":true},{"option":"Web of causation","bool":false},{"option":"Sufficient-component cause model","bool":false}],"id":471},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"In the complement system, which one is the most important chemotactic agent?","answers":[{"option":"C3b","bool":false},{"option":"C9b","bool":false},{"option":"C5a","bool":true},{"option":"C7b","bool":false},{"option":"C8a","bool":false}],"id":472},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"The activity of antithrombin III is increased by 100 to 1000 folds by binding to which of the following molecules?","answers":[{"option":"Heparin","bool":true},{"option":"Prothrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false},{"option":"Protamine sulfate","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false}],"id":473},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Glycosylated hemoglobin test (HbA1C) levels can be measured to diagnose which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes insipidus","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes mellitus","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":false}],"id":474},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Where is the value of mean located in a positively skewed curve?","answers":[{"option":"To the extreme right of the distribution","bool":true},{"option":"To the extreme left of the distribution","bool":false},{"option":"Between the median and the mode","bool":false},{"option":"At the highest peak of distribution","bool":false},{"option":"At the middle of the peak","bool":false}],"id":475},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Deficiency of which of the following causes the hemorrhagic disease of the newborn?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin B-6","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B-12","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B-9","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":true}],"id":476},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"While observing under his microscope, a histologist noticed a few biconcave and disc-like cells under his microscope. What did he name them?","answers":[{"option":"Erythrocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocytes","bool":false}],"id":477},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the square root of variance called?","answers":[{"option":"T-test","bool":false},{"option":"Mean deviation","bool":false},{"option":"Variance coefficient","bool":false},{"option":"Range","bool":false},{"option":"Standard deviation","bool":true}],"id":478},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"The scar is formed by the process of pathological wound healing. What would its nature be?","answers":[{"option":"Collagen","bool":false},{"option":"Necrotic tissue","bool":false},{"option":"Dead tissue","bool":false},{"option":"Elastic","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrotic","bool":true}],"id":479},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which antibody is most likely to pass from the maternal circulation to the fetus through the placenta?","answers":[{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":true}],"id":480},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What causes hemolysis in G6PD deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of Heinz bodies","bool":true},{"option":"Spectrin deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Excess of alpha globin chains","bool":false},{"option":"Hemosiderosis","bool":false}],"id":481},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following statements is true for the term \"carrier\"?","answers":[{"option":"An individual who is a carrier can carry a greater load than normal","bool":false},{"option":"An individual who harbors a potential pathogen and can be a source of infection to others","bool":true},{"option":"An individual who is asymptomatic and thus cannot transmit any infection","bool":false},{"option":"A carrier is one who harbors a usual pathogen","bool":false},{"option":"An individual with pathogens in sites that are normally colonized in others","bool":false}],"id":482},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the generation time of Escherichia coli in a lab?","answers":[{"option":"20 hours","bool":false},{"option":"20 months","bool":false},{"option":"20 weeks","bool":false},{"option":"20 minutes","bool":true},{"option":"20 days","bool":false}],"id":483},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is an important feature of acute inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Accumulation of B-cells at the site of injury","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased blood flow in vessels","bool":false},{"option":"Transmigration of the plasma, and red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of RBC to eliminate the offending agent","bool":false},{"option":"Changes in microvasculature","bool":true}],"id":484},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the major form of vitamin B12 found in human tissue and mitochondria?","answers":[{"option":"Hydroxycobalamin","bool":false},{"option":"Nitrocobalamin","bool":false},{"option":"Cyanocobalamin","bool":false},{"option":"Methylcobalamin","bool":false},{"option":"5'-Deoxyadenosyl cobalamin","bool":true}],"id":485},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the major source of histamine?","answers":[{"option":"Erythrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":true},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false}],"id":486},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What are the mesenchymal cells that aggregate to form blood islands?","answers":[{"option":"Definitive heart","bool":false},{"option":"Chemoblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Fibroblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Angioblasts","bool":true},{"option":"Mesoblasts","bool":false}],"id":487},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What complication of thrombocytopenia is most likely to cause fatality?","answers":[{"option":"Needle prick","bool":false},{"option":"Gum bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Gastro-intestinal bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Nose bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Intracranial bleeding","bool":true}],"id":488},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the most common cause of a defect in leukocyte function?","answers":[{"option":"Inherited defect in leukocyte adhesion","bool":true},{"option":"Bone marrow suppression","bool":false},{"option":"Inherited defect in phagolysosome function","bool":false},{"option":"Chediak-Higashi syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Inherited defect in microbial activity","bool":false}],"id":489},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the process of formation of the formed (solid) elements of blood called?","answers":[{"option":"Erythropoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"Homeostasis","bool":false},{"option":"Hemostasis","bool":false},{"option":"Hematopoiesis","bool":true},{"option":"Leukopoiesis","bool":false}],"id":490},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the time between exposure and occurrence of the first symptom of a disease called?","answers":[{"option":"Serial interview","bool":false},{"option":"Exposure period","bool":false},{"option":"Window period","bool":false},{"option":"Generation time","bool":false},{"option":"Incubation period","bool":true}],"id":491},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Warfarin antagonizes the effect of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Tocopherol","bool":false},{"option":"Ascorbic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin A","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B6","bool":false}],"id":492},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which cardinal sign of inflammation is less easily detected?","answers":[{"option":"Increase in temperature","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of function","bool":true},{"option":"Tenderness","bool":false},{"option":"Swelling","bool":false},{"option":"Pain","bool":false}],"id":493},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What would a disease that occurs in a certain geographical area and is meant to remain there be classified as?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Zoonotic","bool":false},{"option":"Epidemic","bool":false},{"option":"Endemic","bool":true},{"option":"Pandemic","bool":false}],"id":494},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is the most important copper-containing protein?","answers":[{"option":"Cytochrome","bool":false},{"option":"Ceruloplasmin","bool":true},{"option":"Globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false}],"id":495},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the correlation between the probability of an outcome in an exposed group to that in an unexposed group called?","answers":[{"option":"Relative risk","bool":true},{"option":"Epidemic threshold","bool":false},{"option":"Attack rate","bool":false},{"option":"Population-at-risk","bool":false},{"option":"Prevalence risk","bool":false}],"id":496},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following is a malignant tumor?","answers":[{"option":"Osteoma","bool":false},{"option":"Mesothelioma","bool":true},{"option":"Chondroma","bool":false},{"option":"Leiomyoma","bool":false},{"option":"Fibroma","bool":false}],"id":497},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"In which of the following modes of disease transmission does the infection spread either by skin-to-skin or mucosa-to-skin contact?","answers":[{"option":"Vertical transmission","bool":false},{"option":"Air-borne droplet","bool":false},{"option":"Direct contact","bool":true},{"option":"Indirect contact","bool":false},{"option":"Inoculation","bool":false}],"id":498},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following plasma proteins plays the greatest role in maintaining the oncotic pressure?","answers":[{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":true},{"option":"Apolipoprotein","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false}],"id":499},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following plasma proteins has the most prominent role in the transportation of free fatty acids?","answers":[{"option":"Plasma ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":true},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false}],"id":500},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following substances released by platelets plays a role in vasoconstriction?","answers":[{"option":"Prostacyclin","bool":false},{"option":"ATP","bool":false},{"option":"Nitrous oxide","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"Thromboxane A2","bool":true}],"id":501},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following chemical mediators is involved in chemotaxis?","answers":[{"option":"Leukotriene B4 and bacterial products","bool":true},{"option":"Prostaglandin","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotriene C4, D4, E4","bool":false},{"option":"Substance P","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine","bool":false}],"id":502},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following is not a clinical feature of thrombocytopenia?","answers":[{"option":"Bleeding in joints","bool":true},{"option":"Petechial hemorrhages","bool":false},{"option":"Ecchymosis","bool":false},{"option":"Bruises","bool":false},{"option":"Epistaxis","bool":false}],"id":503},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is a characteristic feature of severe iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Poikilocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Macrocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Elliptocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperchromia","bool":false},{"option":"Schistocytosis","bool":false}],"id":504},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following mediates cancer cachexia?","answers":[{"option":"TNF-α","bool":true},{"option":"IL-2","bool":false},{"option":"IL-5","bool":false},{"option":"TGF-β","bool":false},{"option":"CCl-5","bool":false}],"id":505},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following microorganisms is closely associated with dental caries?","answers":[{"option":"Staphylococcus epidermidis","bool":false},{"option":"Neisseria gonorrhoea","bool":false},{"option":"Streptococcus mutans","bool":true},{"option":"Candida albicans","bool":false},{"option":"Prevolta melaninogenica","bool":false}],"id":506},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following sites of the human body does not usually have normal flora?","answers":[{"option":"Vagina","bool":false},{"option":"Colon","bool":false},{"option":"Distal urethra","bool":false},{"option":"Skin","bool":false},{"option":"Blood","bool":true}],"id":507},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following cells are a dominant feature of the thymic medulla?","answers":[{"option":"Thymocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Hassall's corpuscles (thymic corpuscles)","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphoblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false}],"id":508},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following is an oral third generation cephalosporin?","answers":[{"option":"Ceftizoxime","bool":false},{"option":"Cefazidime","bool":false},{"option":"Cefotaxime","bool":false},{"option":"Ceftriaxone","bool":false},{"option":"Cefixime","bool":true}],"id":509},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A 9-month-old girl has been having recurrent infections since she was 2 months old and her\r\nsister complains of a similar history. They were both the children of a consanguineous marriage. Which innate immune defect would most likely be diagnosed in them?","answers":[{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocyte adhesion deficiency (LAD)","bool":true},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE)","bool":false},{"option":"Common variable cell immunodeficiency (CVID)","bool":false}],"id":510},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following plasma proteins helps in the transport of free fatty acids in the blood stream?","answers":[{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrin","bool":false},{"option":"γ-globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":true},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false}],"id":511},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which specific term is used when a biocide is able to kill bacteria?","answers":[{"option":"Bacteriostatic","bool":false},{"option":"Bactericidal","bool":true},{"option":"Antibacteriotic","bool":false},{"option":"Cleaning","bool":false},{"option":"Insecticide","bool":false}],"id":512},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which type of epidemiological method investigates and evaluates preventative and therapeutic measures?","answers":[{"option":"Literature search","bool":false},{"option":"Preventative method","bool":true},{"option":"Observational","bool":false},{"option":"Descriptive","bool":false},{"option":"Ecologic studies","bool":false}],"id":513},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Regarding β-thalassemia major, which of the following is the most relevant?","answers":[{"option":"Iron overload is due to high levels of hepcidin","bool":false},{"option":"Manifests itself in-utero","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow transplantation at an early stage is the treatment of choice","bool":true},{"option":"With transfusions alone, survival into the sixth or seventh decade is possible","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia is due to decreased erythropoietin","bool":false}],"id":514},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A 45-year-old man develops a myocardial infarction. His condition improves and he is discharged from the hospital. He is then prescribed 325 mg aspirin daily. This drug inhibits platelet aggregation by decreasing the production of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Lipoxygenase","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"Thromboxane A₂","bool":true},{"option":"Clotting factor","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclooxygenase","bool":false}],"id":515},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A 55-year-old man is diagnosed with pulmonary embolism. He is admitted to the hospital and started on heparin therapy. The anticoagulant effect of this drug would be the most appropriately assessed by which of the following laboratory values?","answers":[{"option":"International normalized ratio (INR)","bool":false},{"option":"Activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT)","bool":true},{"option":"Bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin time (PT)","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false}],"id":516},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A 60-year-old man with severe chest pain is unresponsive to sublingual nitroglycerin. A thrombolytic therapy is initiated. If streptokinase is given to this patient, it may produce thrombolysis after binding which of the following proteins?","answers":[{"option":"Antithrombin III","bool":false},{"option":"Protein C","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombomodulin","bool":false},{"option":"Plasminogen","bool":true},{"option":"Fibrin","bool":false}],"id":517},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A 60-year-old woman had a mitral valve replacement and was placed on anticoagulants and prophylactics following her surgery. Five days after her surgery, she developed an erythematous rash on her thigh. Two days after the rash appeared, a large hemorrhage bulla then began to form in the area of the rash. Which of the following medications most likely caused the rash?","answers":[{"option":"Heparin","bool":true},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Cefazoline","bool":false},{"option":"Vancomycin","bool":false}],"id":518},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A 7-year-old child has accidentally overdosed on iron supplements. Which of the following agents can be used as an antidote in this child?","answers":[{"option":"Acetylcysteine","bool":false},{"option":"Protamine","bool":false},{"option":"Deferoxamine","bool":true},{"option":"Phytonadione","bool":false},{"option":"Amyl nitrite","bool":false}],"id":519},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A child is suffering from chronic granulomatous disease. He has a genetic deficiency due to which he is more prone to infections, especially staphylococcal infection. Why is this?","answers":[{"option":"Decreased superoxide radical","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased phosphorylative ability","bool":false},{"option":"Lack of antibody coating","bool":false},{"option":"Lack of NADPH oxidase system","bool":true},{"option":"Absence of cofactors such as iodine and bromine","bool":false}],"id":520},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A middle-aged female with a known case of rheumatoid arthritis consulted her physician during her follow-up visit. On examination, she was found to have splenomegaly two fingers below the left costal margin. Lab results show anemia and neutropenia. She is currently on NSAIDs and low-dose steroid treatment. What is the cause of her splenomegaly?","answers":[{"option":"Malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Viral fever","bool":false},{"option":"Septicimia","bool":false},{"option":"Drug induced","bool":false},{"option":"Felty's syndrome","bool":true}],"id":521},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which type of epidemiology interprets the therapeutic and preventive measures?","answers":[{"option":"Descriptive epidemiology","bool":false},{"option":"Environmental epidemiology","bool":false},{"option":"Observational epidemiology","bool":true},{"option":"Experimental epidemiology","bool":false},{"option":"Analytic epidemiology","bool":false}],"id":522},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What type of hypersensitivity reaction is involved in serum sickness?","answers":[{"option":"Type I","bool":false},{"option":"Type II","bool":false},{"option":"Type III and IV","bool":false},{"option":"Type IV","bool":false},{"option":"Type III","bool":true}],"id":523},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"In which of the following diseases are anti-neuronal antibodies formed?","answers":[{"option":"Psoriasis","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE)","bool":true},{"option":"Bannwarth's syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune hepatitis","bool":false},{"option":"Rheumatoid arthritis","bool":false}],"id":524},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What type of red blood cells are seen in iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Microcytic, hypochromic","bool":true},{"option":"Macrocytic, hypochromic","bool":false},{"option":"Normocytic, hyperchromic","bool":false},{"option":"Normocytic, normochromic","bool":false},{"option":"Microcytic, hyperchromic","bool":false}],"id":525},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Once an inflammatory response is mediated by the complement activation, an acute increase in the levels of which of the following can be observed?","answers":[{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"T-lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"B-lymphocytes","bool":false}],"id":526},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What type of antibodies are produced in the Arthus reaction?","answers":[{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":true},{"option":"IgA","bool":false}],"id":527},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of these results in the reduction of the formation of methemoglobin from hemoglobin?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin A","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin E","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin D","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":true}],"id":528},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A 5-year-old girl accidentally touches a bowl of hot soup. Her right-hand skin develops erythema and blisters form on the pads of her fingers. What kind of inflammation is this?","answers":[{"option":"Ulceration","bool":false},{"option":"Serous inflammation","bool":true},{"option":"Granulomatous inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinoid inflammation","bool":false}],"id":529},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A 12-year-old male is suffering from beta-thalassemia major. Which one of the following is the most important factor resulting in iron overload in his body?","answers":[{"option":"Elevated hepcidin levels","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic blood transfusion and low hepcidin levels","bool":true},{"option":"Increased hemolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic blood transfusion","bool":false},{"option":"Low hepcidin levels","bool":false}],"id":530},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A pathologist examines a hemoglobin electrophoresis slide of a patient suffering from beta-thalassemia trait. Which hemoglobin will most likely be seen?","answers":[{"option":"HbA2","bool":true},{"option":"HbF","bool":false},{"option":"HbH","bool":false},{"option":"HbA1C","bool":false},{"option":"HbA1","bool":false}],"id":531},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What is the function of the Fc portion of the antibody?","answers":[{"option":"Blocking ligand-receptor interactions","bool":false},{"option":"Phagocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Antigen binding","bool":false},{"option":"Complement fixation","bool":true},{"option":"Class switiching","bool":false}],"id":532},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"What are the antigens that are expressed in the fetal state and in the tumor cells called?","answers":[{"option":"Oncofetal antigens","bool":true},{"option":"Fraternal antigens","bool":false},{"option":"Oncofetal maternal antigens","bool":false},{"option":"Neonatal antigens","bool":false},{"option":"Cryptic antigens","bool":false}],"id":533},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Deficiency of which enzyme is the cause of hereditary coproporphyria (HCP)?","answers":[{"option":"Ferrochelatase","bool":false},{"option":"Porphobilinogen deaminase","bool":false},{"option":"Coproporphyrinogen oxidase","bool":true},{"option":"Uroporphobilinogen oxidase","bool":false},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen-III synthase","bool":false}],"id":534},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"For the routine blood sample test in the lab upon the centrifugation of the blood, a yellow color fluid is obtained\r\nthat differs from the plasma in one component. Which of these would most likely be that component?","answers":[{"option":"Sugar/carbohydrate","bool":false},{"option":"Inorganic components/electrolytes","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":true},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Globulin","bool":false}],"id":535},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is true about the lymph nodes?","answers":[{"option":"There is a dense medulla present","bool":false},{"option":"Reticular fibers are present in parenchyma","bool":false},{"option":"Peripheral subcapsular sinus is present","bool":true},{"option":"B-cells are present in paracortex","bool":false},{"option":"All of the options are true","bool":false}],"id":536},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"During the development of red blood cells, a cell is formed having 34% of hemoglobin content, a condensed nucleus, with its endoplasmic reticulum reabsorbed. Which of the following is that cell?","answers":[{"option":"Basophilic erythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Polychromatophilic erythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyte","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocyte","bool":false}],"id":537},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A person is suffering from a disease but he is healthy and shows no signs and symptoms because of preventative measures he took for his health post-diagnosis. What type of prevention is this?","answers":[{"option":"Primary prevention","bool":false},{"option":"Early detection","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary prevention","bool":true},{"option":"Tertiary prevention","bool":false},{"option":"Rehabilitation","bool":false}],"id":538},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which substance is present on the plasma membrane of platelets that does not let them bind to the normal\r\nendothelium but instead adhere to the damaged vessels; especially to their exposed collagen?","answers":[{"option":"Coat of glycoprotein","bool":true},{"option":"Actin and myosin","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium ions","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombosthenin","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandin","bool":false}],"id":539},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"In a sample of blood, antisera A and B show agglutination while antiserum D doesn’t. What would the blood type be?","answers":[{"option":"A positive","bool":false},{"option":"O positive","bool":false},{"option":"O negative","bool":false},{"option":"AB positive","bool":false},{"option":"AB negative","bool":true}],"id":540},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"If the genotype of a person is OO, what would the phenotype be?","answers":[{"option":"Agglutinogen A, agglutinin A","bool":false},{"option":"No agglutinogens, agglutinins A and B","bool":true},{"option":"Agglutinogens A & B, agglutinins A & B","bool":false},{"option":"Agglutinogens B, A agglutinins","bool":false},{"option":"No agglutinogens, agglutinin A","bool":false}],"id":541},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Hemoglobin is broken down into heme and globin followed by the conversion of biliverdin into bilirubin. Inside the hepatic system, what does bilirubin gets conjugated with?","answers":[{"option":"Ascorbic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Sulfate","bool":false},{"option":"Globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Glucuronic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false}],"id":542},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A woman with damage to the mitral valve of the heart is placed on warfarin therapy. Which of the following may be used to follow the anticoagulant activity?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Activated partial thromboplastin clotting time (aPTT)","bool":false},{"option":"Bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"The prothrombin time test/ International normalized ratio (PT/INR)","bool":true},{"option":"Complete blood picture","bool":false}],"id":543},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following lymphocyte is involved in frontline defense against tumor cells without any previous exposure?","answers":[{"option":"Natural killer (NK) cells","bool":true},{"option":"Cytotoxic T-lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"CD4+T cells","bool":false},{"option":"CD8+T cells","bool":false},{"option":"B-lymphocytes","bool":false}],"id":544},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A woman's hemoglobin level is 15 g/100ml. How much oxygen will be present in 100ml?","answers":[{"option":"25 ml","bool":false},{"option":"15 ml","bool":false},{"option":"20 ml","bool":true},{"option":"30 ml","bool":false},{"option":"40 ml","bool":false}],"id":545},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following factors is involved in the prevention of the spread of the clot to nearby tissues?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombin and thrombomodulin","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombomodulin","bool":false},{"option":"Plasminogen","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin","bool":false}],"id":546},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is not a common pathway for the spread of metastasis?","answers":[{"option":"Seeding of cavities","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Local invasion","bool":true},{"option":"Hematogenous","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphatics","bool":false}],"id":547},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"The membrane of red blood cells is covered with antibodies that allow which of the following to consume them after they are worn out?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false}],"id":548},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"At which stage do the cancer cells undergo apoptosis?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Before M","bool":false},{"option":"After G1","bool":true},{"option":"After S","bool":false},{"option":"At restriction point","bool":false}],"id":549},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is the cause for graft rejection?","answers":[{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Cytotoxic T cells","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"CD4+ cells","bool":false},{"option":"B cells","bool":false}],"id":550},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"A man was brought into the outpatient department (OPD) after a few hours of having a high-grade fever and cough. His white blood cells count is 13 000/μl (i.e. >7000), platelets is 310,000/mm^3, hemoglobin is 14 g/dL and RBC count is 4.5 million/mm^3. Which leukocyte would be present in abundance here?","answers":[{"option":"T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"B-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false}],"id":551},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2020"],"question":"Within how many hours is the epithelialization of the suture wounds completed?","answers":[{"option":"72 hours","bool":true},{"option":"24 hours","bool":false},{"option":"48 hours","bool":false},{"option":"36 hours","bool":false},{"option":"96 hours","bool":false}],"id":552},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following does not have a capsule?","answers":[{"option":"Palatine tonsils","bool":false},{"option":"Peyer's patches","bool":true},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph node","bool":false}],"id":553},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"After a long bone fracture, when is a fat embolism likely to occur?","answers":[{"option":"After 1 hour","bool":false},{"option":"After 24 hours","bool":false},{"option":"After 1-3 days","bool":true},{"option":"After 1 month","bool":false},{"option":"After 1 week","bool":false}],"id":554},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"A 34-year-old woman is evaluated at the hospital and found to have a large ovarian cyst. During surgery of the cysts, it is found to contain cheesy material, teeth, and hair. What is this type of cyst called?","answers":[{"option":"Mucinous cyst","bool":false},{"option":"Cystadenoma","bool":false},{"option":"Chocolate cyst","bool":false},{"option":"Mature cystic teratoma","bool":true},{"option":"Cystadenocarcinoma","bool":false}],"id":555},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"A 60-year-old male presents to the outpatient department with complaints of burning micturition and fever. On examination, blood pressure is 90/60 mm of Hg, and heart rate is 110 beats/min. The physician also notices blood oozing from a cannulation site. A complete blood count shows low hemoglobin, high WBC count, and low platelet count. Further investigation reveals prolonged PT and aPTT. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Idiopathic autoimmune thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":true}],"id":556},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"If there is a defect of the mesoderm, which cells are primarily affected?","answers":[{"option":"Nurse cells","bool":false},{"option":"Thymic epithelial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Neural crest cells","bool":false},{"option":"Thymocytes","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":557},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is formed by complement activation?","answers":[{"option":"Membrane attack complex","bool":true},{"option":"Antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":false},{"option":"Antigens","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false}],"id":558},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"A patient was given a few milliliters of blood after which he developed an immediate reaction consisting of fever, hypotension, tachypnea, and tachycardia. Which of the following is true about this kind of reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Host cells and donor complement proteins react","bool":false},{"option":"Donor cells and host complement proteins react","bool":false},{"option":"Donor antibodies attack host cells","bool":false},{"option":"The reaction is due to preformed IgE granules","bool":false},{"option":"Host antibodies attack donor cells","bool":true}],"id":559},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"The receptor for IgG is present on phagocytes. Which of the following are phagocytes?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages and lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophage and neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":560},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is correct regarding individuals with blood group A?","answers":[{"option":"They may give blood for transfusion to person of blood group O","bool":false},{"option":"They may have phenotype AB","bool":false},{"option":"They may have children with blood group A and O only","bool":false},{"option":"They have B antigens","bool":false},{"option":"They have anti-B antibodies in their plasma","bool":true}],"id":561},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"What are plasma cells derived from?","answers":[{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":false},{"option":"B lymphocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Astrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false}],"id":562},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following lymphatic tissues is characterized by the presence of subcapsular sinus?","answers":[{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Tonsil","bool":false},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false},{"option":"Peyer's patch","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph node","bool":true}],"id":563},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which model of disease causation is used when agent, host, and environment are considered?","answers":[{"option":"Population pyramid","bool":false},{"option":"Wheel model","bool":false},{"option":"Web of causation","bool":false},{"option":"Epidemiological triad","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":564},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which antibody acts as a B cell antigen receptor and plays a role in B cell maturation, maintenance, silencing, and activation?","answers":[{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":true},{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false}],"id":565},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which type of cancer is the squamous cell carcinoma of the lungs?","answers":[{"option":"Benign tumor of epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Malignant tumor of mesenchyme","bool":false},{"option":"Malignant tumor of epithelium","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Benign tumor of mesenchyme","bool":false}],"id":566},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is used to detect hereditary spherocytosis?","answers":[{"option":"Serum B12 levels","bool":false},{"option":"Osmotic fragility test","bool":true},{"option":"MCHC","bool":false},{"option":"MCV","bool":false},{"option":"RBC count","bool":false}],"id":567},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Hemophilia A is characterized by the deficiency of which factors?","answers":[{"option":"Factor IX","bool":false},{"option":"Tissue factor","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VIII","bool":true},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":false},{"option":"Factor X","bool":false}],"id":568},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is an indication for prenatal diagnostic tests?","answers":[{"option":"Mother taking no medication","bool":false},{"option":"Family history of cigarette smoking","bool":false},{"option":"Past history of neural tube defects","bool":true},{"option":"Maternal age < 15 years","bool":false},{"option":"Maternal age < 30 years","bool":false}],"id":569},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is incorrect regarding the histology of the spleen?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils are the predominant cells of the periarteriolar lymphoid sheaths (PALS)","bool":true},{"option":"White pulp contains leukocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Littoral cells are found in splenic sinusoids","bool":false},{"option":"Red pulp contains sinusoids","bool":false},{"option":"The spleen contains cords of Billroth","bool":false}],"id":570},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following results from the deficiency of uroporphyrinogen decarboxylase?","answers":[{"option":"Acute intermittent porphyria","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary coproporphyria","bool":false},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Variegate porphyria","bool":false},{"option":"Porphyria cutanea tarda","bool":true}],"id":571},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"To slow down the coagulation process, thrombin binds to which of the following proteins?","answers":[{"option":"Protein C","bool":false},{"option":"Protein S","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombomodulin","bool":true},{"option":"Factor VIII","bool":false}],"id":572},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"A first-year medical student has a fever and sore throat. The physician prescribes Ibuprofen. Which process is involved in relieving the pain and fever?","answers":[{"option":"It irreversibly inhibits cyclooxygenase, reducing prostaglandin production","bool":false},{"option":"It reversibly inhibits phospholipase A2, reducing arachidonic acid production","bool":false},{"option":"It reversibly inhibits cyclooxygenase, reducing prostaglandin production","bool":true},{"option":"It irreversibly inhibits phospholipase A2, reducing arachidonic acid production","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":573},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"A venous embolism is likely to cause an infarct in which of the following organs?","answers":[{"option":"Alll of these","bool":false},{"option":"Lung","bool":true},{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Testis","bool":false},{"option":"Heart","bool":false}],"id":574},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"What is the sudden occurrence of cases in a relatively larger geographical area with more than one focal point known as?","answers":[{"option":"Sporadic","bool":false},{"option":"Outbreak","bool":false},{"option":"Endemic","bool":false},{"option":"Epidemic","bool":true},{"option":"Pandemic","bool":false}],"id":575},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following lymphoid organs has stratified squamous epithelial lining?","answers":[{"option":"Thymus","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Palatine tonsil","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false}],"id":576},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following factors is deficient in hemophilia B?","answers":[{"option":"Factor X","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VIII","bool":false},{"option":"Factor IX","bool":true},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":false},{"option":"Tissue factor","bool":false}],"id":577},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following leads to a decrease in plasma oncotic pressure?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphatic obstruction","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperproteinemia","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma albumin decrement","bool":true}],"id":578},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is correct regarding hereditary spherocytosis?","answers":[{"option":"Spherocytes with increased central pallor","bool":false},{"option":"Increased osmotic fragility","bool":true},{"option":"Low MCHC","bool":false},{"option":"High MCV","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":579},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"In the oxygen-hemoglobin dissociation curve, a decrease in pH will lead to which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Increased affinity of hemoglobin to CO2","bool":false},{"option":"No change","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased affinity of hemoglobin to CO2","bool":false},{"option":"Curve shift to the left","bool":false},{"option":"Curve shift to the right","bool":true}],"id":580},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is correct regarding the factors affecting the affinity of hemoglobin for O2?","answers":[{"option":"Increases with decrease in pH","bool":false},{"option":"Decreases with increase in 2,3-BPG","bool":true},{"option":"Increases with increase in CO2","bool":false},{"option":"Increases with increase in temperature","bool":false},{"option":"Decreases with increase in pH","bool":false}],"id":581},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Congenital deficiency of a specific protein leads to the inability to transport conjugated bilirubin out of the liver and into the bile. This statement is most relevant for which of the following diseases?","answers":[{"option":"Crigler-Najjar syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Gilbert syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Physiologic jaundice of the newborn","bool":false},{"option":"Dubin-Johnson syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Obstructive jaundice","bool":false}],"id":582},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Blood is a special type of connective tissue. Which of the following is correct regarding it?","answers":[{"option":"It contains fibers only","bool":false},{"option":"It contains both cells and fibers","bool":false},{"option":"It has a greater proportion of cells as compared to fibers","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Its ground substance is of a fluid nature","bool":true}],"id":583},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which antibody crosses the placenta during erythroblastosis fetalis?","answers":[{"option":"IgG","bool":true},{"option":"IgM","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false}],"id":584},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which antibody is dimeric with a J chain?","answers":[{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":true},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false}],"id":585},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which antibody isotype is the most abundant in serum?","answers":[{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":true},{"option":"IgM","bool":false}],"id":586},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following may result from frequent blood transfusions?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Wilson disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hemochromatosis","bool":true},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false}],"id":587},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which type of hemoglobin prevents symptoms of thalassemia from appearing in neonatal life?","answers":[{"option":"HbC","bool":false},{"option":"HbA","bool":false},{"option":"HbS","bool":false},{"option":"HbA2","bool":false},{"option":"HbF","bool":true}],"id":588},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which protein plays a major role in maintaining oncotic pressure and transportation of lipids and steroids?","answers":[{"option":"C-reactive protein (CRP)","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":true},{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Globulin","bool":false}],"id":589},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"How many oxygen molecules bind to a single hemoglobin molecule?","answers":[{"option":"4","bool":true},{"option":"8","bool":false},{"option":"3","bool":false},{"option":"16","bool":false},{"option":"2","bool":false}],"id":590},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"What is secreted as a result of degranulation of platelets?","answers":[{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"NO (nitric oxide)","bool":false},{"option":"Thromboxane A2","bool":true},{"option":"Lipoxins","bool":false},{"option":"NO synthase","bool":false}],"id":591},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which chains are involved in the formation of hemoglobin A?","answers":[{"option":"2 alpha, 2 zeta","bool":false},{"option":"2 alpha, 2 delta","bool":false},{"option":"2 alpha, 2 epsilon","bool":false},{"option":"2 alpha, 2 gamma","bool":false},{"option":"2 alpha, 2 beta","bool":true}],"id":592},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which antibodies are released during type 2 hypersensitivity reactions?","answers":[{"option":"IgG + IgM","bool":true},{"option":"IgG + IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgD + IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgM + IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgA + IgE","bool":false}],"id":593},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"What is the most important value measured from a cross-sectional study?","answers":[{"option":"Prevalence","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Risk","bool":false},{"option":"Odds ratio","bool":false},{"option":"Incidence","bool":false}],"id":594},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following prevents blood loss in a girl who got a cut on her finger?","answers":[{"option":"Secondary plug","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet plug","bool":true},{"option":"Vasoconstriction","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoconcentration","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrin formation","bool":false}],"id":595},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Pyridoxamine, pyridoxine, and pyridoxal are forms of which vitamin?","answers":[{"option":"B3","bool":false},{"option":"B6","bool":true},{"option":"B12","bool":false},{"option":"B7","bool":false},{"option":"B9","bool":false}],"id":596},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which lymphocyte can destroy cancer cells without having to go through sensitization and hence is able to kill cancer cells in the first line of defense?","answers":[{"option":"CD8+ T cells","bool":false},{"option":"B lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Natural killer cells","bool":true},{"option":"CD4+ T cells","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false}],"id":597},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Post-streptococcal glomerulonephritis is an example of which type of hypersensitivity reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Type 2 and 3 hypersensitivity","bool":false},{"option":"Type 3 hypersensitivity","bool":true},{"option":"Type 2 hypersensitivity","bool":false},{"option":"Type 1 hypersensitivity","bool":false},{"option":"Type 4 hypersensitivity","bool":false}],"id":598},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following factors initiates the extrinsic pathway of clotting?","answers":[{"option":"Factor III","bool":true},{"option":"Factor XII","bool":false},{"option":"Factor X","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VIII","bool":false}],"id":599},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"What of the following is the iron transporter protein in the plasma?","answers":[{"option":"Apotransferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Apoferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":true},{"option":"Hemosiderin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false}],"id":600},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Erythropoietin is produced in kidneys and other cells. What is the second major source of its production?","answers":[{"option":"Bones","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":true},{"option":"Stomach","bool":false},{"option":"Adrenal cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Adrenal medulla","bool":false}],"id":601},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"The deficiency of which of the following enzymes causes erythropoietic protoporphyria?","answers":[{"option":"Uroporhyrinogen decarboxylase","bool":false},{"option":"HMB synthase","bool":false},{"option":"ALA synthase","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrochelatase","bool":true},{"option":"Uroporhyrinogen oxidase","bool":false}],"id":602},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Complete lack of glucuronidation results in which of the following diseases?","answers":[{"option":"Crigler Najjar syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Gilbert syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Ehlers–Danlos syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Dubin Johnson syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Alport syndrome","bool":false}],"id":603},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is attached to unconjugated bilirubin to form conjugated bilirubin?","answers":[{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Iron","bool":false},{"option":"Phosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Glucuronic acid","bool":true}],"id":604},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which protein shows the highest storage reserves of iron?","answers":[{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemosiderin","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":true},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false}],"id":605},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Deficiency of which of the following enzymes causes protoporphyria?","answers":[{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen oxidase","bool":false},{"option":"HMB synthase","bool":false},{"option":"ALA synthase","bool":false},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen decarboxylase","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrochelatase","bool":true}],"id":606},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following complement proteins is used to detect the activity of the immune system?","answers":[{"option":"C2","bool":false},{"option":"C1q","bool":true},{"option":"C3","bool":false},{"option":"C9","bool":false},{"option":"C5","bool":false}],"id":607},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Most of the normal human blood is composed of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Clotting factors","bool":false},{"option":"WBCs","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma","bool":true},{"option":"RBCs","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false}],"id":608},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of these is not a cardinal sign of inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Pain","bool":false},{"option":"Confusion","bool":true},{"option":"Warmth","bool":false},{"option":"Swelling","bool":false},{"option":"Redness","bool":false}],"id":609},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"In smaller vessels, platelets are responsible for vasoconstriction by releasing which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Thromboxane A2","bool":true},{"option":"ADP","bool":false},{"option":"PG-E2","bool":false},{"option":"NO","bool":false},{"option":"Prostacyclin","bool":false}],"id":610},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"According to the report published in a newspaper regarding the cholera outbreak and a large number of patients were brought to the emergency department with diarrhea, vomiting, and fever. The district house officer asked one of his team members to investigate. What is the first step in the outbreak investigation?","answers":[{"option":"Write the report","bool":false},{"option":"Confirmation of the existence of outbreak","bool":false},{"option":"Confirm number of deaths","bool":false},{"option":"Confirmation of all cases","bool":false},{"option":"Verification of diagnosis","bool":true}],"id":611},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"In heme synthesis, Fe2+ is added to protoporphyrin to form heme. Which enzyme is needed for this process?","answers":[{"option":"Ferrochelatase","bool":true},{"option":"Ferrooxidase","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrohydroxylase","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrocarboxylase","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrosynthase","bool":false}],"id":612},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which type of hemoglobin (Hb) is present in greater than normal amounts in beta-thalassemia minor?","answers":[{"option":"HbF","bool":false},{"option":"HbA2","bool":true},{"option":"HbS","bool":false},{"option":"HbC","bool":false},{"option":"HbA","bool":false}],"id":613},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"In erythroblastosis fetalis, which cells become abundant in the blood culture?","answers":[{"option":"T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Immune cells","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":true},{"option":"B-cells","bool":false}],"id":614},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Secondary prevention is the method that helps to prevent any disease or injury. Which of the following is a type of secondary prevention?","answers":[{"option":"Health education regarding routine immunization","bool":false},{"option":"Treatment after a myocardial infarction","bool":false},{"option":"Screening for breast cancer","bool":true},{"option":"Prohibition of driving without driving license","bool":false},{"option":"Rehabilitation therapy after amputation of leg","bool":false}],"id":615},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"A 20-year-old male has a history of sickle cell anemia and has repeated 2-year transfusions with a hemoglobin concentration of 8.0 g/dl. Which hemoglobin has a protective effect?","answers":[{"option":"HbC","bool":false},{"option":"HbA","bool":false},{"option":"HbF","bool":true},{"option":"HbA2","bool":false},{"option":"HbS","bool":false}],"id":616},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which vitamin deficiency causes anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Β-carotene","bool":false},{"option":"Pantothenic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Biotin","bool":false},{"option":"Ascorbic acid","bool":false}],"id":617},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which statement best describes an adenoma?","answers":[{"option":"A benign carcinoma of muscle","bool":false},{"option":"A malignant epithelial carcinoma of glands","bool":false},{"option":"A benign carcinoma of fibrous tissue","bool":false},{"option":"A benign carcinoma of cartilage","bool":false},{"option":"A benign epithelial carcinoma of glands","bool":true}],"id":618},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"A patient has been diagnosed with a malignant eye tumor in the upper right eye. His molecular analysis shows deletion of both copies of the tumor suppressor gene that checks the transition from the G1 to S phase of the cell cycle. Which of the following genes is defective?","answers":[{"option":"NF1","bool":false},{"option":"Rb-gene","bool":true},{"option":"K-Ras","bool":false},{"option":"p53","bool":false},{"option":"BCl-2","bool":false}],"id":619},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Atrophy of stomach mucosa damages the parietal cells that secrete intrinsic factor. This causes which one of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Microcytic hypochromic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Idiopathic aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":620},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following features of the adaptive immune system produces an\r\nexaggerated response?","answers":[{"option":"Antibody production","bool":false},{"option":"Delayed response","bool":false},{"option":"Immediate response","bool":false},{"option":"Antigen specificity","bool":true},{"option":"Memory","bool":false}],"id":621},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"A middle-aged woman with a history of rheumatoid arthritis consults her doctor. On examination, she is found to have splenomegaly. Her laboratory results reveal neutropenia and anemia. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Idiopathic aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Septicemia","bool":false},{"option":"Felty syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Viral infection","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":622},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Learning associated with reinforcement is associated with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Innate behavior","bool":false},{"option":"Operant learning","bool":true},{"option":"Classical conditioning","bool":false},{"option":"Modelling","bool":false},{"option":"Stimulus presenting","bool":false}],"id":623},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which protein does hemoglobin bind to after hemolysis of red blood cells?","answers":[{"option":"Hemosiderin","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Apoferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":true}],"id":624},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"What is the maximum amount of hemoglobin a red blood cell can concentrate at a given time?","answers":[{"option":"34 g/dL","bool":true},{"option":"15 g/dL","bool":false},{"option":"25 g/dL","bool":false},{"option":"21 g/dL","bool":false},{"option":"19 g/dL","bool":false}],"id":625},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following keeps the clotting factors inactivated in the blood?","answers":[{"option":"Glycocalyx of endothelium","bool":true},{"option":"Nitric oxide production","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma membrane of endothelium","bool":false},{"option":"Cholesterol on endothelium","bool":false},{"option":"Thromboxane A2 production","bool":false}],"id":626},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"A middle-aged male comes to the outpatient department with a low to high-grade fever that has been on and off for the last year and has lymphadenopathy. Lymph nodes are discrete, enlarged, non-tender, and have a rubbery consistency. The rest of the examination is unremarkable. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Viral infection","bool":false},{"option":"Connective tissue disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Sarcoidosis","bool":false}],"id":627},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is responsible for anemia due to reduced erythropoiesis?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Microangiopathic hemolysis","bool":false}],"id":628},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A biopsy specimen of the thymus is examined under a microscope and many whorl-like corpuscles are observed. Which of the following statements coincides with the corpuscles mentioned earlier?","answers":[{"option":"They have their embryological origin from mesoderm","bool":false},{"option":"They are derived from T memory cells","bool":false},{"option":"They are frequently seen in thymus of young individuals","bool":false},{"option":"They are composed of epithelial reticular cells type VI","bool":true},{"option":"They are mainly located in the thymic cortex","bool":false}],"id":629},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is a differentiating point between the lymph node and the thymus?","answers":[{"option":"The thymus is a secondary lymphoid organ","bool":false},{"option":"The thymus lacks afferent lymphatics","bool":true},{"option":"The thymus lacks efferent lymphatics","bool":false},{"option":"The thymus is derived from the mesoderm only","bool":false},{"option":"The thymus is derived from the endoderm only","bool":false}],"id":630},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A patient's blood reticulocyte count was increased after a blood loss during an accident. A reticulocyte is classified as which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"An erythrocyte","bool":false},{"option":"An immature erythrocyte","bool":true},{"option":"A agranulocyte","bool":false},{"option":"A granulocyte","bool":false},{"option":"A mature erythrocyte","bool":false}],"id":631},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In which of the following splenic areas does the breakdown of the RBCs occur?","answers":[{"option":"Red pulp","bool":true},{"option":"White pulp","bool":false},{"option":"Splenic module","bool":false},{"option":"Malphigian corpuscle","bool":false},{"option":"Periarteriolar lymphoid sheaths(PALS)","bool":false}],"id":632},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following statements best defines the process of vasculogenesis?","answers":[{"option":"It is the arise of vessels from the heart","bool":false},{"option":"It is the arise of vessels from the subclavian artery","bool":false},{"option":"It is the arise of vessels from the aorta","bool":false},{"option":"It is the arise of vessels from determined group of mesodermal cells(hemangioblasts)","bool":true},{"option":"It is the arise of vessels from pre-existing vessels","bool":false}],"id":633},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Hemangioblasts are classified as which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Ectodermal cells","bool":false},{"option":"Precursor cells","bool":false},{"option":"Endodermal cells","bool":false},{"option":"Progenitor cells","bool":true},{"option":"Mesodermal cells","bool":false}],"id":634},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Absorption of which of the following substance from the small intestine is prevented by hepcidin to avoid its accumulation in the blood?","answers":[{"option":"Magnesium","bool":false},{"option":"Iron","bool":true},{"option":"Folate","bool":false},{"option":"Copper","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":false}],"id":635},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the amount of hemoglobin present in 100 ml of red blood cells?","answers":[{"option":"Mean corpuscular volume","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin index","bool":false},{"option":"Hematocrit","bool":false},{"option":"Mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration","bool":true},{"option":"Mean corpuscular hemoglobin","bool":false}],"id":636},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A person with blood group AB+ve can safely donate blood in an emergency to a patient with which of the following blood groups?","answers":[{"option":"B+ve","bool":false},{"option":"O+ve","bool":false},{"option":"AB+ve","bool":true},{"option":"AB-ve","bool":false},{"option":"A+ve","bool":false}],"id":637},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In which of the following organs is the heme mainly converted to bilirubin?","answers":[{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":true},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false}],"id":638},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"When a serum sample is electrophoresed, which of the following band is normally absent?","answers":[{"option":"Alpha-2 globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha-1 globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Gamma globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":true}],"id":639},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A patient has been diagnosed with Hepatitis type A virus. which type of immunity will they develop in response to the above-mentioned disease?","answers":[{"option":"Innate immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Natural active immunity","bool":true},{"option":"Artificial active immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Artificial passive immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Natural passive immunity","bool":false}],"id":640},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 55-year-old man presents to the emergency room with a complaint of sudden pain in his chest. Based on his electrocardiogram(ECG) and the presence of cardiac enzymes in the blood sample, a diagnosis of myocardial infarction is made. He is given a fibrinolytic agent to dissolve the clot in his coronary blood vessel. Which of the following substance was most likely activated by this agent to dissolve the clot?","answers":[{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Bradykinin","bool":false},{"option":"Clotting factor XII","bool":false},{"option":"Plasminogen","bool":true},{"option":"Prothrombin","bool":false}],"id":641},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following factors is immediately released from the injured vascular endothelium to cause vasoconstriction?","answers":[{"option":"Thromboxane A2","bool":false},{"option":"Endothelin","bool":true},{"option":"Serotonin","bool":false},{"option":"Bradykinin","bool":false},{"option":"Vasopressin","bool":false}],"id":642},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"The first step of heme synthesis takes place in which part of the cell?","answers":[{"option":"Mitochondria","bool":true},{"option":"Lysosome","bool":false},{"option":"Peroxisome","bool":false},{"option":"Nucleolus","bool":false},{"option":"Golgi apparatus","bool":false}],"id":643},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In which of the following stages of erythropoiesis, does hemoglobin make its appearance?","answers":[{"option":"Orthochromatic erythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Colony forming unit-erythrocyte","bool":false},{"option":"Basophil erythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Proerythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Polychromatophil erythroblast","bool":true}],"id":644},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following substances promotes platelet plug formation?","answers":[{"option":"Prostacyclin","bool":false},{"option":"ADP dephosphatase","bool":false},{"option":"Thromboxane A2","bool":true},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Nitric oxide","bool":false}],"id":645},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following growth inducers promotes the growth and reproduction of all types of committed stem cells?","answers":[{"option":"Interleukin-2","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-5","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-3","bool":true},{"option":"Interleukin-1","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-4","bool":false}],"id":646},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following clotting factors initiates the extrinsic pathway of the clotting cascade?","answers":[{"option":"V","bool":false},{"option":"IV","bool":false},{"option":"VII","bool":false},{"option":"II","bool":false},{"option":"III","bool":true}],"id":647},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"The common pathway in the clotting mechanism is the activation of which of the following factors?","answers":[{"option":"IX","bool":false},{"option":"XII","bool":false},{"option":"XIII","bool":false},{"option":"X","bool":true},{"option":"XI","bool":false}],"id":648},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following ions is essential for the coagulation of blood?","answers":[{"option":"Sodium","bool":false},{"option":"Magnesium","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium","bool":true},{"option":"Pottasium","bool":false},{"option":"Chloride","bool":false}],"id":649},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following factors catalyzes the conversion of fibrinogen into fibrin?","answers":[{"option":"Plasminogen","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmin","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombin","bool":true},{"option":"Thromboplastin","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin","bool":false}],"id":650},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"The von Willebrand factor plays an important role in which of the following processes of hemostasis?","answers":[{"option":"Activation of thrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Clot dissolution","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet aggregation","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet adhesion","bool":true},{"option":"Clot formation","bool":false}],"id":651},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A patient with prolonged prothrombin time(PT) and normal activated partial prothrombin time(APTT) indicates which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Factor IV deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VIII deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Factor II deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII deficiency","bool":true}],"id":652},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which clotting factor is activated first in the intrinsic pathway of blood clotting?","answers":[{"option":"Factor IX","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":false},{"option":"Factor XII","bool":true},{"option":"Factor III","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VIII","bool":false}],"id":653},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following molecules is a primary factor in the margination of neutrophils?","answers":[{"option":"Selectin","bool":false},{"option":"Tumor necrosis factor","bool":true},{"option":"Integrin","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-8","bool":false},{"option":"Adherin","bool":false}],"id":654},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In which of the following stages of erythropoiesis, the cell has a condensed nucleus, 34 percent hemoglobin, and reabsorbed endoplasmic reticulum?","answers":[{"option":"Orthochromatic erythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Basophil erythrocyte","bool":false},{"option":"Polychromatophil erythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocyte","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyte","bool":true}],"id":655},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the most potent antigen-presenting cell, among the major types of antigen-presenting cells?","answers":[{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"B lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Helper-T cells","bool":false},{"option":"Cytotoxic-T cells","bool":false},{"option":"Dendritic cells","bool":true}],"id":656},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following changes shifts the oxygen dissociation curve to the left?","answers":[{"option":"Rise in 2,3-diphosphoglyerate","bool":false},{"option":"Rise in hydrogen ion concentration","bool":false},{"option":"Rise in pH","bool":true},{"option":"Rise in carbon di oxide tension","bool":false},{"option":"Rise in temperature","bool":false}],"id":657},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following enzymes in the heme biosynthesis pathway requires pyridoxal phosphate as a coenzyme?","answers":[{"option":"Ferrochelatase","bool":false},{"option":"Coproporphyrinogen deaminase","bool":false},{"option":"Porphobilinogen deaminase","bool":false},{"option":"Aminolevulinic acid dehydratase","bool":false},{"option":"Aminolevulinic acid synthase","bool":true}],"id":658},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"The corrin ring in cobalamin(vitamin B12), is bound to which of the following trace elements?","answers":[{"option":"Cobalt","bool":true},{"option":"Iron","bool":false},{"option":"Selenium","bool":false},{"option":"Zinc","bool":false},{"option":"Copper","bool":false}],"id":659},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Iron is transported to the bone marrow by which of the following proteins?","answers":[{"option":"Transferrin","bool":true},{"option":"C-reactive protein","bool":false},{"option":"Apoferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemosiderin","bool":false}],"id":660},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following are the regions in immunoglobulins that contain three-dimensional antigen binding sites complementary to the structure of the specific antigen?","answers":[{"option":"Crystallizable regions","bool":false},{"option":"Variable regions","bool":true},{"option":"Di-sulphide regions","bool":false},{"option":"Constant regions","bool":false},{"option":"Hinge regions","bool":false}],"id":661},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"An increase in total protein with normal levels of albumin and increased globulin is due to which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Multiple myeloma","bool":true},{"option":"Malabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Inadequate diet","bool":false},{"option":"Burns and trauma","bool":false},{"option":"Dehydration","bool":false}],"id":662},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In red blood cells, when 2,3-biphosphoglycerate combines with hemoglobin in high concentrations, it causes which of the following changes?","answers":[{"option":"No change in oxy-hemoglobin dissociation curve","bool":false},{"option":"Displacement of the oxy-hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Increased affinity of hemoglobin for oxygen","bool":false},{"option":"Shift of oxygen dissociation curve to the left","bool":false},{"option":"Shift of oxygen dissociation curve to the right","bool":true}],"id":663},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 5-year-old boy is brought to the emergency room with a history of a knee injury. On physical examination, the knee is found to be painful and swollen. The boy's mother told the physician that one of his maternal uncles died from a bleeding disorder. What is the most likely diagnosis in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Hemophilia C","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":true},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet function defect","bool":false}],"id":664},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 4-year-old boy is brought to the outpatient clinic with complaints of frequent nosebleeds and an episode of blood in his stools two months ago. His parents and his elder sister were all healthy. His mother informed the doctor, that one of her brothers was also suffering from the same symptoms. The doctor advised laboratory investigations to evaluate his coagulation profile. The disease he is suffering from has which one of the following etiologies?","answers":[{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Multigenic disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Sporadic","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked","bool":true}],"id":665},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A patient was diagnosed with megaloblastic anemia. Why should she be treated with both folic acid and vitamin B12?","answers":[{"option":"Folic acid alone causes improvement of hematologic symptoms but can cause worsening of neurologic symptoms","bool":true},{"option":"Folic acid does not work alone unless supplemented with vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid alone can cause worsening of both hematologic and neurologic symptoms","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 decreases folic acid toxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid requires vitamin B12 for activation","bool":false}],"id":666},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following mediators of inflammation cause symptoms of headache, fever, and pain in the sinuses in individuals sick with flu?","answers":[{"option":"Kinins","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotrienes","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":true},{"option":"Chemokines","bool":false}],"id":667},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 20-year-old man presents to the emergency room with complaints of developing a puffy face and difficulty breathing after eating prawns an hour ago. Which of the following inflammatory mediators is most likely responsible for this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotrienes","bool":false},{"option":"Kinins","bool":false},{"option":"Chemokines","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine","bool":true}],"id":668},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Benign and malignant tumors have different behavior patterns. Which of the following properties unequivocally denotes a tumor as being malignant?","answers":[{"option":"Ability to metastasize","bool":true},{"option":"Local invasiveness","bool":false},{"option":"Round margins","bool":false},{"option":"Encapsulation","bool":false},{"option":"Slow growth","bool":false}],"id":669},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Tumors are classified according to their degree of differentiation and can range from undifferentiated to well-differentiated. What is the term for lack of differentiation?","answers":[{"option":"Dysplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Atrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Anaplasia","bool":true},{"option":"Metaplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplasia","bool":false}],"id":670},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 30-year-old woman presents to the outpatient department with complaints of generalized weakness and shortness of breath on exertion for the past week. On examination she has pallor. Complete blood count showed a Hb of 6.0 g/dL, MCV: 55 fL, MCH: 18 pg, WBCs: 5000, platelets: 400,000. The blood smear shows a hypochromic and microcytic picture. What further investigation would you like to advise?","answers":[{"option":"Chest X-Ray","bool":false},{"option":"Serum iron profile","bool":true},{"option":"Serum B12 level","bool":false},{"option":"Serum folate level","bool":false},{"option":"Abdominal ultrasound","bool":false}],"id":671},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 35-year-old man presents to the outpatient clinic with complaints of exertion and breathlessness for the past three weeks. He was diagnosed with anemia. Laboratory investigations show normal iron levels. The physician suspects impaired ability of the bone marrow to produce normal red blood cells. What is the hallmark of this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Ringed sideroblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased myeloid precursors on bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Low folate levels","bool":true},{"option":"Low ferritin levels","bool":false},{"option":"Normochromic and normocytic cells","bool":false}],"id":672},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy presents to the pediatric outpatient department with complaints of fever and gum bleeding for the past week. A complete blood count showed pancytopenia and reticulocytopenia. The bone marrow biopsy showed hypocellular marrow. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Myeloproliferative disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Storage cell disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Acute leukemia","bool":false}],"id":673},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 25-year-old man was brought to the emergency room after his motorcycle slipped and he got several abrasive injuries. He complained of an excruciating burning sensation on the injured sites with minimal bleeding. Which of the following mechanism is most likely to reduce blood loss from his wounds?","answers":[{"option":"Protein C activation","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombin activation","bool":false},{"option":"Coagulation factors activation","bool":true},{"option":"Platelet aggregation","bool":false},{"option":"Vasoconstriction","bool":false}],"id":674},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 49-year-old bed-bound man feels shortness of breath and dies within a few minutes. Autopsy reveals a saddle embolus in the pulmonary artery. Which of the following events could likely have been his cause of death?","answers":[{"option":"Pulmonary congestion","bool":false},{"option":"Pulmonary fibrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Cardiac failure","bool":true},{"option":"Pulmonary infarction","bool":false},{"option":"Pericarditis","bool":false}],"id":675},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 62-year-old woman is diagnosed with breast cancer, which has metastasized to lymph nodes. Cancer cells often acquire growth autonomy because of mutation in genes that encode components of signaling pathways downstream of growth factor receptors. Which of the following is an important component of oncoproteins in the category of signaling molecules?","answers":[{"option":"PF3","bool":false},{"option":"RAS gene","bool":false},{"option":"Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)","bool":true},{"option":"Platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF)","bool":false},{"option":"Retinoblastoma (RB) protein","bool":false}],"id":676},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A researcher is conducting a research study to find the prevalence of diabetes mellitus in Karachi city. Which of the following epidemiological study design should be undertaken for this research","answers":[{"option":"Case control study","bool":false},{"option":"Cross sectional study","bool":true},{"option":"Case series study","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort study","bool":false},{"option":"Experimental study","bool":false}],"id":677},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A researcher is conducting a research study to find the incidence of diabetes mellitus in Karachi city. Which of the following epidemiological study design should be undertaken for this research?","answers":[{"option":"Case control study","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort study","bool":true},{"option":"Cross sectional study","bool":false},{"option":"Case series study","bool":false},{"option":"Experimental study","bool":false}],"id":678},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A lecturer was teaching his student a very simple form of epidemiological study designs. He explained this type of study is based on a unique condition or rare disease reported by a consultant in a patient. Which of the following study designs is the lecturer referring to?","answers":[{"option":"Case control study","bool":false},{"option":"Cross sectional study","bool":false},{"option":"Randomized control trial","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort study","bool":false},{"option":"Case report","bool":true}],"id":679},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A group of students was analyzing their research data set. The data showed that the frequency distribution of age of the study participants had a long tail on the right-hand side of the curve than on the left side. Which of the following describes this frequency distribution?","answers":[{"option":"Standard","bool":false},{"option":"Gaussian","bool":false},{"option":"Skewed","bool":true},{"option":"Precise","bool":false},{"option":"Normal","bool":false}],"id":680},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A professor of epidemiology was teaching epidemiological study designs to his students. He was emphasizing how to follow up with the patients and how to reduce loss to follow up in an observational study. The professor is teaching his students about which of the following epidemiological study designs?","answers":[{"option":"Cross sectional study","bool":false},{"option":"Experimental study","bool":false},{"option":"Case series study","bool":false},{"option":"Case control study","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort study","bool":true}],"id":681},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"EPI Program in Pakistan offers immunization to young children against various endemic infectious diseases including polio, diphtheria, tetanus, and measles. The routine immunization of young children is an example of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Selective prevention","bool":false},{"option":"Primary prevention","bool":true},{"option":"Secondary prevention","bool":false},{"option":"Outbreak control","bool":false},{"option":"Tertiary prevention","bool":false}],"id":682},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 15-year-old patient is diagnosed with a connective tissue disorder. The disorder involves a protein called fibrillin, encoded by the FBN1 gene that maps to chromosomal locus 15q21. Mutations in the FBN1 gene are found in all patients suffering from which of the following diseases?","answers":[{"option":"Severe combined immunodeficiency (SCID)","bool":false},{"option":"Ehlers-Danlos syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Marfan syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Cystic fibrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Tay-Sachs disease","bool":false}],"id":683},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 33-year-old patient is diagnosed with leukemia. A fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) report of the DNA analysis of the tumor cells has the term \"Philadelphia chromosome\". Which of the following molecular events leads to the formation of this chromosome?","answers":[{"option":"Trinucleotide repeats","bool":false},{"option":"Point mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Duplication","bool":false},{"option":"Translocation","bool":true},{"option":"Deletion","bool":false}],"id":684},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 30-year-old man is brought to the emergency room with a complaint of severe chest pain for the past hour. He is diagnosed with unstable angina secondary to familial hypercholesterolemia. Familial hypercholesterolemia is an autosomal dominant disorder. If an affected person marries an unaffected person, what are the chances of the offspring developing the disorder?","answers":[{"option":"One in five","bool":false},{"option":"One in ten","bool":false},{"option":"One in two","bool":true},{"option":"Cent percent","bool":false},{"option":"One in four","bool":false}],"id":685},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"An approach to psychology focuses on observable behavior that can be measured objectively. It implies that our behavior is related to our environment and we can modify our behavior by modifying our environment. Which of the following paradigms includes this approach?","answers":[{"option":"Psychodynamic approach","bool":false},{"option":"Cognitive approach","bool":false},{"option":"Humanistic approach","bool":false},{"option":"Behavioral approach","bool":true},{"option":"Learning","bool":false}],"id":686},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A type of learning in which a neutral stimulus is presented repeatedly with one that reflexively elicits a particular response so that the neutral stimulus eventually the response itself, is known as classical conditioning. After a conditioned response becomes extinct, the response can re-emerge after a while has passed with no further conditioning. What is this event referred to?","answers":[{"option":"Stimulant generalization","bool":false},{"option":"Operant conditioning","bool":false},{"option":"Learning","bool":false},{"option":"Spontaneous recovery","bool":true},{"option":"Extinction","bool":false}],"id":687},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy has a history of easy bruising and hemarthrosis. He is diagnosed with hemophilia B. Which of the following factors is deficient in hemophilia B?","answers":[{"option":"Factor X","bool":false},{"option":"Factor XII","bool":false},{"option":"Factor IX","bool":true},{"option":"Factor VIII","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":false}],"id":688},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"One of the psychological theories of child development refers to developing relationships between the child and significant others in the child's life, especially the mother. Early internalized relationships affect children as they become adults and develop their own personalities. In adult life, a transitional phenomenon can be expressed as a means of playing with one's own ideas and developing creative and new thoughts. What is this theory known as?","answers":[{"option":"Object relation psychology","bool":true},{"option":"Relational psychoanalysis","bool":false},{"option":"Self psychology","bool":false},{"option":"Drive theory","bool":false},{"option":"Ego psychology","bool":false}],"id":689},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In one of the stages of cognitive development, the child learns to use language and symbols to represent things but does not comprehend certain operations (like logically separating, combining, and transforming information). Thinking is still egocentric: having difficulty in taking the viewpoint of others. This stage has not yet attained conservation in terms of the understanding that the amount of a substance remains the same even when its form is changed. What is this stage known as?","answers":[{"option":"The concrete operational stage","bool":false},{"option":"The sensorimotor stage","bool":false},{"option":"The social development stage","bool":false},{"option":"The formal operational stage","bool":false},{"option":"The preoperational stage","bool":true}],"id":690},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following conditions is not an example of shock associated with systemic inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Myocardial Infarction","bool":true},{"option":"Burns","bool":false},{"option":"Pancreatitis","bool":false},{"option":"Trauma","bool":false},{"option":"Fingal or microbial infection","bool":false}],"id":691},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 55-year-old man presents to the outpatient department with stomach issues. On examination, he has massive splenomegaly seen (crossing the umbilicus). Which of the following conditions is he most likely to have?","answers":[{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false}],"id":692},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is used to normalize blood flow by fibrinolysis of fibrin?","answers":[{"option":"Plasmin","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Protein C","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false}],"id":693},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Deficiency of which of the following options can lead to an accumulation of homocysteine?","answers":[{"option":"Biotin","bool":false},{"option":"Niacin","bool":false},{"option":"Ascorbic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Riboflavin","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid","bool":true}],"id":694},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following helps in the absorption of iron?","answers":[{"option":"Calcium","bool":false},{"option":"Ascorbic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B7","bool":false},{"option":"Niacin","bool":false}],"id":695},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which immunoglobulin helps in opsonization?","answers":[{"option":"IgG","bool":true},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":false}],"id":696},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following options is the functionally active form of folic acid?","answers":[{"option":"Tetrahydrofolic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Monoglutamate","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamate","bool":false},{"option":"5-methyltetrahydrofolic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Polyglutamate","bool":false}],"id":697},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following fluids is similar in electrolyte and water fraction to plasma?","answers":[{"option":"Synovial fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Amniotic fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Interstitial fluid","bool":true},{"option":"Cerebrospinal fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Intracellular fluid","bool":false}],"id":698},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following corresponds to the percentage of HbA2 in adults?","answers":[{"option":"6-7%","bool":false},{"option":"1-5%","bool":false},{"option":"2-3%","bool":true},{"option":"1.5-1.9%","bool":false},{"option":"3.5-4.5%","bool":false}],"id":699},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"At which of the following stages should a RhoGAM be administered to prevent erythroblastosis fetalis?","answers":[{"option":"One week before pregnancy","bool":false},{"option":"7th month of pregnancy","bool":true},{"option":"After birth","bool":false},{"option":"Few weeks after birth","bool":false},{"option":"One month after birth","bool":false}],"id":700},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the site of production of 90% erythropoietin?","answers":[{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":true}],"id":701},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In which of the following organs do blood islands first form first?","answers":[{"option":"Yolk sac or umbilical vesicle","bool":true},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false}],"id":702},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 50-year-old woman is admitted to the hospital after a transient ischemic attack. She has been bedridden for the past 4 days and develops sudden onset pain and edema in her right leg. Ultrasound confirms the presence of deep venous thrombosis. Which of the following is the most likely cause of her condition?","answers":[{"option":"Age factor","bool":false},{"option":"Immobilization","bool":true},{"option":"Alcohol consumption","bool":false},{"option":"Infection","bool":false},{"option":"Pregnancy","bool":false}],"id":703},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which is the main site of hematopoiesis in the second trimester?","answers":[{"option":"Yolk sac","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":true},{"option":"Liver","bool":false}],"id":704},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"What is the most underdeveloped special sense in neonates?","answers":[{"option":"Taste","bool":false},{"option":"Touch","bool":false},{"option":"Visual acuity","bool":true},{"option":"Hearing","bool":false},{"option":"Olfaction","bool":false},{"option":"Phonation","bool":false}],"id":705},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following structures does membrane attack complex (MAC) attach to during complement system activation?","answers":[{"option":"Lipid part of cell membrane","bool":true},{"option":"Mitochondrial membrane","bool":false},{"option":"Proteins channels on cell surface","bool":false},{"option":"Thin cell wall","bool":false},{"option":"Bacteria inside cells","bool":false}],"id":706},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which structure is defective in the genetic disorder Marfan syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Myelin sheath","bool":false},{"option":"Collagen","bool":false},{"option":"Low-density lipoprotein (LDL) receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrillin-1","bool":true},{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":false}],"id":707},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Complement activation leads to the formation of a membrane attack complex (MAC), which causes the lysis of the cell. By which mechanism does MAC work?","answers":[{"option":"Opsonization","bool":false},{"option":"Inducing damage to pathogen by reactive oxygen species (ROS)","bool":false},{"option":"Lysis of microbes with susceptible cell membranes","bool":true},{"option":"Inhibition of microbe replication","bool":false},{"option":"Binding to and neutralization of bacterial toxins","bool":false}],"id":708},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"During leukocyte migration, the process of upregulation of selectins and integrins is referred to as which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Chemotaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Adhesion cascade","bool":false},{"option":"Diapedesis","bool":false},{"option":"Margination","bool":true},{"option":"Leukotriene synthesis","bool":false}],"id":709},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which is not a cause of microcytic hypochromic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Lead poisoning","bool":false},{"option":"Increased red blood cell destruction","bool":true},{"option":"Mutations in the ALAS2 gene","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Abnormalities in hemoglobin chains","bool":false}],"id":710},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is least likely to cause vitamin B12 deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Pregnancy","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperthyroidism","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic infection","bool":false},{"option":"Dietary intake","bool":true},{"option":"Cancer","bool":false}],"id":711},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"What protein is found in plasma, but not in serum, and can appear as a distinct band on electrophoresis that may sometimes be confused with multiple myeloma?","answers":[{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":true},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Myoglobin","bool":false}],"id":712},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A group of students collected data consisting of 10 variables, including 1 constant variable. Which type of chart or graph should they use to plot their data?","answers":[{"option":"Histogram","bool":false},{"option":"Scatter Plot","bool":false},{"option":"Line Graph","bool":false},{"option":"Pie Chart","bool":false},{"option":"Bar Chart","bool":true}],"id":713},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"An elderly man presents with chronic abdominal pain and an enlarged spleen. Which disease is most likely responsible for his symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Idiopathic autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Myeloproliferative disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":714},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"What type of graph is most likely to show a left and right skewed curve?","answers":[{"option":"Pie chart","bool":false},{"option":"Line graph","bool":false},{"option":"Scatter plot","bool":false},{"option":"Histogram","bool":true},{"option":"Box plot","bool":false}],"id":715},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Proteolysis of which of the following components is a critical step during complement activation?","answers":[{"option":"C4","bool":false},{"option":"C1","bool":false},{"option":"C9","bool":false},{"option":"C3","bool":true},{"option":"C5","bool":false}],"id":716},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A young female patient presents to the outpatient department with complaints of bleeding and rashes on her body. On physical examination, she has petechiae on her body, and laboratory findings show low platelets with megakaryocytes. Prothrombin time (PT) and activated partial thrombin time (aPTT) are in a normal range. Which of the following condition does she most likely have?","answers":[{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":true},{"option":"Thalassemia minor","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K deficiency","bool":false}],"id":717},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"An 18-year-old complains of fatigue and shortness of breath. Her mean corpuscular volume (MCV) is 60 femtolitre and her mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH) is 22 picogram. Which of the following is true for the morphology of her red blood cells?","answers":[{"option":"Microcytic normochromic","bool":false},{"option":"Macrocytic normochromic","bool":false},{"option":"Normocytic normochromic","bool":false},{"option":"Microcytic hypochromic","bool":true},{"option":"Normocytic hypochromic","bool":false}],"id":718},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which plasma protein is commonly measured to indicate infection or inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Immunoglobulins","bool":false},{"option":"Complement proteins","bool":false},{"option":"C-reactive protein","bool":true},{"option":"Coagulation factors","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false}],"id":719},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is released from granulocytes in an allergic reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Prostaglandins","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine","bool":true},{"option":"Interleukin-1","bool":false},{"option":"Leukotrienes","bool":false},{"option":"IgE antibody","bool":false}],"id":720},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following mechanisms attracts leukocytes toward the site of infection?","answers":[{"option":"Chemotaxis","bool":true},{"option":"Inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Opsonization","bool":false},{"option":"Diapedesis","bool":false},{"option":"Phagocytosis","bool":false}],"id":721},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which disease occurs when the hydrophilic amino acid glutamic acid is replaced by the hydrophobic amino acid valine at position 6 in the globin chain?","answers":[{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Hemoglobin C disease","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Cystic fibrosis","bool":false}],"id":722},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which chromosome is affected in β-thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Chromosome18","bool":false},{"option":"Chromososme 9","bool":false},{"option":"Chromosome 16","bool":false},{"option":"Chromososme 17","bool":false},{"option":"Chromosome 11","bool":true}],"id":723},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the genetic inheritance of hemophilia A?","answers":[{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":true},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"It is not a genetic disorder","bool":false}],"id":724},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which vitamin is required for the conversion of 5-methyl-tetrahydrofolate to tetrahydrofolate in the conversion of homocysteine to methionine?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin B6","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin A","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin B9","bool":false}],"id":725},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is considered negative reinforcement?","answers":[{"option":"Reward prevents the repetition of behavior","bool":false},{"option":"Punishment will prevent the repetition of behaviour","bool":false},{"option":"Removal of painful situations will encourage the repetition of behavior","bool":true},{"option":"An upleasant stimulus encourages the repetition of behavior","bool":false},{"option":"Removal of reward prevents the repetition of behavior","bool":false}],"id":726},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In which of the following forms is dietary folate present?","answers":[{"option":"Monoglutamate","bool":false},{"option":"Monoaspartate","bool":false},{"option":"Monosulfate","bool":false},{"option":"Polyglutamate","bool":true},{"option":"Polyaspartate","bool":false}],"id":727},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following represents the clinicopathological representation of Arthus reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Cutaneous vasculitis","bool":true},{"option":"Systemic vasculitis","bool":false},{"option":"Nephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute arthritis","bool":false},{"option":"Skin lesions","bool":false}],"id":728},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Leucocytes reach the inflamed tissue by which of the following process?","answers":[{"option":"Chemotaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Amoeboid movement","bool":false},{"option":"Margination","bool":false},{"option":"Rolling","bool":false},{"option":"Diapedesis","bool":true}],"id":729},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is a type II hypersensitivity reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Serum sickness","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE)","bool":false},{"option":"Type 1 diabetes mellitus","bool":false},{"option":"Bronchial asthma","bool":false},{"option":"Mysthania gravis","bool":true}],"id":730},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Where are hemangioblasts formed?","answers":[{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Mesoderm","bool":true},{"option":"Yolk sac","bool":false}],"id":731},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"A 65-year-old man presented to the outpatient department with complaints of cough and fever. He was diagnosed with acute respiratory infection/inflammation. On a complete blood picture (CBC) test, which of the following leukocyte will be most abundant?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocyte","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Monocyte","bool":false}],"id":732},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Which one of the following substances is required to dissolve the fibrin clot to achieve normal blood flow?","answers":[{"option":"Antithrombin III","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmin","bool":true},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Aminocaproic acid","bool":false}],"id":733},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In which of the following conditions does iron undergo oxidation from ferrous to the ferric form in hemoglobin?","answers":[{"option":"Anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia","bool":false},{"option":"Methemoglobinemia","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell disease","bool":false}],"id":734},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"Stages of child development were given by which of the following scientists?","answers":[{"option":"Sigmund Freud","bool":false},{"option":"Jean Paiget","bool":false},{"option":"Lawrence Kohlberg","bool":false},{"option":"Lev Vygotsky","bool":false},{"option":"Erik Erikson","bool":true}],"id":735},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2022"],"question":"In which location does a saddle embolus usually lodge?","answers":[{"option":"At the aortic arch","bool":false},{"option":"At the coronary artery","bool":false},{"option":"At the superior vena cava","bool":false},{"option":"At the bifurcation of the pulmonary artery","bool":true},{"option":"At the carotid artery","bool":false}],"id":736},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which one of the following types of cells starts their existence in the bone marrow, and gives rise to all blood cells on its own?","answers":[{"option":"Colony-forming unit-blast","bool":false},{"option":"Pluripotent hematopoietic stem cell","bool":true},{"option":"Colony-forming unit-spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Proerythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Colony-forming unit-erythrocytes","bool":false}],"id":737},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Why is blood classified as a special connective tissue?","answers":[{"option":"It consists of only fibers","bool":false},{"option":"It has a greater ratio of cells than fibers","bool":false},{"option":"It consists of hydroxyapatite crystals in its matrix","bool":false},{"option":"It is composed of cells and fibers","bool":false},{"option":"It has fluid nature of its ground substance","bool":true}],"id":738},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which one of the following is an unencapsulated lymphatic tissue found in the human body?","answers":[{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Tonsils","bool":false},{"option":"Peyer patches","bool":true},{"option":"Lymph node","bool":false},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false}],"id":739},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"In comparison to primitive hematopoiesis, which of the following is not the feature of definitive hematopoiesis (DH)?","answers":[{"option":"During definitive hematopoiesis, many types of white blood cells are produced","bool":false},{"option":"Definitive hematopoiesis is permanent","bool":false},{"option":"During definitive hematopoiesis, red blood cells do not have the nuclei","bool":true},{"option":"Definitive hematopoiesis starts in yolk sac","bool":false},{"option":"Definitive hematopoiesis begins in fetal life","bool":false}],"id":740},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A biopsy specimen of the thymus from an old man is examined under the microscope and many whorl-like corpuscles are observed. Which of the following statement truly matches the corpuscles mentioned above?","answers":[{"option":"They are mainly located in the thymic cortex","bool":false},{"option":"They have their embryological origin from mesoderm","bool":false},{"option":"They are derived from T memory cells","bool":false},{"option":"They are frequently seen in thymus of young individuals","bool":false},{"option":"They are composed of epithelial reticular cells (type VI)","bool":true}],"id":741},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following proteins stimulates the expansion and multiplication of nearly all types of stem cells?","answers":[{"option":"Granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF)","bool":false},{"option":"Granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF)","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-3 (IL-3)","bool":true},{"option":"Interleukin-6 (IL-6)","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophage colony-stimulating factor (M-CSF)","bool":false}],"id":742},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following cells does erythropoietin stimulate to enhance RBC synthesis?","answers":[{"option":"Pluripotent hematopoietic stem cell (PHSC)","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyles","bool":false},{"option":"Colony-forming unit-erythrocytes (CFU-E)","bool":true},{"option":"Basophil erythroblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Proerythroblast","bool":false}],"id":743},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following have MHC-I molecules present on their surfaces?","answers":[{"option":"Antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Coreceptors","bool":false},{"option":"T cell antigens","bool":false},{"option":"Processed foreign antigens","bool":false},{"option":"Processed self-antigens","bool":true}],"id":744},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A middle-aged obese doctor presents to the emergency room with complaints of significant left-sided chest \"tightness\" and pain that radiates to his left arm and jaw. He was given streptokinase when he was diagnosed with a heart attack four months back. The patient went into shock after receiving a fibrinolytic drug due to a hypersensitivity reaction. Which fibrinolytic agent did the patient receive this time?","answers":[{"option":"Tissue plasminogen activator","bool":false},{"option":"Alteplase","bool":false},{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":true},{"option":"Retaplase","bool":false},{"option":"Urokinase","bool":false}],"id":745},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following terms denotes the average weight of hemoglobin in an individual erythrocyte?","answers":[{"option":"Mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH)","bool":true},{"option":"Mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC)","bool":false},{"option":"Mean corpuscular volume (MCV)","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin index","bool":false},{"option":"Hematocrit","bool":false}],"id":746},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 40-year-old man was recovered after having walked for hours, two days after becoming lost in a sweltering and humid wilderness. His complete blood picture showed increased hematocrit. Which of the following is a likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Polycythemia vera","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary polycythemia","bool":false},{"option":"Primary polycythemia","bool":false},{"option":"Relative polycythemia","bool":true},{"option":"Physiological polycythemia","bool":false}],"id":747},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"The hematocrit of a person with a tumor-like disease is elevated. What value of hematocrit value would you most likely expect to see?","answers":[{"option":"More than 70%","bool":false},{"option":"More than 50%","bool":true},{"option":"Less than 30%","bool":false},{"option":"10% above normal","bool":false},{"option":"80% above normal","bool":false}],"id":748},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which one of the following values corresponds to the percentage of hemoglobin A2 (HbA₂) in a normal adult person?","answers":[{"option":"2.5 to 3.5%","bool":true},{"option":"0.5 to 0.8%","bool":false},{"option":"0.9 to 1.4%","bool":false},{"option":"4.5 to 5.5%","bool":false},{"option":"1.5 to 1.9%","bool":false}],"id":749},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 44-year-old man discovers he is positive for HIV after a blood donation screening. The screening of blood work shows hemoglobin of 10 g/dL, hematocrit 30%, total leukocyte count 4600/mm³, platelet count 15,000/mm³, prothrombin time 12 seconds (INR=1.1), and partial thromboplastin time 23 seconds. Which physical finding is most likely in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Subungual hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Deep venous thrombosis","bool":false},{"option":"Petechiae","bool":true},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Visceral hematoma","bool":false}],"id":750},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 44-year-old man is treated with high doses of rabbit anti-thymocyte globulin for bone marrow failure. He develops fever, lymphadenopathy, arthralgias, and erythema of the hands and feet arise ten days later. Which of the following is the most probable explanation for these signs and symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Polyclonal T-lymphocyte activation","bool":false},{"option":"Cytokine secretion by natural killer cells","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophil degranulation","bool":false},{"option":"Immune complex deposition in tissues","bool":true},{"option":"Widespread apoptosis of B lymphocytes","bool":false}],"id":751},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 20-year-old lady visits the doctor, after five years of significant menstrual bleeding. She complains of easy bruising and states that bleeding from a tiny finger cut lasts longer than normal. Lab results show a hemoglobin of 10.5g/dL, and a platelet count of 275,000/mm^3, with normal platelet aggregation. Prothrombin time is 10.5 seconds (INR = 1.0) and аctivated partial thromboplastin time is 28 sec. Pap smear shows no abnormalities. Which of the following hematologic disorders is the most likely cause of this patient's menorrhagia?","answers":[{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin K deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Afibrinogenemia","bool":false},{"option":"Intravascular coagulation","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false}],"id":752},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following features characterizes fetal hemoglobin compared to adult hemoglobin?","answers":[{"option":"It has delta polypeptide chain","bool":false},{"option":"It contains five pyrrole rings","bool":false},{"option":"It unloads oxygen to tissues with difficulty","bool":false},{"option":"It possesses more affinity for oxygen","bool":true},{"option":"It shows lesser oxygen content at a given partial pressure of oxygen","bool":false}],"id":753},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"After the breakdown of red blood cells, which of the following proteins binds hemoglobin to be cleared by liver macrophages?","answers":[{"option":"Hemopexin","bool":false},{"option":"Hepcidin","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":true},{"option":"Bilirubin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemin","bool":false}],"id":754},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 5-year-old child was brought to a clinic with complaints of high-grade fever, pain in the throat, and difficulty in swallowing. Examination and a blood test confirmed the diagnosis of acute bacterial infection of the tonsils. Which of the following cells would be increased in blood in this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false}],"id":755},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 68-year-old male with carcinoma of the lung was given subcutaneous heparin to prevent any intravascular coagulation. The activity of this anticoagulant is increased when it combines with a protein. Which one of the following proteins shows this effect?","answers":[{"option":"Protein C","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombomodulin","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand factor","bool":false},{"option":"Antithrombin III","bool":true},{"option":"Protein S","bool":false}],"id":756},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A young woman presents to the outpatient department with complaints of being exhausted and short of breath when she tries to do anything. She has a respiratory rate of 18 breaths per minute and is quite pale. Hemoglobin is 10 g/dL according to the lab results. What is the approximate amount of oxygen that is transported by each one hundred milliliters of her blood?","answers":[{"option":"15 mL","bool":false},{"option":"20 mL","bool":false},{"option":"10 mL","bool":false},{"option":"8 mL","bool":false},{"option":"13 mL","bool":true}],"id":757},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 65-year-old woman arrives at the orthopedic department with joint pain. Her doctor diagnoses her with osteoarthritis and osteoporosis. She is prescribed NSAIDs, calcium, and vitamin D. She returns after six months on the same medication, pale and short of breath. Her MCV is 73 fL and her hemoglobin was 9 g/dL. What could be the cause of low hemoglobin?","answers":[{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false}],"id":758},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 24-year-old Indian male arrives at the emergency room with severe chest and back pain that started three hours earlier while he was ascending a mountain and was short of breath. He states that he experienced identical symptoms several years earlier. Lab tests show that hemoglobin is 10 g/dL, total leukocyte count is 12,000/mm3, MCV is 87 fL, and reticulocytes are 25%. What could be his diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":true}],"id":759},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A manufacturing company worker who looks sick, feverish, and tired, complains of bleeding from the nose and gums. The laboratory findings show that the patient has low levels of hemoglobin, white blood cells, and platelets, as well as a low reticulocyte count and a mean corpuscular volume of 88 fL. What could be the potential diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false}],"id":760},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 27-year-old Ethiopian male presents to the outpatient department with breathlessness. He has a high heart rate and pale oral mucosa and conjunctiva. His initial blood tests showed 7.8 g/dL hemoglobin and 65 fL MCV. The doctor advises iron studies, which are normal. What could be the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":true},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false}],"id":761},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 24-year-old media sciences student presents with exhaustion, nausea, and vomiting for one week. She also has a low-grade fever and visited the outpatient department after observing yellow skin and sclera. Abdominal examination reveals right upper abdominal discomfort. Her liver tests are abnormal. She is diagnosed with hepatitis A after testing. Which immunity will she build from her acute viral infection?","answers":[{"option":"Innate immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Natural passive immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Artificial passive immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Natural active immunity","bool":true},{"option":"Artificial active immunity","bool":false}],"id":762},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A young man presented to the outpatient department with complaints of fever for 5 days and body aches. He has stable blood pressure, 103° C temperature, 110 beats/min pulse, and 20 breaths/min respiration. His total leukocyte count was 2500/μL. Which reflects his condition best?","answers":[{"option":"Leukemoid reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Leukopenia","bool":true},{"option":"Leukoplakia","bool":false}],"id":763},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Elevated concentration of lactate in the plasma is associated with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin D deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Myocardial infarction","bool":false},{"option":"Exercise-induced muscle fatigue","bool":true},{"option":"Dehydration","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false}],"id":764},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"When interpreting an iron profile, which of the following parameters is the most reliable indicator of iron deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Serum hepcidin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin levels","bool":true},{"option":"Serum iron levels","bool":false},{"option":"Total iron-binding capacity","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin saturation","bool":false}],"id":765},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the first bile pigment produced in the catabolism of heme molecule?","answers":[{"option":"Cholic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Deoxycholic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Biliverdin","bool":true},{"option":"Lithocholic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Bilirubin","bool":false}],"id":766},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"What is the net yield of ATP molecules produced by the glycolysis of one glucose molecule in red blood cells?","answers":[{"option":"36 ATP","bool":false},{"option":"0 ATP","bool":false},{"option":"6 ATP","bool":false},{"option":"2 ATP","bool":true},{"option":"1 ATP","bool":false}],"id":767},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which form of vitamin K is required for the activation of clotting factors?","answers":[{"option":"Menaquinone","bool":false},{"option":"Menadione","bool":false},{"option":"Dimenadione","bool":false},{"option":"Phylloquinone","bool":false},{"option":"Hydroquinone","bool":true}],"id":768},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"The plasma proteins electrophoresis shows two major protein electrophoretic bands, one for albumin and the other for globulin. Globulin further gives different fractions. These are α1 globulins, α2 globulin, β1 globulin, β2 globulin, and γ globulins. Which of the following is the protein present in the γ globulin fraction?","answers":[{"option":"Acid glycoprotein","bool":false},{"option":"Immunoglobulins","bool":true},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Ceruloplasmin","bool":false},{"option":"Transthyretin","bool":false}],"id":769},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"What is the most characteristic feature of granulation tissue?","answers":[{"option":"Presence of monocytes and fibroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Resemblance to granuloma","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of neutrophils and macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Growth of fibroblasts and new capillaries","bool":true},{"option":"Presence of exudate","bool":false}],"id":770},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 41-year-old man comes into the medical outpatient department with complaints of weight loss, nausea, and vomiting for 5 months. He works at a factory that produces plastic pipes. On physical examination, he has tenderness to palpation in the right upper quadrant of the abdomen with hepatomegaly. An abdominal CT scan shows a 12 cm mass in the right lobe of the liver. A liver biopsy is performed, and a microscopic examination shows an angiosarcoma. The patient has most likely been exposed to which of the following agents?","answers":[{"option":"Benzene","bool":false},{"option":"Vinyl chloride","bool":true},{"option":"Beryllium","bool":false},{"option":"Asbestos","bool":false},{"option":"Arsenic","bool":false}],"id":771},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 25-year-old male patient visited the outpatient department with complaints of shortness of breath at rest. His chest is normal on auscultation and there are no visible signs of lung disease on X-ray. He has low hemoglobin and an MCV of 105 fL based on his blood tests. Multisegmented neutrophils are not seen on blood smear. What could be the cause of his anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Liver disease","bool":true},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":772},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"An 18-year-old male comes to the outpatient department with a palpable mass on the right side of his neck for 6 months. On physical examination, there is a 2 cm, firm, non-tender nodule involving the right lobe of the thyroid gland. Biopsy specimens of the nodule showed features consistent with carcinoma of the thyroid. No positive family history was found. Which of the following is relevant in the woman's past medical history?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic alcoholism","bool":false},{"option":"Exposure to arsenic compounds","bool":false},{"option":"Blunt trauma from a fall","bool":false},{"option":"Radiation therapy in childhood","bool":true},{"option":"Ataxia telangiectasia","bool":false}],"id":773},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 52-year-old man noted a darkly pigmented \"mole\" on the back of his hand. During the past month, the lesion has gradually enlarged and bled spontaneously. On examination, there is a slightly raised, darkly pigmented, 1.2 cm lesion on the dorsum of the right hand. The lesion is completely excised. Microscopically, malignant melanoma is diagnosed. Which of the following factors is associated with the greatest risk for the development of this neoplasm?","answers":[{"option":"Smoking tobacco","bool":false},{"option":"Ultraviolet radiation","bool":true},{"option":"Asbestos exposure","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotherapy","bool":false},{"option":"Allergy to latex","bool":false}],"id":774},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 58-year-old woman experienced an increased feeling of fullness in the neck for the past 3 months and noted a 3 kg weight loss during that time. On physical examination, there is a firm, fixed mass in a 3 × 5 cm area on the right side of the neck. A biopsy of the mass is performed. All areas of the tumor have similar morphology. Which of the following terms best describes this neoplasm?","answers":[{"option":"Adenoma","bool":false},{"option":"Leiomyoma","bool":false},{"option":"Well-differentiated adenocarcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Anaplastic carcinoma","bool":true},{"option":"Squamous cell carcinoma","bool":false}],"id":775},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Malignant neoplasms can be categorized as carcinomas and sarcomas. Which of the following statements describes carcinoma?","answers":[{"option":"Arising exclusively from the cells of mesodermal origin","bool":false},{"option":"Arising from sheets of solid mesenchyme","bool":false},{"option":"Arising exclusively from the epithelium","bool":true},{"option":"Arising exclusively from the cells of ectodermal origin","bool":false},{"option":"Arising exclusively from the cells of endodermal origin","bool":false}],"id":776},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 26-year-old woman has a lump in her left breast. On physical examination, the physician finds an irregular, firm, 2 cm mass in the upper inner quadrant of the breast. A fine-needle aspirate of the mass shows carcinoma. The patient's 30-year-old sister was recently diagnosed with ovarian cancer, and 3 years ago her maternal aunt was diagnosed with ductal carcinoma of the breast and had a mastectomy. Which of the following genes is most likely to have undergone mutation to produce these findings","answers":[{"option":"ERBB2 (growth factor receptor gene)","bool":false},{"option":"BCL2 (anti-apoptosis gene)","bool":false},{"option":"BRCA1 (DNA repair gene)","bool":true},{"option":"HSTI (fibroblast growth factor gene)","bool":false},{"option":"EGF (epidermal growth factor gene)","bool":false}],"id":777},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A first-year medical student develops pneumonia and is in the hospital for a week. Two weeks after hospital discharge, he develops a fever and begins coughing up thick, whitish, foul-smelling sputum. Computed tomography (CT) scan chest shows a localized collection of thick fluid in the lung. How would you best describe the outcome of acute inflammation in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Resolution","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Abscess formation","bool":true},{"option":"Granuloma formation","bool":false},{"option":"Ulcer formation","bool":false}],"id":778},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"What term best describes the type of inflammation in a 4-year-old child with redness and blister formation on the hands after accidental contact with boiling water?","answers":[{"option":"Serous","bool":true},{"option":"Suppurative","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinous","bool":false},{"option":"Granulomatous","bool":false},{"option":"Ulcerative","bool":false}],"id":779},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which statement best describes autosomal dominant disorders?","answers":[{"option":"Protein shows loss of function","bool":false},{"option":"New mutations detected early clinically","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced penetrance and variable expressivity","bool":true},{"option":"Onset usually early in life","bool":false},{"option":"Disease in homozygous state","bool":false}],"id":780},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"An affected male does not transmit the disorder to his sons, but all daughters are carriers. Which pattern of inheritance corresponds to the above statement?","answers":[{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":true},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Sex chromosome abnormality","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false}],"id":781},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which cell type is most likely to be increased in a first year medical student experiencing excessive sneezing and watering of the eyes every year during spring and summer?","answers":[{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false}],"id":782},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 34-year-old man complains of epigastric pain. Endoscopy reveals a shallow sharply demarcated ulcer in the gastric antrum. Biopsy findings include lymphocyte, macrophage, and plasma cell infiltration, along with granulation tissue formation and fibrosis. What term best describes the type of inflammation observed in this man?","answers":[{"option":"Acute","bool":false},{"option":"Serous","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic","bool":true},{"option":"Fibrinous","bool":false},{"option":"Granulomatous","bool":false}],"id":783},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"What does the membrane attack complex (MAC) formed during complement activation consist of?","answers":[{"option":"C5b, C6, C7, C8, and C9","bool":true},{"option":"C1, C2, C4 and C6","bool":false},{"option":"C5a and C5b","bool":false},{"option":"C1, C3b, and C4b","bool":false},{"option":"C3a, C3b, and C5b","bool":false}],"id":784},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"What initiates the classical pathway of complement activation?","answers":[{"option":"Antigen-antibody complexes","bool":true},{"option":"Binding of mannose-binding lectin (MBL) to microbial surfaces","bool":false},{"option":"Breakdown of C3","bool":false},{"option":"Binding of C-reactive protein (CRP) to microbial surfaces","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of C3 convertase","bool":false}],"id":785},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is correct regarding the inflammation in a 65-year-old man with a 5-year history of osteoarthritis?","answers":[{"option":"Cytokines and growth factors having no role in this type of inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Granuloma formation as a constant feature in these patients","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophilic exudate with pus formation on biopsy","bool":false},{"option":"Alternatively activated macrophages promoting tissue repair","bool":true},{"option":"Plasma cells and B lymphocytes being almost never found","bool":false}],"id":786},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Complement deficiencies lead to an increased risk of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Allergic reactions","bool":false},{"option":"Hypergammaglobulinemia","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune diseases","bool":false},{"option":"Hypersensitivity","bool":false},{"option":"Bacterial infections","bool":true}],"id":787},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"What is the involvement of the major histocompatibility complex (MHC)?","answers":[{"option":"Muscle contraction","bool":false},{"option":"Blood clotting","bool":false},{"option":"Neurotransmitter release","bool":false},{"option":"Hormone regulation","bool":false},{"option":"Transplant rejection","bool":true}],"id":788},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"In a normal distribution curve, what percentage of the curve is represented by the shaded area under the curve with ±1 SD (plus minus one standard deviation around the mean) on either side of the mean value?","answers":[{"option":"45%","bool":false},{"option":"13%","bool":false},{"option":"68%","bool":true},{"option":"27%","bool":false},{"option":"50%","bool":false}],"id":789},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"What does sterilization refer to?","answers":[{"option":"Reducing the number of microorganisms to a safe level","bool":false},{"option":"Removing visible dirt from a surface","bool":false},{"option":"Killing or removing all forms of microbial life","bool":true},{"option":"Killing bacteria but not viruses","bool":false},{"option":"Inactivating viruses on a surface","bool":false}],"id":790},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"What is the most resistant form of microbial life to physical and chemical agents?","answers":[{"option":"Viruses","bool":false},{"option":"Gram-negative bacteria","bool":false},{"option":"Fungal spores","bool":false},{"option":"Bacterial endospores","bool":true},{"option":"Protozoan cysts","bool":false}],"id":791},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"What do agents referred to as \"bactericidal\" do?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibit bacterial growth","bool":false},{"option":"Inactivate bacterial toxins","bool":false},{"option":"Remove bacteria from the surface","bool":false},{"option":"Kill bacteria","bool":true},{"option":"Prevent bacterial attachment","bool":false}],"id":792},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 19-year-old woman came into the medical outpatient department with a history of frequent nosebleeds and increased menstrual flow. On physical examination, petechiae and purpura are present on the skin of her extremities. Laboratory studies show normal partial thromboplastin time (APTT), prothrombin time (PT), platelet count, and decreased von Willebrand factor activity. This patient most likely has a derangement in which of the following steps in hemostasis?","answers":[{"option":"Vasoconstriction","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet adhesion","bool":true},{"option":"Prothrombin generation","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet aggregation","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin inhibition","bool":false}],"id":793},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 23-year-old pregnant woman has macrocytic anemia, an increased serum concentration of transferrin, and a normal serum concentration of vitamin B12. The most likely cause of her anemia is a deficiency of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Iron","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Intrinsic factor","bool":false},{"option":"Cobalamin","bool":false},{"option":"Erythropoietin","bool":false}],"id":794},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 20-year-old woman presents to her primary care physician with heavy menstrual bleeding. Her physician prescribes tranexamic acid. What is tranexamic acid's mechanism of action?","answers":[{"option":"Activates plasminogen","bool":false},{"option":"Blocks cyclooxygenase","bool":false},{"option":"Activates platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Suppresses LH surge","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibits plasmin","bool":true}],"id":795},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A medical study is conducted to estimate the prevalence of hypertension amongst a defined population and evaluate people of different ages, ethnicities, geographical locations, and social backgrounds. Which one of the following options best describes the type of study design most appropriate for the above study?","answers":[{"option":"Correlational","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort","bool":false},{"option":"Case-series","bool":false},{"option":"Cross-sectional","bool":true},{"option":"Case-control","bool":false}],"id":796},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"In a study that began in 2001, a group of 3500 adults in Islamabad were asked about\r\nalcohol consumption. The occurrence of cases of liver cancer between 2018-2023 was\r\nstudied in this group. What is the above study design?","answers":[{"option":"Case series","bool":false},{"option":"Cross-sectional","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort","bool":true},{"option":"Correlational","bool":false},{"option":"Case-control","bool":false}],"id":797},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A research paper states that: \"To access the frequency of mood disorders among medical students of Karachi.\" Which of the following best describes the statement in the above scenario?","answers":[{"option":"Operational definitions","bool":false},{"option":"Hypothesis","bool":false},{"option":"Rationale","bool":false},{"option":"Topic","bool":false},{"option":"Objective","bool":true}],"id":798},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"In a small study, 12 women with ovarian cancer and 12 women with no apparent disease were asked whether they had ever used estrogen. Each woman with cancer was matched by age, race, weight, and parity to a woman without disease. Identify the study design.","answers":[{"option":"Case-control","bool":true},{"option":"Case report","bool":false},{"option":"Cross-sectional","bool":false},{"option":"Ecological","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort","bool":false}],"id":799},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"\"Like cases should be treated as like, and the benefits and the risks associated with research must be allocated equitably across patients.\" Which of the following best expresses this principle of medical ethics?","answers":[{"option":"Autonomy","bool":false},{"option":"Beneficence","bool":false},{"option":"Justice","bool":true},{"option":"Equality","bool":false},{"option":"Non-maleficence","bool":false}],"id":800},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A group of medical students started researching the health issues and quality of life of commercial sex workers. For data collection, they would have to go to various unsuitable places. They spent a year trying to collect data but enrolled a dozen participants. They became discouraged and left the study altogether. Which of the following options best describes the factor ignored by the students while deciding the research topic?","answers":[{"option":"Economics","bool":false},{"option":"Preventability","bool":false},{"option":"Feasibility","bool":true},{"option":"Magnitude","bool":false},{"option":"Politics","bool":false}],"id":801},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A researcher of a new drug trial informed the volunteers about the possible benefits of a new drug under trial in that study. She deliberately laid more emphasis on the possible benefits of the drug under trial and avoided discussion of the possible adverse effects of the drug to enrolled participants to increase participation. Which of the following identifies the central ethical principle lacking in the above scenario?","answers":[{"option":"Beneficence","bool":false},{"option":"Justice","bool":false},{"option":"Non-maleficence","bool":true},{"option":"Informed consent","bool":false},{"option":"Confidentiality","bool":false}],"id":802},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 25-year-old male patient presents with a history of irrelevant talks, anger, and suspicion towards family members, had a big fight with the family, and injured the younger with an iron rod. He has been brought to you for treatment. Which of the following would you consider before initiating an interview with him?","answers":[{"option":"Inquire about any danger objects with the patient","bool":true},{"option":"Ask the staff to hold the patient and sedate him immediately","bool":false},{"option":"Talk to the family and ask them to leave the patient alone","bool":false},{"option":"Talk to the security guard and restraint the patient forcefully","bool":false},{"option":"Wait for the patient's violent reaction to happen in the ward","bool":false}],"id":803},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"During the case discussion in the ward, you noticed that the safety measures in place for your junior doctor, who is responsible for taking psychiatric history from a violent patient, are inadequate.  What would you advise your junior doctor?","answers":[{"option":"Safety is not important as compared to the patient's illness","bool":false},{"option":"Reassure your junior doctor and ask her to take a complete history","bool":false},{"option":"Ignore the family’s account of the patient and his violent acts","bool":false},{"option":"Postpone the interview until all safety measures have been ensured","bool":true},{"option":"Wait for 72 hours to take the history from the patient","bool":false}],"id":804},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 22-year-old male presented to the outpatient department with a complaint of swelling in the neck region for 10-12 days. He does not give any history of flu or sore throat. Physical examination revealed right anterior cervical lymph nodes, about 1.0 cm in size., soft, non-tender, and mobile i.e. not fixed. The spleen is also enlarged. There is no other positive finding. What should be the next step in the management of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Lymph node biopsy","bool":true},{"option":"Reassure the patient and send him home","bool":false},{"option":"Antibiotics/antivirals","bool":false},{"option":"Observe the patient for 3-4 weeks","bool":false},{"option":"Send viral serology/VDRL/PCR","bool":false}],"id":805},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Hemostasis is the natural process that stops blood loss when an injury occurs. Which of the following bleeding manifestations or associations suggests secondary hemostatic disorder?","answers":[{"option":"Distensible skin and lax joints","bool":false},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Bruising","bool":false},{"option":"Epistaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Mucocutaneous bleed","bool":false}],"id":806},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 65-year-old male presents with a 2 months history of fever, lethargy, and night\r\nsweats. On physical examination, he has palpable cervical and axillary lymph nodes. The spleen is palpable 2 cm below the left costal margin. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Viral fever","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Metastatic cancer","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":true}],"id":807},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"A 62-year-old woman complains of fatigue and numbness in her arms and legs for 1 month and takes thyroid replacement therapy for hypothyroidism. She has a long history of diarrhea on and off. A complete blood count (CBC) shows white blood cells (WBC) 3.8x10^9/L (normal: 4.0 to 11 x 10^9/L), hemoglobin (Hb) 8g/dL (normal: 12 to 16g/dL), hematocrit (Hct) 27 percent (normal: 36 to 46 percent), mean corpuscular volume (MCV) 120 fL (normal: 80 to 100fL), and platelets 115x109/L (normal: 150 to 400x10^9/L). She is diagnosed as a case of megaloblastic anemia with vitamin B12 deficiency. Which of the following autoantibodies is most likely present in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Antigliadin antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Antimitochondrial antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Anticentromere antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-intrinsic factor antibodies","bool":true},{"option":"Antismooth muscle antibodies","bool":false}],"id":808},{"info":["1st-year/blood/compiled","1st-year/blood/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is a characteristic of megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Bone marrow will be hypercellular","bool":true},{"option":"Serum iron will be reduced","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyte count will be increased","bool":false},{"option":"Serum vitamin B12 will be increased","bool":false},{"option":"TIBC will be increased","bool":false}],"id":809}]
export default arr